<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-10-09T17:27:39-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Victoria Gitman</title><entry><title type="html">Model theoretic characterizations of large cardinals revisited</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publications/2020/10/09/model-theoretic-characterizations-of-large-cardinals-revisited.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Model theoretic characterizations of large cardinals revisited" /><published>2020-10-09T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-10-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publications/2020/10/09/model-theoretic-characterizations-of-large-cardinals-revisited</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publications/2020/10/09/model-theoretic-characterizations-of-large-cardinals-revisited.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;BoneyDimopoulosGitmanMagidor:AbstractLogics&quot;&gt;W. Boney, S. Dimopoulos, V. Gitman, and M. Magidor, “Model theoretic characterizations of large cardinals revisited,” &lt;i&gt;Manuscript&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The compactness of strong logics and set theory have been intertwined since Tarski &lt;a href=&quot;#Tarski:compactness&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; defined (weakly and strongly) compact cardinals in terms of the properties of the infinitary logic $\mathbb L_{\kappa, \omega}$. This established a strong connection between abstract model theory and the theory of large cardinals, which has also become apparent by the recent breakthroughs in the theory of Abstract Elementary Classes-a purely model theoretic framework-where certain important results depend on the existence of large cardinal axioms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The interaction between the two fields is also strengthened by the first author's article &lt;a href=&quot;#Boney:ModelTheoreticCharacterizationsOfLargeCardinals&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;, which establishes new characterizations of established large cardinal notions, expressed in model theoretic terms as compactness properties. This paper is a sequel to &lt;a href=&quot;#Boney:ModelTheoreticCharacterizationsOfLargeCardinals&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt; and characterizes more large cardinals this way, namely Woodin, various virtual large cardinals and subtle cardinals. Notably, this has led us to generalise or define new concepts in abstract model theory, that may be useful outside the scope of the current exposition. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the main philosophical open questions about the large cardinal hierarchy is to explain the fact that it appears to be linear. Hence, apart from the intrinsic interest, we believe that the framework of compactness principles that we invoke offers a new insight into this problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We give a model-theoretic characterisation of Woodin cardinals by introducing a notion of Henkin models for arbitrary abstract logics. We characterise various virtual large cardinals, by introducing the notion of a pseudo-model for a theory. Finally, we characterise (a class version of) subtle cardinals as a natural weakening of Vopěnka's principle by showing that if ${\rm Ord}$ is subtle, then every abstract logic has a stationary class of weak compactness cardinals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The conversations leading to this paper began at the conference &quot;Accessible categories and their connections&quot; organized by Andrew Brooke-Taylor, and we would like to thank Brooke-Taylor for organizing a fascinating meeting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Tarski:compactness&quot;&gt;A. Tarski, “Some problems and results relevant to the foundations of set theory,” in &lt;i&gt;Logic, Methodology and Philosophy of Science, Proceedings of the 1960 International Congress&lt;/i&gt;, 1962. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Boney:ModelTheoreticCharacterizationsOfLargeCardinals&quot;&gt;W. Boney, “Model theoretic characterizations of large cardinals,” &lt;i&gt;Israel J. Math.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 236, no. 1, pp. 133–181, 2020. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1007/s11856-020-1971-6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">{% reference page.ref %} The compactness of strong logics and set theory have been intertwined since Tarski {% cite Tarski:compactness %} defined (weakly and strongly) compact cardinals in terms of the properties of the infinitary logic $\mathbb L_{\kappa, \omega}$. This established a strong connection between abstract model theory and the theory of large cardinals, which has also become apparent by the recent breakthroughs in the theory of Abstract Elementary Classes-a purely model theoretic framework-where certain important results depend on the existence of large cardinal axioms. The interaction between the two fields is also strengthened by the first author's article {% cite Boney:ModelTheoreticCharacterizationsOfLargeCardinals %}, which establishes new characterizations of established large cardinal notions, expressed in model theoretic terms as compactness properties. This paper is a sequel to {% cite Boney:ModelTheoreticCharacterizationsOfLargeCardinals %} and characterizes more large cardinals this way, namely Woodin, various virtual large cardinals and subtle cardinals. Notably, this has led us to generalise or define new concepts in abstract model theory, that may be useful outside the scope of the current exposition. One of the main philosophical open questions about the large cardinal hierarchy is to explain the fact that it appears to be linear. Hence, apart from the intrinsic interest, we believe that the framework of compactness principles that we invoke offers a new insight into this problem. We give a model-theoretic characterisation of Woodin cardinals by introducing a notion of Henkin models for arbitrary abstract logics. We characterise various virtual large cardinals, by introducing the notion of a pseudo-model for a theory. Finally, we characterise (a class version of) subtle cardinals as a natural weakening of Vopěnka's principle by showing that if ${\rm Ord}$ is subtle, then every abstract logic has a stationary class of weak compactness cardinals. The conversations leading to this paper began at the conference &quot;Accessible categories and their connections&quot; organized by Andrew Brooke-Taylor, and we would like to thank Brooke-Taylor for organizing a fascinating meeting. References {% bibliography --cited %}</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The virtual large cardinal hierarchy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publications/2020/09/08/the-virtual-large-cardinal-hierarchy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The virtual large cardinal hierarchy" /><published>2020-09-08T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-09-08T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publications/2020/09/08/the-virtual-large-cardinal-hierarchy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publications/2020/09/08/the-virtual-large-cardinal-hierarchy.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;GitmanNielsenDimopoulos:virtualHierarchy&quot;&gt;V. Gitman, S. Dimopoulos, and D. S. Nielsen, “The virtual large cardinal hierarchy,” &lt;i&gt;Manuscript&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study of generic large cardinals, being cardinals that are critical points of elementary embeddings existing in generic extensions, goes back to the 1970's. At that time, the primary interest was the existence of &lt;em&gt;precipitous&lt;/em&gt; and &lt;em&gt;saturated&lt;/em&gt; ideals on small cardinals like $\omega_1$ and $\omega_2$. Research in this area later moved to the study of more general generic embeddings, both defined on $V$, but also on rank-initial segments of $V$ - these were investigated by e.g. &lt;a href=&quot;#DonderLevinski:OnWeaklyPrecipitousFilters&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;#FerberGitik:OnAlmostPrecipitousIdeals&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The move to &lt;em&gt;virtual&lt;/em&gt; large cardinals happened when &lt;a href=&quot;#schindler:remarkable1&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt; introduced the &lt;em&gt;remarkable cardinals&lt;/em&gt;, which it turned out later were precisely a virtualization of supercompactness. Various other virtual large cardinals were first investigated in &lt;a href=&quot;#GitmanSchindler:virtualCardinals&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;. The key difference between virtual large cardinals and generic versions of large cardinals studied earlier is that in the virtual case we require the embedding to be between sets with the target model being a subset of the ground model. These assumptions imply that virtual large cardinals are actual large cardinals: they are at least ineffable, but small enough to exist in $L$. These large cardinals are special because they allow us to work with embeddings as in the higher reaches of the large cardinal hierarchy while being consistent with $V=L$, which enables equiconsistencies at these &quot;lower levels&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To take a few examples, &lt;a href=&quot;#schindler:remarkable1&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt; has shown that the existence of a remarkable cardinal is equiconsistent with the statement that the theory of $L(\mathbb R)$ cannot be changed by proper forcing, which was improved to semi-proper forcing in &lt;a href=&quot;#schindler:remarkable2&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href=&quot;#Wilson:VopenkaCardinalsZFSuslinSets&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt; has shown that the existence of a virtually Vopěnka cardinal is equiconsistent with the hypothesis
$$
  {\rm ZF}+ \ulcorner\text{${\bf\Sigma}^1_2$ is the class of all $\omega_1$-Suslin sets}\urcorner + \Theta = \omega_2,
$$

and &lt;a href=&quot;#SchindlerWilson:perfectSetPropertyUniversallyBaire&quot;&gt;[7]&lt;/a&gt; has shown that the existence of a virtually Shelah cardinal is equiconsistent with the hypothesis
$$
  {\rm ZF} + \ulcorner\text{every universally Baire set of reals has the perfect set property}\urcorner.
$$

&lt;p&gt;Kunen's Inconsistency fails for virtual large cardinals in the sense that a forcing extension can have elementary embeddings $j:V_\alpha^V\to V_\alpha^V$ with $\alpha$ much larger than the supremum of the critical sequence. In the theory of large cardinals, Kunen's Inconsistency is for instance used to prove that requiring that $j(\kappa)&gt;\lambda$ in the definition of $\kappa$ being $\lambda$-strong is superfluous. It turns out that the use of Kunen's Inconsistency in that argument is actually essential because versions of virtual strongness with and without that condition are not equivalent. The same holds for virtual versions of other large cardinals where this condition is used in the embeddings characterization. Each of these virtual large cardinals therefore has two non-equivalent versions, with and without the condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we continue the study of virtual versions of various large cardinals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We establish some new relationships between virtual large cardinals that were previously studied. We prove the Gitman-Schindler result, alluded to in &lt;a href=&quot;#GitmanSchindler:virtualCardinals&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;, that virtualizations of strong and supercompact cardinals are equivalent to remarkability. We show how the existence of virtual supercompact cardinals without the $j(\kappa)&gt;\lambda$ condition is related to the existence of virtually rank-into-rank cardinals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We study virtual versions of Woodin and Vop\v enka cardinals. We show that inaccessible cardinals are virtually Vopěnka if and only if they are &lt;em&gt;faintly pre-Woodin&lt;/em&gt;, a weakening of the virtual notion of Woodinness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We study a virtual version of &lt;em&gt;Berkeley&lt;/em&gt; cardinals, a large cardinal known to be inconsistent with ${\rm ZFC}$. We show that the existence of a virtually Berkeley cardinal is equivalent to ${\rm Ord}$ being virtually pre-Woodin but not virtually Woodin, and also equivalent to the virtual Vopěnka principle holding while ${\rm Ord}$ is not Mahlo, improving on a result of &lt;a href=&quot;#GitmanHamkins:GVP&quot;&gt;[8]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;DonderLevinski:OnWeaklyPrecipitousFilters&quot;&gt;H.-D. Donder and J.-P. Levinski, “On weakly precipitous filters,” &lt;i&gt;Israel J. Math.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 67, no. 2, pp. 225–242, 1989. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1007/BF02937297&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;FerberGitik:OnAlmostPrecipitousIdeals&quot;&gt;A. Ferber and M. Gitik, “On almost precipitous ideals,” &lt;i&gt;Arch. Math. Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 49, no. 3, pp. 301–328, 2010. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1007/s00153-009-0173-z&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;schindler:remarkable1&quot;&gt;R.-D. Schindler, “Proper forcing and remarkable cardinals,” &lt;i&gt;Bull. Symbolic Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 6, no. 2, pp. 176–184, 2000. Available at: http://dx.doi.org.ezproxy.gc.cuny.edu/10.2307/421205&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;GitmanSchindler:virtualCardinals&quot;&gt;V. Gitman and R. Schindler, “Virtual large cardinals,” &lt;i&gt;Ann. Pure Appl. Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 169, no. 12, pp. 1317–1334, 2018. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apal.2018.08.005&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;schindler:remarkable2&quot;&gt;R.-D. Schindler, “Proper forcing and remarkable cardinals. II,” &lt;i&gt;J. Symbolic Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 66, no. 3, pp. 1481–1492, 2001. Available at: http://dx.doi.org.ezproxy.gc.cuny.edu/10.2307/2695120&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Wilson:VopenkaCardinalsZFSuslinSets&quot;&gt;T. Wilson, “Generic Vopěnka cardinals and models of ZF with few $\aleph_1$-Suslin sets,” &lt;i&gt;Archive for Mathematical Logic&lt;/i&gt;, pp. 1–16, 2019. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;SchindlerWilson:perfectSetPropertyUniversallyBaire&quot;&gt;R. Schindler and T. Wilson, “The consistency strength of the perfect set property for universally Baire sets of reals,” &lt;i&gt;Manuscript&lt;/i&gt;, 2018. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;GitmanHamkins:GVP&quot;&gt;V. Gitman and J. D. Hamkins, “A model of the generic Vopěnka principle in which the
              ordinals are not Mahlo,” &lt;i&gt;Arch. Math. Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 58, no. 1-2, pp. 245–265, 2019. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1007/s00153-018-0632-5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">{% reference page.ref %} The study of generic large cardinals, being cardinals that are critical points of elementary embeddings existing in generic extensions, goes back to the 1970's. At that time, the primary interest was the existence of precipitous and saturated ideals on small cardinals like $\omega_1$ and $\omega_2$. Research in this area later moved to the study of more general generic embeddings, both defined on $V$, but also on rank-initial segments of $V$ - these were investigated by e.g. {% cite DonderLevinski:OnWeaklyPrecipitousFilters %} and {% cite FerberGitik:OnAlmostPrecipitousIdeals %}. The move to virtual large cardinals happened when {% cite schindler:remarkable1 %} introduced the remarkable cardinals, which it turned out later were precisely a virtualization of supercompactness. Various other virtual large cardinals were first investigated in {% cite GitmanSchindler:virtualCardinals %}. The key difference between virtual large cardinals and generic versions of large cardinals studied earlier is that in the virtual case we require the embedding to be between sets with the target model being a subset of the ground model. These assumptions imply that virtual large cardinals are actual large cardinals: they are at least ineffable, but small enough to exist in $L$. These large cardinals are special because they allow us to work with embeddings as in the higher reaches of the large cardinal hierarchy while being consistent with $V=L$, which enables equiconsistencies at these &quot;lower levels&quot;. To take a few examples, {% cite schindler:remarkable1 %} has shown that the existence of a remarkable cardinal is equiconsistent with the statement that the theory of $L(\mathbb R)$ cannot be changed by proper forcing, which was improved to semi-proper forcing in {% cite schindler:remarkable2 %}. {% cite Wilson:VopenkaCardinalsZFSuslinSets %} has shown that the existence of a virtually Vopěnka cardinal is equiconsistent with the hypothesis $$ {\rm ZF}+ \ulcorner\text{${\bf\Sigma}^1_2$ is the class of all $\omega_1$-Suslin sets}\urcorner + \Theta = \omega_2, $$ and {% cite SchindlerWilson:perfectSetPropertyUniversallyBaire %} has shown that the existence of a virtually Shelah cardinal is equiconsistent with the hypothesis $$ {\rm ZF} + \ulcorner\text{every universally Baire set of reals has the perfect set property}\urcorner. $$ Kunen's Inconsistency fails for virtual large cardinals in the sense that a forcing extension can have elementary embeddings $j:V_\alpha^V\to V_\alpha^V$ with $\alpha$ much larger than the supremum of the critical sequence. In the theory of large cardinals, Kunen's Inconsistency is for instance used to prove that requiring that $j(\kappa)&gt;\lambda$ in the definition of $\kappa$ being $\lambda$-strong is superfluous. It turns out that the use of Kunen's Inconsistency in that argument is actually essential because versions of virtual strongness with and without that condition are not equivalent. The same holds for virtual versions of other large cardinals where this condition is used in the embeddings characterization. Each of these virtual large cardinals therefore has two non-equivalent versions, with and without the condition. In this paper, we continue the study of virtual versions of various large cardinals. We establish some new relationships between virtual large cardinals that were previously studied. We prove the Gitman-Schindler result, alluded to in {% cite GitmanSchindler:virtualCardinals %}, that virtualizations of strong and supercompact cardinals are equivalent to remarkability. We show how the existence of virtual supercompact cardinals without the $j(\kappa)&gt;\lambda$ condition is related to the existence of virtually rank-into-rank cardinals. We study virtual versions of Woodin and Vop\v enka cardinals. We show that inaccessible cardinals are virtually Vopěnka if and only if they are faintly pre-Woodin, a weakening of the virtual notion of Woodinness. We study a virtual version of Berkeley cardinals, a large cardinal known to be inconsistent with ${\rm ZFC}$. We show that the existence of a virtually Berkeley cardinal is equivalent to ${\rm Ord}$ being virtually pre-Woodin but not virtually Woodin, and also equivalent to the virtual Vopěnka principle holding while ${\rm Ord}$ is not Mahlo, improving on a result of {% cite GitmanHamkins:GVP %}. References {% bibliography --cited %}</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Abstract Logics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/research/2020/08/10/abstract-logics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Abstract Logics" /><published>2020-08-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-08-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/research/2020/08/10/abstract-logics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/research/2020/08/10/abstract-logics.html">&lt;p&gt;Since the early 20th century, logicians have formalized the study of mathematical structures in the system of first-order logic. But first-order logic itself, the so-called meta-theory of mathematics, does not exist outside of mathematics. It depends on the ambient set-theoretic background in which we choose to work, or at the minimum on some weak fragment of it codifying the properties of natural numbers. Using more of the available set-theoretic background we can define much stronger logics through which we gain access to more advanced properties of mathematical structures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what is a logic? Roughly speaking, a logic is an assignment to every mathematical language of a collection of formulas together with a satisfaction relation which tells us which formulas a given structure in a given language satisfies. We are all familiar with first-order logic's recursive definition of formulas and Tarski's satisfaction. Formulas and satisfaction in other logics can be much stranger in nature and they usually gain us much more access to the set-theoretic properties of structures. By a language, here, we simply mean a collection of functions, relations, and constants. I will give a formal definition of &lt;em&gt;logic&lt;/em&gt; in a little bit, but I think it is more instructive to start with some examples of different logics and their properties.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two very basic properties of first-order logic which we take for granted are (1) that there are set-many formulas for every fixed language and (2) that any single formula can mention only finitely much of the language. Although these properties are obvious enough in this case, it turns out that they are fairly important for abstracting away to the desired properties of tractable abstract logics. One of the most useful, surprising, and significant properties of first-order logic is ($\omega$-)compactness, the assertion that if every finite fragment of a theory has a model, then so does the whole theory. Compactness tends to fail for stronger logics, but depending on the existence of large cardinals, they will satisfy $\kappa$-compactness for some cardinal $\kappa$, meaning that if every ${&lt;}\kappa$-sized fragment of a theory has a model, then so will the whole theory. If a logic is $\kappa$-compact, we will say that $\kappa$ is a &lt;em&gt;strong compactness cardinal&lt;/em&gt; for the logic. We will say that $\kappa$ is a &lt;em&gt;weak compactness cardinal&lt;/em&gt; if $\kappa$-compactness holds for theories of size $\kappa$. Set theorists and model theorists, going back to Tarski, have uncovered a very close connection between large cardinals and compactness cardinals for strong logics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In first-order logic we can take finite conjunctions and disjunctions of formulas. Using more of the set-theoretic background, we can strengthen first-order logic to allow conjunctions and disjunctions of size less than $\delta$ for some cardinal $\delta$. This gives rise to a family of logics indexed by cardinals $\delta$, the $\mathbb L_{\delta,\omega}$ logics. The weakest such logic $\mathbb L_{\omega_1,\omega}$ allows  countable-length conjunctions and disjunctions of formulas. A formula of $\mathbb L_{\delta,\omega}$ can mention a $\gamma$-sized chunk of a language for any $\gamma&lt;\delta$, so we are no longer restricted to only finitely much of the language appearing in a single formula. In $\mathbb L_{\omega_1,\omega}$, we can express, for instance, that there are no nonstandard natural numbers by saying that if $n$ is a natural number, then $$n=0\vee n=1\vee n=2\vee\cdots.$$ We can express that a given first-order type is realized or omitted, by saying that there is/isn't an element satisfying the infinite conjunction of formulas in this type. We can express that a model is recursively saturated because there are only countably many recursive types. More generally, in a logic $\mathbb L_{\delta,\omega}$, for every ordinal $\xi&lt;\delta$, there is a formula $\varphi_\xi(x)$ in a language with a binary relation $E$, which expresses that $(x,E)$ is isomorphic to $\xi$ (argue by transfinite induction).  The price for this strength is compactness: consider the theory which says that there is a nonstandard natural number.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
How about allowing set-sized conjunctions and disjunctions for a set of any size? This gives the logic $\mathbb L_{\rm {Ord},\omega}$, but actually it will not be a logic under our definition because it fails a number of reasonable properties. For one thing, there are class-many formulas for any language, and for another, a formula can mention arbitrarily large chunks of a language. These failures stand in the way of the existence of strong compactness cardinals. $\mathbb L_{\rm {Ord},\omega}$ does not have a strong compactness cardinal. Why? Suppose $\kappa$ is a strong compactness cardinal for $\mathbb L_{\rm {Ord},\omega}$. Consider the theory with a relation $E$ which says that the universe is isomorphic to $\kappa$ and also has assertions $$\exists x\exists y\, x&gt;\varphi_\xi(y)$$ for every $\xi&lt;\kappa$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Why stop at long conjunctions and disjunctions? We can also allow long sequences of quantifiers. The logics $\mathbb L_{\delta,\gamma}$, for cardinals $\delta$ and $\gamma$, allow quantifier blocks of length less than $\gamma$. In the logic $\mathbb L_{\omega_1,\omega_1}$ we can express that a relation is well-founded. In the logic $\mathbb L_{\omega_1,\omega_2}$ we can express that the universe is uncountable. We can weaken these logics by adding to $\mathbb L_{\omega_1,\omega}$ the quantifier $Q^{WF}xy$ and define that $Q^{WF}xy\,\varphi(x,y)$ holds whenever $\varphi$ defines a well-founded relation. Similarly we can add the quantifier $Q^{U}x$ and define that $Q^{U}x\,\varphi(x)$ holds whenever there are uncountably many elements satisfying $\varphi(x)$. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Notice how these logic are reliant on more and more of the ambient set-theoretic background to give us more information about the properties of our structures. Can these logics have compactness cardinals? A cardinal $\kappa$ is a weak compactness cardinal for $\mathbb L_{\kappa,\kappa}$ if and only if $\kappa$ is weakly compact (hence the name). A cardinal $\kappa$ is a strong compactness cardinal for $\mathbb L_{\kappa,\kappa}$ if and only if it is strongly compact. (Both results are due to Tarski &lt;a href=&quot;#Tarski:compactness&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;) Indeed, there is a large cardinal principle under which every logic has a strong compactness cardinal and there is a much weaker large cardinal principle under which every logic has a weak compactness cardinal. We will talk about those in a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next, let's delve even deeper into the set-theoretic universe to define the second-order logic $\mathbb L^2$ in which we have second-order quantifiers ranging over all relations on the structure. In second-order logic, we can express that a relation is well-founded, that the universe is infinite, and that a relation is isomorphic to a rank initial segment $(V_\alpha,\in)$ of the set-theoretic universe. We can express that a linear order has a countable dense subset or that a graph can be colored in 3 colors or that a group has an infinite abelian subgroup. But despite how strong the logic is, a formula of $\mathbb L^2$ can use only finitely much of a language. A cardinal $\kappa$ is a strong compactness cardinal for $\mathbb L_{\kappa,\kappa}^2$ if and only if it is extendible and the least strong compactness cardinal for $\mathbb L^2$ must be extendible &lt;a href=&quot;#Magidor:Logics&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt; (a cardinal $\kappa$ is extendible if for every $\alpha&gt;\kappa$, there is an elementary embedding $j:V_\alpha\to V_\beta$ with $\text{crit}(j)=\kappa$ and $j(\kappa)&gt;\alpha$). As we can see, strong compactness for $\mathbb L^2$ is a strong property. Extendible cardinals are the second step in the $C^{(n)}$-extendible cardinals hierarchy, introduced by Bagaria &lt;a href=&quot;#Bagaria:CnExtendible&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;, they are precisely the $C^{(2)}$-extendible cardinals ($C^{(1)}$-extendible cardinals are the supercompacts). A cardinal $\kappa$ is $C^{(n)}$-extendible if for every $\alpha&gt;\kappa$ such that $V_\alpha\prec_{\Sigma_n}V$, there is an elementary embedding $j:V_\alpha\to V_\beta$ with $\text{crit}(j)=\kappa$, $V_\beta\prec_{\Sigma_n}V$ and $j(\kappa)&gt;\alpha$. Are the rest of the $C^{(n)}$-extendible cardinals strong compactness cardinals for some natural logics?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Väänänen defined a class of very strong logics, the &lt;em&gt;sort logics&lt;/em&gt; $\mathbb L^{s,\Sigma_n}$, which generalize second-order logic, by allowing a search throughout the entire universe of sets for an object in some way related to our structure &lt;a href=&quot;#Vaananen:SortLogic&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;. Second-order logic is a two-sorted logic because it has two sorts of objects: the elements of the model and the relations on the model. This easily generalizes to multi-sorted logics, which can have more different sorts, each sort coming with its own variables and quantifiers. Each sort has its own corresponding universe of objects for the quantifiers to range over. Sort logics are multi-sorted logics with additional special sort quantifiers $\forall^\sim$ and $\exists^\sim$. A formula $\exists^\sim E\,\varphi(E)$ answers the question whether we can expand our existing collection of universes of various sorts by a new sort with a relation $E$ on it satisfying $\varphi(E)$ with respect to the old sorts. The $\Sigma_n$ in $\mathbb L^{s,\Sigma_n}$ limits the sort quantifiers to a $\Sigma_n$-formula. The stratification of sort logic into the $\Sigma_n$-levels is necessary because a satisfaction relation for the full sort logic with arbitrary alternations of sort quantifiers would yield definability of truth. In sort logic, we can express whether a set is isomorphic to a $V_\alpha$ which is $\Sigma_n$-elementary in $V$. We can express whether a group is the additive group of some field. A cardinal $\kappa$ is $C^{(n)}$-extendible if and only if it is a strong compactness cardinal for $\mathbb L^{s,\Sigma_n}_{\kappa,\kappa}$ and the least strong compactness cardinal for $\mathcal L^{s,\Sigma_n}$ must be $C^{(n)}$-extendible &lt;a href=&quot;#Boney:ModelTheoreticCharacterizationsOfLargeCardinals&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We can also have logics tailor-made for a cause. Suppose, for instance, that you do not want the full power of second-order logic, but you just want to recognize whether a given set with a relation $E$ is isomorphic to a rank initial segment $V_\alpha$. To achieve this we can simply extend first-order logic by a single formula $\varphi_E(x)$ which can be applied to a language with a binary relation $E$, and decree that it holds true whenever $x$ is transitive with respect to the $E$ relation and $(x,E)$ is isomorphic to $V_\alpha$ for some $\alpha$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
With all these examples, we are ready to see a formal definition of abstract logic. First let's formally define languages.  A &lt;em&gt;language&lt;/em&gt; $\tau$ is a collection of function and relation symbols that come with a finite number arity, as well as constant symbols.  Formally, $\tau$ is an ordered quadruple $(\mathfrak F, \mathfrak R, \mathfrak C, a)$ where $\mathfrak F$, $\mathfrak R$, and $\mathfrak C$ are disjoint sets and $a:\mathfrak F\cup\mathfrak R \to \omega$ is the arity function. To every language $\tau$ we associate the corresponding class $\text{Str }\tau$ of all $\tau$-structures, namely sets with interpretations for the relations, functions, and constants in $\tau$. A renaming $f$ between two languages $\tau=(\mathfrak F, \mathfrak R, \mathfrak C, a)$ and $\sigma=(\mathfrak F', \mathfrak R', \mathfrak C', a')$ is a bijection $f:\mathfrak F\cup\mathfrak R\cup\mathfrak C \to \mathfrak F'\cup\mathfrak R'\cup\mathfrak C'$ that preserves the partition and the arities. Informally, a renaming simply gives different names to the functions, relations, and constants of a given language. If there is a renaming $f$ between two languages $\tau$ and $\sigma$, then there is the obvious bijection $f^*$ between $\text{Str }\tau$ and $\text{Str } \sigma$ which takes a $\tau$-structure and maps it to a structure with the same underlying set but with renamed functions, relations, and constants. Now for the definition:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Definition:&lt;/strong&gt;
An &lt;em&gt;abstract logic&lt;/em&gt; is a pair $(\mathcal L, \vDash_{\mathcal L})$ satisfying the following conditions.
	&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		(sentences) $\mathcal L$ is a class function which takes a language $\tau$ to $\mathcal L(\tau)$ - the set of all sentences in $\tau$.&lt;/li&gt;
 &lt;li&gt;(satisfaction) $\vDash_{\mathcal L}$ is some sub-collection of the class of all pairs $(M,\varphi)$ where $M$ is a $\tau$-structure and $\varphi\in \mathcal L(\tau)$, and we interpret that $M\vDash_{\mathcal L}$ whenever $(M,\varphi)$ is in this collection.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt; (monotonicity) If $\tau \subseteq \sigma$, then $\mathcal L(\tau) \subseteq \mathcal L(\sigma)$. &lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt; (expansion) If $\varphi \in \mathcal L(\tau)$, $\sigma\supseteq \tau$, and $M$ is a $\sigma$-structure, then $M \vDash_{\mathcal L} \varphi$ if and only if the reduct of $M$ to $\tau$, $M \upharpoonright \tau \vDash_{\mathcal L} \varphi$.&lt;/li&gt;
		&lt;li&gt; (isomorphism) If $M \cong N$, then $M \vDash_{\mathcal L} \varphi$ if and only if $N \vDash_{\mathcal L} \varphi$.&lt;/p&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;(renaming) Every renaming $f$ between languages $\tau$ and $\sigma$ induces a unique bijection $f_*:\mathcal L(\tau) \to \mathcal L(\sigma)$ such that for any $\tau$-structure $M$ and $\varphi \in \mathcal L(\tau)$, we have
		$$M\vDash_{\mathcal L} \varphi \text{ if and only if } f^*(M) \vDash_{\mathcal L} f_*(\varphi).$$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; There is a least cardinal $\kappa$, called the &lt;em&gt;occurrence number&lt;/em&gt; of $\mathcal L$, such that for every sentence $\varphi\in \mathcal L(\tau)$, there is a sub-language $\tau^*$ of size less than $\kappa$ such that $\varphi\in\tau^*$. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
It is the easiest course of action to restrict logics to sentences and introduce formulas by adding and interpreting constants. Some other sources (see for instance &lt;a href=&quot;#ChangKeisler:ModelTheory&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;) add other properties such as closure under conjunctions, negations, and quantification.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let's get back to the large cardinal principle under which every abstract logic has a strong compactness cardinal. Vopenka's principle is the assertion that every class of structures in a common language has two structures which elementarily embed. Bagaria showed that Vopenka's principle is equivalent to the assertion that for every $n&lt;\omega$, there is a $C^{(n)}$-extendible cardinal &lt;a href=&quot;#Bagaria:CnExtendible&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;. Makowsky showed that Vopenka's principle is equivalent to the assertion that every abstract logic has a strong compactness cardinal &lt;a href=&quot;#Makowsky:Vopenka&quot;&gt;[7]&lt;/a&gt;. In an upcoming joint work with Boney, Dimopolous and Magidor we show that every abstract logic has stationarily many weak compactness cardinals if and only if ${\rm Ord}$ is subtle &lt;a href=&quot;#BoneyDimopoulosGitmanMagidor:AbstractLogics&quot;&gt;[8]&lt;/a&gt;. The principle &lt;em&gt;${\rm Ord}$ is subtle&lt;/em&gt; asserts that for every class club $C$ and every sequence $\langle  A_\xi\mid\xi\in{\rm Ord}\rangle$ with $A_\alpha\subseteq \alpha$, there are $\alpha&lt;\beta\in C$ such that $A_\beta\cap \alpha=A_\alpha$. In this work we also provide compactness characterizations of various virtual large cardinals in terms of a new notion of &lt;em&gt;pseudo-model&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#BoneyDimopoulosGitmanMagidor:AbstractLogics&quot;&gt;[8]&lt;/a&gt;. Given a language $\tau$ and a theory $T$ in an abstract logic $\mathcal L(\tau)$, we can say informally that a pseudo-model of $T$ is a set $M$ on which we can impose partial $\tau$-structures to interpret all possible small pieces of $T$ with the extension property that any interpretation of a small piece of $T$ can be extended to an interpretation of another small piece of $T$.&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Tarski:compactness&quot;&gt;A. Tarski, “Some problems and results relevant to the foundations of set theory,” in &lt;i&gt;Logic, Methodology and Philosophy of Science, Proceedings of the 1960 International Congress&lt;/i&gt;, 1962. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Magidor:Logics&quot;&gt;M. Magidor, “On the role of supercompact and extendible cardinals in logic,” &lt;i&gt;Israel Journal of Mathematics&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 10, pp. 147–157, 1971. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Bagaria:CnExtendible&quot;&gt;J. Bagaria, “$C^{(n)}$-cardinals,” &lt;i&gt;Arch. Math. Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 51, no. 3-4, pp. 213–240, 2012. Available at: http://dx.doi.org.ezproxy.gc.cuny.edu/10.1007/s00153-011-0261-8&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Vaananen:SortLogic&quot;&gt;J. Väänänen, “Sort logic and foundations of mathematics,” in &lt;i&gt;Infinity and Truth&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 25, C. Chong, Q. Fend, T. Slaman, and H. Woodin, Eds. 2014, pp. 171–186. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Boney:ModelTheoreticCharacterizationsOfLargeCardinals&quot;&gt;W. Boney, “Model theoretic characterizations of large cardinals,” &lt;i&gt;Israel J. Math.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 236, no. 1, pp. 133–181, 2020. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1007/s11856-020-1971-6&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;ChangKeisler:ModelTheory&quot;&gt;C. C. Chang and H. J. Keisler, &lt;i&gt;Model theory&lt;/i&gt;, Third., vol. 73. North-Holland Publishing Co., Amsterdam, 1990, p. xvi+650. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Makowsky:Vopenka&quot;&gt;J. Makowsky, “Vopenka’s principle and compact logics,” &lt;i&gt;Journal of Symbolic Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 50, pp. 42–48, 1985. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;BoneyDimopoulosGitmanMagidor:AbstractLogics&quot;&gt;W. Boney, S. Dimopoulos, V. Gitman, and M. Magidor, “Model theoretic characterizations of large cardinals revisited,” &lt;i&gt;Manuscript&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Since the early 20th century, logicians have formalized the study of mathematical structures in the system of first-order logic. But first-order logic itself, the so-called meta-theory of mathematics, does not exist outside of mathematics. It depends on the ambient set-theoretic background in which we choose to work, or at the minimum on some weak fragment of it codifying the properties of natural numbers. Using more of the available set-theoretic background we can define much stronger logics through which we gain access to more advanced properties of mathematical structures. So what is a logic? Roughly speaking, a logic is an assignment to every mathematical language of a collection of formulas together with a satisfaction relation which tells us which formulas a given structure in a given language satisfies. We are all familiar with first-order logic's recursive definition of formulas and Tarski's satisfaction. Formulas and satisfaction in other logics can be much stranger in nature and they usually gain us much more access to the set-theoretic properties of structures. By a language, here, we simply mean a collection of functions, relations, and constants. I will give a formal definition of logic in a little bit, but I think it is more instructive to start with some examples of different logics and their properties. Two very basic properties of first-order logic which we take for granted are (1) that there are set-many formulas for every fixed language and (2) that any single formula can mention only finitely much of the language. Although these properties are obvious enough in this case, it turns out that they are fairly important for abstracting away to the desired properties of tractable abstract logics. One of the most useful, surprising, and significant properties of first-order logic is ($\omega$-)compactness, the assertion that if every finite fragment of a theory has a model, then so does the whole theory. Compactness tends to fail for stronger logics, but depending on the existence of large cardinals, they will satisfy $\kappa$-compactness for some cardinal $\kappa$, meaning that if every ${strong compactness cardinal for the logic. We will say that $\kappa$ is a weak compactness cardinal if $\kappa$-compactness holds for theories of size $\kappa$. Set theorists and model theorists, going back to Tarski, have uncovered a very close connection between large cardinals and compactness cardinals for strong logics. In first-order logic we can take finite conjunctions and disjunctions of formulas. Using more of the set-theoretic background, we can strengthen first-order logic to allow conjunctions and disjunctions of size less than $\delta$ for some cardinal $\delta$. This gives rise to a family of logics indexed by cardinals $\delta$, the $\mathbb L_{\delta,\omega}$ logics. The weakest such logic $\mathbb L_{\omega_1,\omega}$ allows countable-length conjunctions and disjunctions of formulas. A formula of $\mathbb L_{\delta,\omega}$ can mention a $\gamma$-sized chunk of a language for any $\gamma How about allowing set-sized conjunctions and disjunctions for a set of any size? This gives the logic $\mathbb L_{\rm {Ord},\omega}$, but actually it will not be a logic under our definition because it fails a number of reasonable properties. For one thing, there are class-many formulas for any language, and for another, a formula can mention arbitrarily large chunks of a language. These failures stand in the way of the existence of strong compactness cardinals. $\mathbb L_{\rm {Ord},\omega}$ does not have a strong compactness cardinal. Why? Suppose $\kappa$ is a strong compactness cardinal for $\mathbb L_{\rm {Ord},\omega}$. Consider the theory with a relation $E$ which says that the universe is isomorphic to $\kappa$ and also has assertions $$\exists x\exists y\, x&gt;\varphi_\xi(y)$$ for every $\xi Why stop at long conjunctions and disjunctions? We can also allow long sequences of quantifiers. The logics $\mathbb L_{\delta,\gamma}$, for cardinals $\delta$ and $\gamma$, allow quantifier blocks of length less than $\gamma$. In the logic $\mathbb L_{\omega_1,\omega_1}$ we can express that a relation is well-founded. In the logic $\mathbb L_{\omega_1,\omega_2}$ we can express that the universe is uncountable. We can weaken these logics by adding to $\mathbb L_{\omega_1,\omega}$ the quantifier $Q^{WF}xy$ and define that $Q^{WF}xy\,\varphi(x,y)$ holds whenever $\varphi$ defines a well-founded relation. Similarly we can add the quantifier $Q^{U}x$ and define that $Q^{U}x\,\varphi(x)$ holds whenever there are uncountably many elements satisfying $\varphi(x)$. Notice how these logic are reliant on more and more of the ambient set-theoretic background to give us more information about the properties of our structures. Can these logics have compactness cardinals? A cardinal $\kappa$ is a weak compactness cardinal for $\mathbb L_{\kappa,\kappa}$ if and only if $\kappa$ is weakly compact (hence the name). A cardinal $\kappa$ is a strong compactness cardinal for $\mathbb L_{\kappa,\kappa}$ if and only if it is strongly compact. (Both results are due to Tarski {% cite Tarski:compactness %}) Indeed, there is a large cardinal principle under which every logic has a strong compactness cardinal and there is a much weaker large cardinal principle under which every logic has a weak compactness cardinal. We will talk about those in a bit. Next, let's delve even deeper into the set-theoretic universe to define the second-order logic $\mathbb L^2$ in which we have second-order quantifiers ranging over all relations on the structure. In second-order logic, we can express that a relation is well-founded, that the universe is infinite, and that a relation is isomorphic to a rank initial segment $(V_\alpha,\in)$ of the set-theoretic universe. We can express that a linear order has a countable dense subset or that a graph can be colored in 3 colors or that a group has an infinite abelian subgroup. But despite how strong the logic is, a formula of $\mathbb L^2$ can use only finitely much of a language. A cardinal $\kappa$ is a strong compactness cardinal for $\mathbb L_{\kappa,\kappa}^2$ if and only if it is extendible and the least strong compactness cardinal for $\mathbb L^2$ must be extendible {% cite Magidor:Logics %} (a cardinal $\kappa$ is extendible if for every $\alpha&gt;\kappa$, there is an elementary embedding $j:V_\alpha\to V_\beta$ with $\text{crit}(j)=\kappa$ and $j(\kappa)&gt;\alpha$). As we can see, strong compactness for $\mathbb L^2$ is a strong property. Extendible cardinals are the second step in the $C^{(n)}$-extendible cardinals hierarchy, introduced by Bagaria {% cite Bagaria:CnExtendible %}, they are precisely the $C^{(2)}$-extendible cardinals ($C^{(1)}$-extendible cardinals are the supercompacts). A cardinal $\kappa$ is $C^{(n)}$-extendible if for every $\alpha&gt;\kappa$ such that $V_\alpha\prec_{\Sigma_n}V$, there is an elementary embedding $j:V_\alpha\to V_\beta$ with $\text{crit}(j)=\kappa$, $V_\beta\prec_{\Sigma_n}V$ and $j(\kappa)&gt;\alpha$. Are the rest of the $C^{(n)}$-extendible cardinals strong compactness cardinals for some natural logics? Väänänen defined a class of very strong logics, the sort logics $\mathbb L^{s,\Sigma_n}$, which generalize second-order logic, by allowing a search throughout the entire universe of sets for an object in some way related to our structure {% cite Vaananen:SortLogic %}. Second-order logic is a two-sorted logic because it has two sorts of objects: the elements of the model and the relations on the model. This easily generalizes to multi-sorted logics, which can have more different sorts, each sort coming with its own variables and quantifiers. Each sort has its own corresponding universe of objects for the quantifiers to range over. Sort logics are multi-sorted logics with additional special sort quantifiers $\forall^\sim$ and $\exists^\sim$. A formula $\exists^\sim E\,\varphi(E)$ answers the question whether we can expand our existing collection of universes of various sorts by a new sort with a relation $E$ on it satisfying $\varphi(E)$ with respect to the old sorts. The $\Sigma_n$ in $\mathbb L^{s,\Sigma_n}$ limits the sort quantifiers to a $\Sigma_n$-formula. The stratification of sort logic into the $\Sigma_n$-levels is necessary because a satisfaction relation for the full sort logic with arbitrary alternations of sort quantifiers would yield definability of truth. In sort logic, we can express whether a set is isomorphic to a $V_\alpha$ which is $\Sigma_n$-elementary in $V$. We can express whether a group is the additive group of some field. A cardinal $\kappa$ is $C^{(n)}$-extendible if and only if it is a strong compactness cardinal for $\mathbb L^{s,\Sigma_n}_{\kappa,\kappa}$ and the least strong compactness cardinal for $\mathcal L^{s,\Sigma_n}$ must be $C^{(n)}$-extendible {% cite Boney:ModelTheoreticCharacterizationsOfLargeCardinals %}. We can also have logics tailor-made for a cause. Suppose, for instance, that you do not want the full power of second-order logic, but you just want to recognize whether a given set with a relation $E$ is isomorphic to a rank initial segment $V_\alpha$. To achieve this we can simply extend first-order logic by a single formula $\varphi_E(x)$ which can be applied to a language with a binary relation $E$, and decree that it holds true whenever $x$ is transitive with respect to the $E$ relation and $(x,E)$ is isomorphic to $V_\alpha$ for some $\alpha$. With all these examples, we are ready to see a formal definition of abstract logic. First let's formally define languages. A language $\tau$ is a collection of function and relation symbols that come with a finite number arity, as well as constant symbols. Formally, $\tau$ is an ordered quadruple $(\mathfrak F, \mathfrak R, \mathfrak C, a)$ where $\mathfrak F$, $\mathfrak R$, and $\mathfrak C$ are disjoint sets and $a:\mathfrak F\cup\mathfrak R \to \omega$ is the arity function. To every language $\tau$ we associate the corresponding class $\text{Str }\tau$ of all $\tau$-structures, namely sets with interpretations for the relations, functions, and constants in $\tau$. A renaming $f$ between two languages $\tau=(\mathfrak F, \mathfrak R, \mathfrak C, a)$ and $\sigma=(\mathfrak F', \mathfrak R', \mathfrak C', a')$ is a bijection $f:\mathfrak F\cup\mathfrak R\cup\mathfrak C \to \mathfrak F'\cup\mathfrak R'\cup\mathfrak C'$ that preserves the partition and the arities. Informally, a renaming simply gives different names to the functions, relations, and constants of a given language. If there is a renaming $f$ between two languages $\tau$ and $\sigma$, then there is the obvious bijection $f^*$ between $\text{Str }\tau$ and $\text{Str } \sigma$ which takes a $\tau$-structure and maps it to a structure with the same underlying set but with renamed functions, relations, and constants. Now for the definition: Definition: An abstract logic is a pair $(\mathcal L, \vDash_{\mathcal L})$ satisfying the following conditions. (sentences) $\mathcal L$ is a class function which takes a language $\tau$ to $\mathcal L(\tau)$ - the set of all sentences in $\tau$. (satisfaction) $\vDash_{\mathcal L}$ is some sub-collection of the class of all pairs $(M,\varphi)$ where $M$ is a $\tau$-structure and $\varphi\in \mathcal L(\tau)$, and we interpret that $M\vDash_{\mathcal L}$ whenever $(M,\varphi)$ is in this collection. (monotonicity) If $\tau \subseteq \sigma$, then $\mathcal L(\tau) \subseteq \mathcal L(\sigma)$. (expansion) If $\varphi \in \mathcal L(\tau)$, $\sigma\supseteq \tau$, and $M$ is a $\sigma$-structure, then $M \vDash_{\mathcal L} \varphi$ if and only if the reduct of $M$ to $\tau$, $M \upharpoonright \tau \vDash_{\mathcal L} \varphi$. (isomorphism) If $M \cong N$, then $M \vDash_{\mathcal L} \varphi$ if and only if $N \vDash_{\mathcal L} \varphi$. (renaming) Every renaming $f$ between languages $\tau$ and $\sigma$ induces a unique bijection $f_*:\mathcal L(\tau) \to \mathcal L(\sigma)$ such that for any $\tau$-structure $M$ and $\varphi \in \mathcal L(\tau)$, we have $$M\vDash_{\mathcal L} \varphi \text{ if and only if } f^*(M) \vDash_{\mathcal L} f_*(\varphi).$$ There is a least cardinal $\kappa$, called the occurrence number of $\mathcal L$, such that for every sentence $\varphi\in \mathcal L(\tau)$, there is a sub-language $\tau^*$ of size less than $\kappa$ such that $\varphi\in\tau^*$. It is the easiest course of action to restrict logics to sentences and introduce formulas by adding and interpreting constants. Some other sources (see for instance {% cite ChangKeisler:ModelTheory %}) add other properties such as closure under conjunctions, negations, and quantification. Let's get back to the large cardinal principle under which every abstract logic has a strong compactness cardinal. Vopenka's principle is the assertion that every class of structures in a common language has two structures which elementarily embed. Bagaria showed that Vopenka's principle is equivalent to the assertion that for every $n${\rm Ord}$ is subtle asserts that for every class club $C$ and every sequence $\langle A_\xi\mid\xi\in{\rm Ord}\rangle$ with $A_\alpha\subseteq \alpha$, there are $\alphapseudo-model {% cite BoneyDimopoulosGitmanMagidor:AbstractLogics %}. Given a language $\tau$ and a theory $T$ in an abstract logic $\mathcal L(\tau)$, we can say informally that a pseudo-model of $T$ is a set $M$ on which we can impose partial $\tau$-structures to interpret all possible small pieces of $T$ with the extension property that any interpretation of a small piece of $T$ can be extended to an interpretation of another small piece of $T$. References {% bibliography --cited %}</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Class forcing in its rightful setting</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/talks/2020/06/25/class-forcing-in-its-rightful-setting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Class forcing in its rightful setting" /><published>2020-06-25T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/talks/2020/06/25/class-forcing-in-its-rightful-setting</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/talks/2020/06/25/class-forcing-in-its-rightful-setting.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the Kurt Godel Research Seminar, University of Vienna, June 25, 2020 (virtual).&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/ClassForcingTalk.pdf&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The use of class forcing in set theoretic constructions goes back to the proof Easton's Theorem that ${\rm GCH}$ can fail at all regular cardinals. Class forcing extensions are ubiquitous in modern set theory, particularly in the emerging field of set-theoretic geology. Yet, besides the pioneering work by Friedman and Stanley concerning pretame and tame class forcing, the general theory of class forcing has not really been developed until recently. A revival of interest in second-order set theory has set the stage for understanding the properties of class forcing in its natural setting. Class forcing makes a fundamental use of class objects, which in the first-order setting can only be studied in the meta-theory. Not surprisingly it has turned out that properties of class forcing notions are fundamentally determined by which other classes exist around them. In this talk, I will survey recent results (of myself, Antos, Friedman, Hamkins, Holy, Krapf, Schlicht, Williams and others) regarding the general theory of class forcing, the effects of the second-order set theoretic background on the behavior of class forcing notions and the numerous ways in which familiar properties of set forcing can fail for class forcing even in strong second-order set theories.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the Kurt Godel Research Seminar, University of Vienna, June 25, 2020 (virtual).Slides</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Elementary embeddings and smaller large cardinals</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/talks/2020/05/06/elementary-embeddings-and-smaller-large-cardinals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Elementary embeddings and smaller large cardinals" /><published>2020-05-06T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/talks/2020/05/06/elementary-embeddings-and-smaller-large-cardinals</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/talks/2020/05/06/elementary-embeddings-and-smaller-large-cardinals.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the Oxford Logic Seminar, Oxford University, May 6, 2020 (virtual).&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/smallembeddings.pdf&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href='https://www.youtube.com/watch?time_continue=113&amp;v=8h_OJcrNl2o&amp;feature=emb_logo'&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A common theme in the definitions of larger large cardinals is the existence of elementary embeddings from the universe into an inner model. In contrast, smaller large cardinals, such as weakly compact and Ramsey cardinals, are usually characterized by their combinatorial properties such as existence of large homogeneous sets for colorings. It turns out that many familiar smaller large cardinals have elegant elementary embedding characterizations. The embeddings here are correspondingly ‘small’; they are between transitive set models of set theory, usually the size of the large cardinal in question. The study of these elementary embeddings has led us to isolate certain important properties via which we have defined robust hierarchies of large cardinals below a measurable cardinal. In this talk, I will introduce these types of elementary embeddings and discuss the large cardinal hierarchies that have come out of the analysis of their properties. The more recent results in this area are a joint work with Philipp Schlicht.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the Oxford Logic Seminar, Oxford University, May 6, 2020 (virtual).Slides Video</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Toy multiverses of set theory</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/talks/2020/01/10/toy-multiverses-of-set-theory.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Toy multiverses of set theory" /><published>2020-01-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-01-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/talks/2020/01/10/toy-multiverses-of-set-theory</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/talks/2020/01/10/toy-multiverses-of-set-theory.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Winter ASL Meeting&lt;/a&gt;, Denver, January 17-18, 2020.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Modern set theoretic research has produced a myriad of set-theoretic universes with fundamentally different properties and structures. Multiversists hold the philosophical position that none of these universes is the true universe of set theory - they all have equal ontological status and populate the set-theoretic multiverse. Hamkins, one of the main proponents of this view, formulated his position via the heuristic Hamkins Multiverse Axioms, which include such radical relativity assertions as that any universe is ill-founded from the perspective of another universe in the multiverse. With Hamkins, we showed that the collection of all countable computably saturated models of ${\rm ZFC}$ satisfies his axioms. Countable computably saturated models form a unique natural class with a number of desirable model theoretic properties such as existence of truth predicates and automorphisms. Indeed, any collection of models satisfying the Hamkins Multiverse Axioms must be contained within this class. In a joint work with Toby Meadows, Michał Godziszewski, and Kameryn Williams, we explore which weaker versions of the multiverse axioms have 'toy multiverses' that are not made up entirely of computably saturated models.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the Winter ASL Meeting, Denver, January 17-18, 2020.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ramsey-like cardinals</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/talks/2020/01/10/ramsey-like-cardinals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ramsey-like cardinals" /><published>2020-01-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-01-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/talks/2020/01/10/ramsey-like-cardinals</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/talks/2020/01/10/ramsey-like-cardinals.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the Algebra and Logic Seminar, University of Denver, January 14, 2020.&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/ramseyLikeCardinalsTalk.pdf&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ramsey-like cardinals originated with the study of elementary embedding properties of smaller large cardinals. Measurable cardinals and stronger large cardinals $\kappa$ are defined by the existence of elementary embeddings $j:V\to M$ with critical point $\kappa$ from the universe into an inner model. Elementary embeddings provide a unifying framework in the study of these large cardinals and set theorists have developed a toolbox of techniques for working with elementary embeddings, particularly for showing indestructibility under forcing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smaller large cardinals such as weakly compact cardinals and Ramsey cardinals were originally defined in terms of combinatorial Ramsey-type properties, but it turns out that they also have elementary embedding characterizations involving elementary embeddings of set-sized models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elementary embeddings $j:V\to M$ are connected with the existence of certain ultrafilters. The ultrapower of $V$ by a non-principal &lt;em&gt;countably complete&lt;/em&gt; ultrafilter is well-founded, and therefore produces a non-trivial elementary embedding $j:V\to M$, and such an embedding, if its critical point is $\kappa$, can be used to obtain a non-principal $\kappa$-complete ultrafilter $$U=\{A\subseteq\kappa\mid \kappa\in j(A)\}.$$  We will say that $U$ is &lt;em&gt;generated by $\kappa$ via $j$&lt;/em&gt;. Thus, in particular, there is a non-trivial elementary embedding $j:V\to M$ if and only if there is a non-principal countably complete ultrafilter on some cardinal $\kappa$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ultrapower construction with a countably complete ultrafilter can be iterated through all the ordinals to produce ${\rm Ord}$-many well-founded iterated ultrapowers. Given such an ultrafilter $U$, the first step is the original ultrapower $j:V\to M$, the second step is the ultrapower by $j(U)$, and we proceed in this manner, using the image of the original ultrafilter at successor stages and direct limits at limit stages. The successor stages are well-founded because all ultrafilters are countably complete (by elementarity) from the perspective of the model in which the ultrapower is constructed, and the direct limits are well-founded by a theorem of Gaifman &lt;a href=&quot;#gaifman:ultrapowers&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. Thus, we say that countably complete ultrafilters are &lt;em&gt;iterable&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elementary embeddings of set-sized models of set theory are also connected with the existence of certain ultrafilters. So let's talk about these  models and ultrafilters. We say that a &lt;em&gt;weak $\kappa$-model&lt;/em&gt; is a transitive set model $M\models{\rm ZFC}^-$ of size $\kappa$ and height above $\kappa$. A weak $\kappa$-model $M$ is a &lt;em&gt;$\kappa$-model&lt;/em&gt; if it is additionally closed under sequences of length less than $\kappa$, the maximum possible closure for a model of size $\kappa$. Natural weak $\kappa$-models arise as elementary substructures of $H_{\kappa^+}$. Smaller large cardinals $\kappa$ are characterized by the existence of elementary embeddings of weak $\kappa$-models or $\kappa$-models with critical point $\kappa$. Given a weak $\kappa$-model $M$, we say that $U\subseteq P^M(\kappa)$ is an &lt;em&gt;$M$-ultrafilter&lt;/em&gt; if the structure $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$, that is $M$ together with a predicate for $U$, satisfies that $U$ is a normal ultrafilter on $\kappa$. What this means is that $U$ is an ultrafilter measuring $P^M(\kappa)$ that is closed under diagonal intersections of sequences from $M$. The set $U$ is allowed to be completely external to $M$, and while normality for sequences from $M$ implies $\kappa$-completeness for sequences from $M$, an $M$-ultrafilter $U$ may not even be countably complete because $M$, having no closure, can be missing many countable sequences. Note that, while the weak $\kappa$-model $M$ is required to satisfy ${\rm ZFC}^-$, replacement almost certainly fails in the structure $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$ once we add the $M$-ultrafilter. How do we know this? Read on. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the context of $M$-ultrafilters, we will weaken the notion of &lt;em&gt;countable completeness&lt;/em&gt; to say only that the intersection of countably many sets from the $M$-ultrafilter is non-empty. The two notions are equivalent for ultrafilters on $\kappa$, but for $M$-ultrafilters it is too strong to require that the intersection of countably many sets in the ultrafilter is itself in the ultrafilter because the intersection may not even be an element of $M$ and therefore not measured by the $M$-ultrafilter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can build the ultrapower of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ by an $M$-ultrafilter using functions $f$  on $\kappa$ from $M$. While we have a complete characterization of when an ultrafilter on $\kappa$ has a well-founded ultrapower, namely countable completeness, the situation with $M$-ultrafilters is much messier. Countable completeness of the $M$-ultrafilter suffices for well-foundedness, but this condition, as we will see, is too strong. Let's call an $M$-ultrafilter &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; if it has a well-founded ultrapower. There is no known elegant characterization of good $M$-ultrafilters. The existence of good $M$-ultrafilters is equivalent to the existence of elementary embeddings $j:M\to N$ because the set $U$ generated by $\kappa$ via $j$ as above is a good $M$-ultrafilter.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Next, let's talk about iterability of $M$-ultrafilters. After a moment's thought one realizes that given a good $M$-ultrafilter $U$ we cannot even perform the second step of the iterated ultrapower construction because, since $U$ is not an element of $M$, we cannot take the image of it under the ultrapower embedding. To have any hope of being iterable, an $M$-ultrafilter first needs to be internal enough to $M$ to make it possible to define successor stage ultrafilters. An $M$-ultrafilter is said to be &lt;em&gt;weakly amenable&lt;/em&gt; if for every set $S\in M$ with $|S|^M=\kappa$, $S\cap U\in M$. The condition of weak amenability suffices to define successor stage ultrafilters. It also has another nice characterization. We will say that an elementary embedding $j:M\to N$ with critical point $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;$\kappa$-powerset preserving&lt;/em&gt; if $M$ and $N$ have the same subsets of $\kappa$. It is always the case that $P^M(\kappa)\subseteq P^N(\kappa)$, but the other inclusion need not hold. Indeed, if a good $M$-ultrafilter $U$ is weakly amenable, then the ultrapower embedding $j:M\to N$ is $\kappa$-powerset preserving and conversely an $M$-ultrafilter generated by $\kappa$ via a $\kappa$-powerset preserving embedding $j:M\to N$ is weakly amenable. We will see below that while weak amenability makes it possible to define the stages of the iterated ultrapower construction, it does not guarantee the well-foundeness even of the second step ultrapower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are finally ready to see some elementary embedding characterizations of smaller large cardinals. The simplest such characterization belongs to weakly compact cardinals. An inaccessible cardinal $\kappa$ is weakly compact if and only if every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ which has a good $M$-ultrafilter $U$. It turns out that this characterization can be strengthened in a number of ways. We can replace weak $\kappa$-model by $\kappa$-model, even by $\kappa$-model that is elementary in $H_{\kappa^+}$. Indeed, if $\kappa$ is weakly compact, then &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; weak $\kappa$-model has a good $M$-ultrafilter! Can we further strengthen the characterization by asking that all or at least some weak $\kappa$-models have weakly amenable good $M$-ultrafilters? The answer turns out to be no.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's make another definition. We will say that a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter is &lt;em&gt;$\alpha$-good&lt;/em&gt; if it has $\alpha$-many well-founded iterated ultrapowers. Note that $1$-good equals weakly amenable plus good. Some observations are in order. By a theorem of Gaifman &lt;a href=&quot;#gaifman:ultrapowers&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, only countable stages of the iteration matter. If an $M$-ultrafilter is $\omega_1$-good, then it is $\alpha$-good for every $\alpha$. By a theorem of Kunen &lt;a href=&quot;#kunen:ultrapowers&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;, a countably complete $M$-ultrafilter is $\omega_1$-good. We will say that a cardinal $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;$\alpha$-iterable&lt;/em&gt; if every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ which has an $\alpha$-good $M$-ultrafilter. Thus, we can rephrase the question about weakly compacts above as asking whether a weakly compact cardinal is 1-iterable. In fact, 1-iterable cardinals are limits of weakly compact cardinals, even limits of ineffable cardinals &lt;a href=&quot;#gitman:ramsey&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;. The $\alpha$-iterable cardinals for $\alpha\leq\omega_1$ form a hierarchy of strength where a $\beta$-iterable cardinal is a limit of $\alpha$-iterable cardinals for every $\alpha\lt\beta$. The $\alpha$-iterable cardinals for $\alpha$ countable are downward absolute to $L$, but $\omega_1$-iterable cardinals already imply $0^{\#}$ &lt;a href=&quot;#gitman:welch&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, up are Ramsey cardinals, which also have an unexpectedly nice elementary embedding characterization. A cardinal $\kappa$ is Ramsey if and only if every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ which has a weakly amenable countably complete $M$-ultrafilter &lt;a href=&quot;#mitchell:ramsey&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;. Can we strengthen the Ramsey elementary embedding characterization by replacing weak $\kappa$-model with $\kappa$-model or even $\kappa$-model elementary in $H_{\kappa^+}$, or even ask that it holds for all weak $\kappa$-models? The answer is no.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We say that a cardinal $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;strongly Ramsey&lt;/em&gt; if every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a $\kappa$-model $M$ which has a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter and a cardinal $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;super Ramsey&lt;/em&gt; if we replace $\kappa$-model with $\kappa$-model elementary in $H_{\kappa^+}$. Strongly Ramsey cardinals are limits of Ramsey cardinals and super Ramsey cardinals are limits of strongly Ramsey cardinals. The assertion that every weak $\kappa$-model has a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter is inconsistent! &lt;a href=&quot;#gitman:ramsey&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt; Broadly speaking, the reason for this contrast in relationships with the introduction of weak amenability is that having the same subsets of $\kappa$ creates a great deal of reflection between $M$ and its ultrapower $N$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are there other natural large cardinal notions between super Ramsey and measurable cardinals? Super Ramsey cardinals require embeddings on $\kappa$-model elementary in $H_{\kappa^+}$ because such models look like an initial segment of the universe. A natural extension of the idea of having embeddings on models reflecting an initial segment of the universe is to require that the weak $\kappa$-model is elementary in some larger $H_\theta$. But this is impossible because large $H_\theta$ cannot have transitive elementary submodels of size $\kappa$. So let's define that an &lt;em&gt;imperfect weak $\kappa$-model&lt;/em&gt; is a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ where we replace transitivity with the weaker requirement that $\kappa+1\subseteq M$, and similarly define &lt;em&gt;imperfect $\kappa$-models&lt;/em&gt;. Now we can consider the large cardinal notion &lt;em&gt;$\kappa$-Ramsey&lt;/em&gt;, introduced by Holy and Schlicht, where for every set $A$ and arbitrarily large cardinals $\theta$, $A$ is an element of an imperfect $\kappa$-model $M\prec H_\theta$ which has a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter. $\kappa$-Ramsey cardinals have a natural game characterization. The game is played by the challenger and the judge, with the challenger playing an increasing sequence of imperfect $\kappa$-models $M\prec H_\theta$ and the judge responding with nested $M$-ultrafilters. For the judge to win a game of length $\alpha$ she has to be able to play for $\alpha$-many steps, with the challenger winning otherwise. The reason the large cardinal is called $\kappa$-Ramsey is that it is characterized by the challenger failing to have a winning strategy in this game of length $\kappa$. $\kappa$-Ramsey cardinals are limits of super Ramsey cardinals. &lt;a href=&quot;#HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are there natural large cardinal notions between $\kappa$-Ramsey cardinals and measurable cardinals? Yes! Remember I remarked earlier that the structure $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$, where $M$ is a weak $\kappa$-model and $U$ is an $M$-ultrafilter almost certainly fails to satisfy replacement? Well, let's define that a cardinal $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;weakly baby measurable&lt;/em&gt; if every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ which has a good $M$-ultrafilter such that $\langle M,\in, U\rangle\models{\rm ZFC}^-$. Similar large cardinal notions were introduced and investigated recently by McKenzie and Bovykin &lt;a href=&quot;#BovykinMcKenzie:RamseyLikeNFUM&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;. We recently realized with Philipp Schlicht that if $\kappa$ is weakly baby measurable, then $V_\kappa$ is a model of proper class many cardinals $\alpha$ that are $\alpha$-Ramsey. Baby measurable cardinals (McKenzie and Bovykin call them &lt;em&gt;simultaneously baby measurable&lt;/em&gt;) would be cardinals where we replace weak $\kappa$-model with $\kappa$-model. These are even stronger, but still some ways below a measurable!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;gaifman:ultrapowers&quot;&gt;H. Gaifman, “Elementary embeddings of models of set-theory and certain
              subtheories,” in &lt;i&gt;Axiomatic set theory (Proc. Sympos. Pure Math., Vol.
              XIII, Part II, Univ. California, Los Angeles,
              Calif., 1967)&lt;/i&gt;, Providence R.I.: Amer. Math. Soc., 1974, pp. 33–101. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;kunen:ultrapowers&quot;&gt;K. Kunen, “Some applications of iterated ultrapowers in set theory,” &lt;i&gt;Ann. Math. Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 1, pp. 179–227, 1970. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;gitman:ramsey&quot;&gt;V. Gitman, “Ramsey-like cardinals,” &lt;i&gt;The Journal of Symbolic Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 76, no. 2, pp. 519–540, 2011. Available at: http://dx.doi.org/10.2178/jsl/1305810762&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;gitman:welch&quot;&gt;V. Gitman and P. D. Welch, “Ramsey-like cardinals II,” &lt;i&gt;The Journal of Symbolic Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 76, no. 2, pp. 541–560, 2011. Available at: http://dx.doi.org/10.2178/jsl/1305810763&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;P. Holy and P. Schlicht, “A hierarchy of Ramsey-like cardinals,” &lt;i&gt;Fund. Math.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 242, no. 1, pp. 49–74, 2018. Available at: https://doi.org/10.4064/fm396-9-2017&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;BovykinMcKenzie:RamseyLikeNFUM&quot;&gt;A. Bovykin and Z. McKenzie, “Ramsey-like cardinals that characterize the exact consistency strength of NFUM,” &lt;i&gt;Manuscript&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the Algebra and Logic Seminar, University of Denver, January 14, 2020.Slides</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Modern class forcing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publications/2019/11/13/modern-class-forcing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modern class forcing" /><published>2019-11-13T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publications/2019/11/13/modern-class-forcing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publications/2019/11/13/modern-class-forcing.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;AntosGitman:ModernClassForcing&quot;&gt;C. Antos and V. Gitman, “Modern Class Forcing,” &lt;i&gt;Manuscript&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Set theorists started forcing with class partial orders to modify global properties of the universe very soon after general forcing techniques were developed. Once Cohen showed that ${\rm CH}$ could fail, and that indeed the continuum could assume any reasonable value, it was natural to ask whether, for instance, the ${\rm GCH}$ can fail unboundedly often, or more generally what global patterns were possible for the continuum function. Since a set partial order can only affect a set-sized chunk of the continuum function, a class partial order was required to modify the ${\rm GCH}$ pattern unboundedly. Easton used a class product of set-forcing notions, with what became known as Easton support, to show that the ${\rm GCH}$ can fail at every regular cardinal, and that, in fact, any reasonable pattern on the continuum function was consistent with ${\rm ZFC}$ &lt;a href=&quot;#easton:gch&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. Since then class products and iterations, usually with Easton support, have been used, for example, to globally kill large cardinals, to make all supercompact cardinals indestructible, or to code the universe into the continuum function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two approaches to handling class forcing in first-order set theory. We can use a generic filter $G$ for a class forcing notion $\mathbb P$ to interpret the $\mathbb P$-names and obtain the forcing extension $V[G]$, and then throw $G$ away. We can also work in the structure $(V[G],\in,G)$ with a predicate for $G$. While both approaches were used by set theorists to handle specific instances of class forcing, neither approach could provide a robust framework for the study of general properties of class forcing because it relegated properties of classes to the meta-theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Important early results on class forcing, due to Friedman and Stanley, showed that class partial orders satisfying `niceness' conditions, such as pretameness, behave like set partial orders. But despite the pervasive use of class forcing in set theoretic constructions, a general theory of class forcing was not fully developed until recently. These recent results demonstrated that properties of class forcing depend on what other classes exist around them, establishing that the theory of class forcing can only be properly investigated in a second-order set theoretic setting. The mathematical framework of second-order set theory has objects for both sets and classes, and allows us to move the study of classes out of the meta-theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Class forcing becomes even more important in the context of second-order set theory, where it can be used to modify the structure of classes. With class forcing, we can, for instances, add a global well-order or shoot class clubs with desirable properties. Both these forcing notions leave the first-order part of the model intact because they do not add sets. Such forcing constructions over models of second-order set theory can actually be used to prove theorems about models of ${\rm ZFC}$. One of the most important results in the model theory of set theory is the Keisler-Morley extension theorem asserting that every countable model of ${\rm ZFC}$ has an elementary top-extension (adding only sets of rank above the ordinals of the model) &lt;a href=&quot;#keislermorley:topextensions&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. Given a countable model $M$ of ${\rm ZFC}$, the top-extension is built as an ultrapower of $M$ by a special ultrafilter, which we can construct provided that $M$ can be expanded to a model of ${\rm GBC}$. If $M$ doesn't already have a definable global well-order, we use class forcing to add it without altering $M$ itself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many ways class forcing does not behave as nicely as set forcing. Class forcing can destroy ${\rm ZFC}$; even the atomic forcing relation may fail to be definable for a class forcing notion; densely embedded class forcing notions need not be forcing equivalent; most class forcing notions don't have Boolean completions; the intermediate model theorem fails badly for class forcing, etc. At the same time, conditions on class forcing, such as pretameness, guarantee that these pathologies are avoided, and these conditions hold for most familiar class forcing notions used by set theorists, such as progressively closed Easton support products and iterations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, we survey most of the recent results developing a general theory of class forcing in the second-order setting and establishing surprising connections between properties of class forcing and the structure of second-order set theories.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;easton:gch&quot;&gt;W. B. Easton, “Powers of regular cardinals,” &lt;i&gt;Ann. Math. Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 1, pp. 139–178, 1970. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;keislermorley:topextensions&quot;&gt;H. J. Keisler and M. Morley, “Elementary extensions of models of set theory,” &lt;i&gt;Israel J. Math.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 6, pp. 49–65, 1968. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">{% reference page.ref %} Set theorists started forcing with class partial orders to modify global properties of the universe very soon after general forcing techniques were developed. Once Cohen showed that ${\rm CH}$ could fail, and that indeed the continuum could assume any reasonable value, it was natural to ask whether, for instance, the ${\rm GCH}$ can fail unboundedly often, or more generally what global patterns were possible for the continuum function. Since a set partial order can only affect a set-sized chunk of the continuum function, a class partial order was required to modify the ${\rm GCH}$ pattern unboundedly. Easton used a class product of set-forcing notions, with what became known as Easton support, to show that the ${\rm GCH}$ can fail at every regular cardinal, and that, in fact, any reasonable pattern on the continuum function was consistent with ${\rm ZFC}$ {% cite easton:gch %}. Since then class products and iterations, usually with Easton support, have been used, for example, to globally kill large cardinals, to make all supercompact cardinals indestructible, or to code the universe into the continuum function. There are two approaches to handling class forcing in first-order set theory. We can use a generic filter $G$ for a class forcing notion $\mathbb P$ to interpret the $\mathbb P$-names and obtain the forcing extension $V[G]$, and then throw $G$ away. We can also work in the structure $(V[G],\in,G)$ with a predicate for $G$. While both approaches were used by set theorists to handle specific instances of class forcing, neither approach could provide a robust framework for the study of general properties of class forcing because it relegated properties of classes to the meta-theory. Important early results on class forcing, due to Friedman and Stanley, showed that class partial orders satisfying `niceness' conditions, such as pretameness, behave like set partial orders. But despite the pervasive use of class forcing in set theoretic constructions, a general theory of class forcing was not fully developed until recently. These recent results demonstrated that properties of class forcing depend on what other classes exist around them, establishing that the theory of class forcing can only be properly investigated in a second-order set theoretic setting. The mathematical framework of second-order set theory has objects for both sets and classes, and allows us to move the study of classes out of the meta-theory. Class forcing becomes even more important in the context of second-order set theory, where it can be used to modify the structure of classes. With class forcing, we can, for instances, add a global well-order or shoot class clubs with desirable properties. Both these forcing notions leave the first-order part of the model intact because they do not add sets. Such forcing constructions over models of second-order set theory can actually be used to prove theorems about models of ${\rm ZFC}$. One of the most important results in the model theory of set theory is the Keisler-Morley extension theorem asserting that every countable model of ${\rm ZFC}$ has an elementary top-extension (adding only sets of rank above the ordinals of the model) {% cite keislermorley:topextensions %}. Given a countable model $M$ of ${\rm ZFC}$, the top-extension is built as an ultrapower of $M$ by a special ultrafilter, which we can construct provided that $M$ can be expanded to a model of ${\rm GBC}$. If $M$ doesn't already have a definable global well-order, we use class forcing to add it without altering $M$ itself. In many ways class forcing does not behave as nicely as set forcing. Class forcing can destroy ${\rm ZFC}$; even the atomic forcing relation may fail to be definable for a class forcing notion; densely embedded class forcing notions need not be forcing equivalent; most class forcing notions don't have Boolean completions; the intermediate model theorem fails badly for class forcing, etc. At the same time, conditions on class forcing, such as pretameness, guarantee that these pathologies are avoided, and these conditions hold for most familiar class forcing notions used by set theorists, such as progressively closed Easton support products and iterations. In this article, we survey most of the recent results developing a general theory of class forcing in the second-order setting and establishing surprising connections between properties of class forcing and the structure of second-order set theories. References {% bibliography --cited %}</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Structural properties of the stable core</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publications/2019/10/10/structural-properties-of-the-stable-core.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Structural properties of the stable core" /><published>2019-10-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-10-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publications/2019/10/10/structural-properties-of-the-stable-core</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publications/2019/10/10/structural-properties-of-the-stable-core.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;FriedmanGitmanMuller:StableCore&quot;&gt;S.-D. Friedman, V. Gitman, and S. Müller, “Some properties of the Stable Core,” &lt;i&gt;Manuscript&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first author introduced the inner model &lt;em&gt;stable core&lt;/em&gt; while investigating under what
circumstances the universe $V$ is a class forcing extension of the
inner model ${\rm HOD}$, the collection of all hereditarily ordinal
definable sets (missing reference). He showed in &lt;a href=&quot;#Friedman:stableCore&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; that there is a robust $\Delta_2$-definable
class $S$ contained in ${\rm HOD}$ such that $V$ is a class-forcing extension of the structure $\langle L[S],\in, S\rangle$, which he called the stable core, by an ${\rm Ord}$-cc class partial order $\mathbb P$ definable from $S$. Indeed, for any inner model $M$, $V$ is a $\mathbb P$-forcing extension of $\langle M[S],\in,S\rangle$, so that in particular, since ${\rm HOD}[S]={\rm HOD}$, $V$ is a $\mathbb P$-forcing extension of $\langle {\rm HOD},\in,S\rangle$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's explain the result in more detail for the stable core $L[S]$, noting that exactly the same analysis applies to ${\rm HOD}$. The partial order $\mathbb P$ is definable in $\langle L[S],\in,S\rangle$ and there is a generic filter $G$, meeting all dense sub-classes of $\mathbb P$ definable in $\langle L[S],\in,S\rangle$,
such that $V=L[S][G]$. All standard forcing theorems hold for $\mathbb P$ since it has the ${\rm Ord}$-cc. Thus, we get that the forcing relation for $\mathbb P$ is definable in $\langle L[S],\in,S\rangle$ and the forcing extension $\langle V,\in,G\rangle\models{\rm ZFC}$. However, this particular generic filter $G$ is not definable in $V$. To obtain $G$, we first force with an auxiliary forcing $\mathbb Q$ to add a particular class $F$, without adding sets, such that $V=L[F]$. We then show that $G$ is definable from $F$ and $F$ is in turn definable in the structure $\langle L[S][G], \in, S,G\rangle$, so that $L[S][G]=V$. This gives a formulation of the result as a ${\rm ZFC}$-theorem because we can say (using the definitions of $\mathbb P$ and $\mathbb Q$) that it is forced by $\mathbb Q$ that $V=L[F]$, where $F$ is $V$-generic for $\mathbb Q$, and (the definition of) $G$ is $\langle L[S],\in,S\rangle$-generic, and finally that $F$ is definable in $\langle L[S][G],\in,S,G\rangle$. Of course, a careful formulation would say that the result holds for all sufficiently large natural numbers $n$, where $n$ bounds the complexity of the formulas used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Without the niceness requirement on $\mathbb P$ that it has the ${\rm Ord}$-cc, there is a much easier construction of a class forcing notion $\mathbb P$, suggested by Woodin, such that $V$ is a class forcing extension of $\langle {\rm HOD},\in, \mathbb P\rangle$. At the same time, some additional predicate must be added to ${\rm HOD}$ in
order to realize all of $V$ as a class-forcing extension because, as
Hamkins and Reitz observed in
&lt;a href=&quot;#HamkinsReitz:The-set-theoretic-universe-is-not-necessarily-a-forcing-extension-of-HOD&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;,
it is consistent that $V$ is not a class-forcing extension of ${\rm HOD}$. To construct such a counterexample, we suppose that $\kappa$ is inaccessible in $L$ and force over the Kelley-Morse model $\mathcal L=\langle L_\kappa,\in, L_{\kappa+1}\rangle$ to code the truth predicate of $L_\kappa$ (which is an element of $L_{\kappa+1}$) into the continuum pattern below $\kappa$. The first-order part $L_\kappa[G]$ of this extension cannot be a forcing extension of ${\rm HOD}^{L_\kappa[G]}=L_\kappa$ (by the weak homogeneity of the coding forcing), because the truth predicate of $L_\kappa$ is definable there and this can be recovered via the forcing relation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While the definition of the partial order $\mathbb P$ is fairly involved, the
&lt;em&gt;stability predicate&lt;/em&gt; $S$ simply codes the elementarity relations
between sufficiently nice initial segments $H_\alpha$ (the collection of all sets with transitive closure of size less than $\alpha$) of $V$. Given a
natural number $n\geq 1$, call a cardinal $\alpha$ $n$-&lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; if
it is a strong limit cardinal and $H_\alpha$ satisfies
$\Sigma_n$-collection. The predicate $S$ consists of
triples $(n,\alpha,\beta)$ such that $n\geq 1$, $\alpha$ and $\beta$
are $n$-good cardinals and $H_\alpha\prec_{\Sigma_n}H_\beta$. We will denote by $S_n$ the $n$-th slice of the stability predicate $S$, namely $S_n=\{(\alpha,\beta)\mid (n,\alpha,\beta)\in S\}$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Clearly the stable core $L[S]\subseteq{\rm HOD}$, and the first author showed in (missing reference) that
it is consistent that $L[S]$ is smaller than ${\rm HOD}$. The stable core has several nice properties which fail for ${\rm HOD}$ such as that it is partially forcing absolute and, assuming ${\rm GCH}$, is preserved by forcing to code the universe into a real (missing reference)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In order to
motivate the many questions which arise about the stable core let us
briefly discuss the set-theoretic goals of studying inner models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study of canonical inner models has proved to be one of the most
fruitful directions of modern set-theoretic research. The canonical
inner models, of which Gödel's constructible universe $L$ was the first
example, are built bottom-up by a canonical procedure. The resulting
fine structure of the models leads to regularity properties, such as
the ${\rm GCH}$ and $\square$, and sometimes even absoluteness
properties. But all known canonical inner models are incompatible with
sufficiently large large cardinals, and indeed each such inner model
is very far from the universe in the presence of sufficiently large
large cardinals in the sense, for example, that covering fails and the
large cardinals are not downward absolute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The inner model ${\rm HOD}$ was introduced by Gödel, who showed that in a
universe of ${\rm ZF}$ it is always a model of ${\rm ZFC}$. But unlike the
constructible universe which also shares this property, ${\rm HOD}$ has
turned out to be highly non-canonical. While $L$ cannot be modified by
forcing, ${\rm HOD}$ can be easily changed by forcing because we can use
forcing to code information into ${\rm HOD}$. For instance, any subset of
the ordinals from $V$ can be made ordinal definable in a set-forcing extension
by coding its characteristic function into the continuum pattern, so
that it becomes an element of the ${\rm HOD}$ of the extension. Indeed, by
coding all of $V$ into the continuum pattern of a class-forcing
extension, Roguski showed that every universe $V$ is the ${\rm HOD}$ of one
of its class-forcing extensions &lt;a href=&quot;#Roguski:HOD&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;. Thus, any
consistent set-theoretic property, including all known large cardinals, consistently holds in ${\rm HOD}$. At the same time, the
${\rm HOD}$ of a given universe can be very far from it. It is consistent
that every measurable cardinal is not even weakly compact in ${\rm HOD}$
and that a universe can have a supercompact cardinal which is not even
weakly compact in ${\rm HOD}$
&lt;a href=&quot;#ChengFriedmanHamkins:LargeCardinalsNeedNotBeLargeInHOD&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;. It is
also consistent that ${\rm HOD}$ is wrong about all successor cardinals
&lt;a href=&quot;#CummingsFriedmanGolshani:CollapsingCardinalsHOD&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Does the stable core behave more like the canonical inner models or
more like ${\rm HOD}$? Is there a fine structural version of the stable
core, does it satisfy regularity properties such as the ${\rm GCH}$? Is
there a bound on the large cardinals that are compatible with the stable core? Or, on the other hand, are the large cardinals
downward absolute to the stable core? Can we code information into the
stable core using forcing?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

In this article, we show the following results about the structure of
the stable core, which answer some of the aforementioned questions as
well as motivate further questions about the structure of the stable
core in the presence of sufficiently large large cardinals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Measurable cardinals are consistent with the stable core.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;:
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt; The stable core of $L[\mu]$, the canonical model for one measurable
  cardinal, is $L[\mu]$. In particular, the stable core can have a measurable cardinal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; If $\vec U=\langle U_\alpha\mid\alpha\in{\rm Ord}\rangle$ is a discrete collection of normal measures, then the stable core of $L[\vec U]$ is $L[\vec U]$. In particular, the stable core can have a discrete proper class of measurable cardinals.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We can code information into the stable core over $L$ or $L[\mu]$
using forcing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;:
  Suppose $\mathbb P\in L$ is a forcing notion and $G\subseteq \mathbb P$ is
  $L$-generic. Then there is a further forcing extension $L[G][H]$
  such that $G\in L[S^{L[G][H]}]$ (the universe of the stable core). An analogous result holds for
  $L[\mu]$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
An extension of the coding results shows that the ${\rm GCH}$ can fail
badly in the stable core.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;:
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a class-forcing extension of $L$ such that in its stable core the ${\rm GCH}$
  fails at every regular cardinal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; There is a class-forcing extension of $L[\mu]$ such that in its stable core there is
  a measurable cardinal and the ${\rm GCH}$ fails on a tail of regular
  cardinals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Measurable cardinals need not be downward absolute to the stable core.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;:
  There is a forcing extension of $L[\mu]$ in which the measurable
  cardinal $\kappa$ of $L[\mu]$ remains measurable, but it is not even
  weakly compact in the stable core.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

Although we don't know whether the stable core can have a measurable limit of measurables, the stable core has inner models with measurable limits of measurables, and much more. Say that a cardinal $\kappa$ is $1$-&lt;em&gt;measurable&lt;/em&gt;
if it is measurable, and, for $n &lt; \omega$, $(n+1)$-&lt;em&gt;measurable&lt;/em&gt; if it
is measurable and a limit of $n$-measurable cardinals. Write $m_0^\#$ for $0^\#$ and $m_n^\#$ for the minimal mouse which is a sharp for a proper class of $n$-measurable cardinals, namely, an active mouse $\mathcal M$ such that the critical point of the top extender is a limit of $n$-measurable cardinals in $\mathcal M$. Here we mean &lt;em&gt;mouse&lt;/em&gt; in the sense of &lt;a href=&quot;#Mitchell:BeginningInnerModelTheory&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt; (Sections 1 and 2), i.e., a mouse has only total measures on its sequence. The mouse $m_n^{\#}$ can also be construed as a fine structural
mouse with both total and partial extenders (see &lt;a href=&quot;#Zeman:InnerModelsLargeCardinals&quot;&gt;[7]&lt;/a&gt;, Section 4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;:
  For all $n&lt;\omega$, if $m_{n+1}^\#$ exists, then $m_n^\#$ is in the
  stable core.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Moreover, we obtain the following characterization of natural inner
models of the stable core.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;:
  Let $n &lt; \omega$ and suppose that $m_n^\#$ exists. Then whenever
  $$C_1\supseteq C_2\supseteq\ldots\supseteq C_n$$ are class clubs of
  uncountable cardinals such that for every $1 &lt; i\leq n$ and every
  $\gamma \in C_i$,
\[\langle H_\gamma,\in, C_1,\ldots,C_{i-1}\rangle\prec_{\Sigma_1} \langle V,\in,
  C_1,\ldots,C_{i-1}\rangle,\] then $L[C_1,\ldots,C_n]$ is a hyperclass-forcing extension of a (truncated) iterate of $m_n^\#$.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Friedman:stableCore&quot;&gt;S.-D. Friedman, “The stable core,” &lt;i&gt;Bull. Symbolic Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 18, no. 2, pp. 261–267, 2012. Available at: https://doi.org/10.2178/bsl/1333560807&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;HamkinsReitz:The-set-theoretic-universe-is-not-necessarily-a-forcing-extension-of-HOD&quot;&gt;J. D. Hamkins and J. Reitz, “The set-theoretic universe $V$ is not necessarily a class-forcing extension of HOD,” &lt;i&gt;ArXiv e-prints&lt;/i&gt;, Sep. 2017. Available at: http://jdh.hamkins.org/the-universe-need-not-be-a-class-forcing-extension-of-hod&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Roguski:HOD&quot;&gt;S. Roguski, “Cardinals and iterations of ${\rm HOD}$,” &lt;i&gt;Colloq. Math.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 58, no. 2, pp. 159–161, 1990. Available at: https://doi.org/10.4064/cm-58-2-159-161&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;ChengFriedmanHamkins:LargeCardinalsNeedNotBeLargeInHOD&quot;&gt;Y. Cheng, S.-D. Friedman, and J. D. Hamkins, “Large cardinals need not be large in HOD,” &lt;i&gt;Ann. Pure Appl. Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 166, no. 11, pp. 1186–1198, 2015. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apal.2015.07.004&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;CummingsFriedmanGolshani:CollapsingCardinalsHOD&quot;&gt;J. Cummings, S. D. Friedman, and M. Golshani, “Collapsing the cardinals of HOD,” &lt;i&gt;J. Math. Log.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 15, no. 2, pp. 1550007, 32, 2015. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1142/S0219061315500075&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Mitchell:BeginningInnerModelTheory&quot;&gt;W. J. Mitchell, “Beginning inner model theory,” in &lt;i&gt;Handbook of set theory. Vols. 1, 2, 3&lt;/i&gt;, Springer, Dordrecht, 2010, pp. 1449–1495. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4020-5764-9_18&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Zeman:InnerModelsLargeCardinals&quot;&gt;M. Zeman, &lt;i&gt;Inner models and large cardinals&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 5. Walter de Gruyter &amp;amp; Co., Berlin, 2002, p. xii+369. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1515/9783110857818&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">{% reference page.ref %} The first author introduced the inner model stable core while investigating under what circumstances the universe $V$ is a class forcing extension of the inner model ${\rm HOD}$, the collection of all hereditarily ordinal definable sets (missing reference). He showed in {% cite Friedman:stableCore %} that there is a robust $\Delta_2$-definable class $S$ contained in ${\rm HOD}$ such that $V$ is a class-forcing extension of the structure $\langle L[S],\in, S\rangle$, which he called the stable core, by an ${\rm Ord}$-cc class partial order $\mathbb P$ definable from $S$. Indeed, for any inner model $M$, $V$ is a $\mathbb P$-forcing extension of $\langle M[S],\in,S\rangle$, so that in particular, since ${\rm HOD}[S]={\rm HOD}$, $V$ is a $\mathbb P$-forcing extension of $\langle {\rm HOD},\in,S\rangle$. Let's explain the result in more detail for the stable core $L[S]$, noting that exactly the same analysis applies to ${\rm HOD}$. The partial order $\mathbb P$ is definable in $\langle L[S],\in,S\rangle$ and there is a generic filter $G$, meeting all dense sub-classes of $\mathbb P$ definable in $\langle L[S],\in,S\rangle$, such that $V=L[S][G]$. All standard forcing theorems hold for $\mathbb P$ since it has the ${\rm Ord}$-cc. Thus, we get that the forcing relation for $\mathbb P$ is definable in $\langle L[S],\in,S\rangle$ and the forcing extension $\langle V,\in,G\rangle\models{\rm ZFC}$. However, this particular generic filter $G$ is not definable in $V$. To obtain $G$, we first force with an auxiliary forcing $\mathbb Q$ to add a particular class $F$, without adding sets, such that $V=L[F]$. We then show that $G$ is definable from $F$ and $F$ is in turn definable in the structure $\langle L[S][G], \in, S,G\rangle$, so that $L[S][G]=V$. This gives a formulation of the result as a ${\rm ZFC}$-theorem because we can say (using the definitions of $\mathbb P$ and $\mathbb Q$) that it is forced by $\mathbb Q$ that $V=L[F]$, where $F$ is $V$-generic for $\mathbb Q$, and (the definition of) $G$ is $\langle L[S],\in,S\rangle$-generic, and finally that $F$ is definable in $\langle L[S][G],\in,S,G\rangle$. Of course, a careful formulation would say that the result holds for all sufficiently large natural numbers $n$, where $n$ bounds the complexity of the formulas used. Without the niceness requirement on $\mathbb P$ that it has the ${\rm Ord}$-cc, there is a much easier construction of a class forcing notion $\mathbb P$, suggested by Woodin, such that $V$ is a class forcing extension of $\langle {\rm HOD},\in, \mathbb P\rangle$. At the same time, some additional predicate must be added to ${\rm HOD}$ in order to realize all of $V$ as a class-forcing extension because, as Hamkins and Reitz observed in {% cite HamkinsReitz:The-set-theoretic-universe-is-not-necessarily-a-forcing-extension-of-HOD %}, it is consistent that $V$ is not a class-forcing extension of ${\rm HOD}$. To construct such a counterexample, we suppose that $\kappa$ is inaccessible in $L$ and force over the Kelley-Morse model $\mathcal L=\langle L_\kappa,\in, L_{\kappa+1}\rangle$ to code the truth predicate of $L_\kappa$ (which is an element of $L_{\kappa+1}$) into the continuum pattern below $\kappa$. The first-order part $L_\kappa[G]$ of this extension cannot be a forcing extension of ${\rm HOD}^{L_\kappa[G]}=L_\kappa$ (by the weak homogeneity of the coding forcing), because the truth predicate of $L_\kappa$ is definable there and this can be recovered via the forcing relation. While the definition of the partial order $\mathbb P$ is fairly involved, the stability predicate $S$ simply codes the elementarity relations between sufficiently nice initial segments $H_\alpha$ (the collection of all sets with transitive closure of size less than $\alpha$) of $V$. Given a natural number $n\geq 1$, call a cardinal $\alpha$ $n$-good if it is a strong limit cardinal and $H_\alpha$ satisfies $\Sigma_n$-collection. The predicate $S$ consists of triples $(n,\alpha,\beta)$ such that $n\geq 1$, $\alpha$ and $\beta$ are $n$-good cardinals and $H_\alpha\prec_{\Sigma_n}H_\beta$. We will denote by $S_n$ the $n$-th slice of the stability predicate $S$, namely $S_n=\{(\alpha,\beta)\mid (n,\alpha,\beta)\in S\}$. Clearly the stable core $L[S]\subseteq{\rm HOD}$, and the first author showed in (missing reference) that it is consistent that $L[S]$ is smaller than ${\rm HOD}$. The stable core has several nice properties which fail for ${\rm HOD}$ such as that it is partially forcing absolute and, assuming ${\rm GCH}$, is preserved by forcing to code the universe into a real (missing reference) In order to motivate the many questions which arise about the stable core let us briefly discuss the set-theoretic goals of studying inner models. The study of canonical inner models has proved to be one of the most fruitful directions of modern set-theoretic research. The canonical inner models, of which Gödel's constructible universe $L$ was the first example, are built bottom-up by a canonical procedure. The resulting fine structure of the models leads to regularity properties, such as the ${\rm GCH}$ and $\square$, and sometimes even absoluteness properties. But all known canonical inner models are incompatible with sufficiently large large cardinals, and indeed each such inner model is very far from the universe in the presence of sufficiently large large cardinals in the sense, for example, that covering fails and the large cardinals are not downward absolute. The inner model ${\rm HOD}$ was introduced by Gödel, who showed that in a universe of ${\rm ZF}$ it is always a model of ${\rm ZFC}$. But unlike the constructible universe which also shares this property, ${\rm HOD}$ has turned out to be highly non-canonical. While $L$ cannot be modified by forcing, ${\rm HOD}$ can be easily changed by forcing because we can use forcing to code information into ${\rm HOD}$. For instance, any subset of the ordinals from $V$ can be made ordinal definable in a set-forcing extension by coding its characteristic function into the continuum pattern, so that it becomes an element of the ${\rm HOD}$ of the extension. Indeed, by coding all of $V$ into the continuum pattern of a class-forcing extension, Roguski showed that every universe $V$ is the ${\rm HOD}$ of one of its class-forcing extensions {% cite Roguski:HOD %}. Thus, any consistent set-theoretic property, including all known large cardinals, consistently holds in ${\rm HOD}$. At the same time, the ${\rm HOD}$ of a given universe can be very far from it. It is consistent that every measurable cardinal is not even weakly compact in ${\rm HOD}$ and that a universe can have a supercompact cardinal which is not even weakly compact in ${\rm HOD}$ {% cite ChengFriedmanHamkins:LargeCardinalsNeedNotBeLargeInHOD %}. It is also consistent that ${\rm HOD}$ is wrong about all successor cardinals {% cite CummingsFriedmanGolshani:CollapsingCardinalsHOD %}. Does the stable core behave more like the canonical inner models or more like ${\rm HOD}$? Is there a fine structural version of the stable core, does it satisfy regularity properties such as the ${\rm GCH}$? Is there a bound on the large cardinals that are compatible with the stable core? Or, on the other hand, are the large cardinals downward absolute to the stable core? Can we code information into the stable core using forcing? In this article, we show the following results about the structure of the stable core, which answer some of the aforementioned questions as well as motivate further questions about the structure of the stable core in the presence of sufficiently large large cardinals. Measurable cardinals are consistent with the stable core. Theorem: The stable core of $L[\mu]$, the canonical model for one measurable cardinal, is $L[\mu]$. In particular, the stable core can have a measurable cardinal. If $\vec U=\langle U_\alpha\mid\alpha\in{\rm Ord}\rangle$ is a discrete collection of normal measures, then the stable core of $L[\vec U]$ is $L[\vec U]$. In particular, the stable core can have a discrete proper class of measurable cardinals. We can code information into the stable core over $L$ or $L[\mu]$ using forcing. Theorem: Suppose $\mathbb P\in L$ is a forcing notion and $G\subseteq \mathbb P$ is $L$-generic. Then there is a further forcing extension $L[G][H]$ such that $G\in L[S^{L[G][H]}]$ (the universe of the stable core). An analogous result holds for $L[\mu]$. An extension of the coding results shows that the ${\rm GCH}$ can fail badly in the stable core. Theorem: There is a class-forcing extension of $L$ such that in its stable core the ${\rm GCH}$ fails at every regular cardinal. There is a class-forcing extension of $L[\mu]$ such that in its stable core there is a measurable cardinal and the ${\rm GCH}$ fails on a tail of regular cardinals. Measurable cardinals need not be downward absolute to the stable core. Theorem: There is a forcing extension of $L[\mu]$ in which the measurable cardinal $\kappa$ of $L[\mu]$ remains measurable, but it is not even weakly compact in the stable core. Although we don't know whether the stable core can have a measurable limit of measurables, the stable core has inner models with measurable limits of measurables, and much more. Say that a cardinal $\kappa$ is $1$-measurable if it is measurable, and, for $n measurable if it is measurable and a limit of $n$-measurable cardinals. Write $m_0^\#$ for $0^\#$ and $m_n^\#$ for the minimal mouse which is a sharp for a proper class of $n$-measurable cardinals, namely, an active mouse $\mathcal M$ such that the critical point of the top extender is a limit of $n$-measurable cardinals in $\mathcal M$. Here we mean mouse in the sense of {% cite Mitchell:BeginningInnerModelTheory %} (Sections 1 and 2), i.e., a mouse has only total measures on its sequence. The mouse $m_n^{\#}$ can also be construed as a fine structural mouse with both total and partial extenders (see {% cite Zeman:InnerModelsLargeCardinals %}, Section 4). Theorem: For all $n Moreover, we obtain the following characterization of natural inner models of the stable core. Theorem: Let $n References {% bibliography --cited %}</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ground model definability in ${\rm ZF}$</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/talks/2019/10/10/ground-model-definability-in-zf.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ground model definability in ${&amp;#92;rm ZF}$" /><published>2019-10-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-10-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/talks/2019/10/10/ground-model-definability-in-zf</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/talks/2019/10/10/ground-model-definability-in-zf.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jointmathematicsmeetings.org/jmm&quot;&gt;Joint Mathematics Meeting&lt;/a&gt;, special session on 'Choiceless Set Theory and related areas', University of Denver, January 15-16, 2020.&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/ZFGroundModelDefinability.pdf&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Laver, and independently Woodin, showed that a ground model is always definable (with a ground model parameter) in its set-forcing extensions &lt;a href=&quot;#laver:groundmodel&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;#woodin:groundmodel&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. More so, the definition is uniform for all ${\rm ZFC}$-universes: there is a single formula $\varphi(x,y)$ such that whenever $V\models{\rm ZFC}$ and $V[G]$ is a set-forcing extension of $V$ by a poset $\mathbb P\in V$ of size $|\mathbb P|^V=\gamma$, then $V$ is defined in $V[G]$ by $\varphi(x,P^V(\delta))$ with $\delta=(\gamma^+)^V(=(\gamma^+)^{V[G]})$. Let's explain what the formula $\varphi(x,P^V(\delta))$ says. Let ${\rm Z}^*$ be a certain finite fragment of ${\rm ZFC}$. We will say that a transitive model $M\in V[G]$ is &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; if $M\models {\rm Z}^*$, $P^M(\delta)=P^V(\delta)$ and $(\delta^+)^M=(\delta^+)^{V[G]}$. The formula $\varphi(x,P^V(\delta))$ then holds of a set $x$ if $x$ is an element of a good model $M$ of height $\lambda\gg\delta$ such that $V[G]_\lambda\models {\rm Z}^*$ and the pair $M\subseteq V[G]_\lambda$ has the $\delta$-cover and $\delta$-approximation properties (we will explain what those are in a moment). Here is the reason the formula works. Any forcing extension by a poset of size less than a regular cardinal $\delta$ has the property that there are unboundedly many ordinals $\lambda$ such that both $V_\lambda$ and $V[G]_\lambda$ satisfy ${\rm Z}^*$ and the pair $V_\lambda\subseteq V[G]_\lambda$ has the $\delta$-cover and $\delta$-approximation properties. Also, if there is a good model $M$ of height $\lambda$ with $P^M(\delta)=P^V(\delta)$ and $(\delta^+)^M=(\delta^+)^{V[G]}$ such that that pair $M\subseteq V[G]_\delta\models {\rm Z}^*$ has the the $\delta$-cover and $\delta$-approximation properties, then the model is unique. Hence such a model $M$ of height $\lambda$ can only be $V_\lambda$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The notions of $\delta$-cover and $\delta$-approximation properties are due to Hamkins &lt;a href=&quot;#hamkins:coverandapproximations&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;. Suppose that $V\subseteq W$ are transitive models of (some fragment of) ${\rm ZFC}$ and $\delta$ is a cardinal in $W$.
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
The pair $V\subseteq W$ satisfies the &lt;em&gt;$\delta$-cover property&lt;/em&gt; if for every $A\in W$ with $A\subseteq V$ and $|A|^W&lt;\delta$, there is $B\in V$ with $A\subseteq B$ and $|B|^V&lt;\delta$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The pair $V\subseteq W$ satisfies the &lt;em&gt;$\delta$-approximation property&lt;/em&gt; if whenever $A\in W$ with $A\subseteq V$ and $A\cap a\in V$ for every $a$ of size less than $\delta$ in $V$, then $A\in V$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Because the existence of cardinalities is fundamental to the definition of the cover and approximation properties, these notions appear to rely  essentially on the axiom of choice. Therefore proofs of ground model definability based on these properties cannot be easily modified to work in the absence of choice. It is not known yet whether ground definability holds in ${\rm ZF}$. There are partial positive results and no known counterexamples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Tom Johnstone, we adapted the approximation and cover properties arguments to show that for a cardinal $\delta$, uniform ground model definability holds in models of ${\rm ZF}+{\rm DC}_\delta$ for posets admitting a gap at $\delta$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;: There is a single formula $\varphi(x,y)$ such that whenever $V\models{\rm ZF}+{\rm DC}_\delta$ and $V[G]$ is a set-forcing extension of $V$ by a poset $\mathbb P$ admitting a gap at $\delta$ in $V$, then $V$ is defined in $V[G]$ by $\varphi(x,P^V(\delta))$.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
A poset is said to &lt;em&gt;admit a gap at $\delta$&lt;/em&gt; if it has the form $\mathbb R*\dot{\mathbb Q}$ where $\mathbb R$ is a non-trivial forcing of size less than $\delta$ and it is forced by $\mathbb R$ that is $\dot{\mathbb Q}$ is $\leq\delta$-strategically closed. The $\delta$-dependent choice principle ${\rm DC}_\delta$, introduced by Lévy, allows us to make $\delta$-many dependent choices along any relation without terminal nodes. It asserts that for any non-empty set $S$ and any binary relation  $R$, if for each sequence $s\in S^{\lt\delta}$ there is a $y\in S$ such that $s$ is $R$ related $y$, then there is a function $f:\delta\to S$ such that $f\upharpoonright\alpha \,R\, f(\alpha)$ for all $\alpha&lt;\delta$. The principle ${\rm DC}_\delta$ is robust for forcing with posets admitting a gap at $\delta$ because they preserve it to the forcing extension (see &lt;a href=&quot;#gitmanjohnstone:groundmodels&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A very different recent partial result on ${\rm ZF}$-ground model definability is due to Usuba &lt;a href=&quot;#Usuba:ZFGroundModelDefinability&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;. Usuba showed that if a ${\rm ZF}$-universe has a proper class of Löwenheim-Skolem cardinals, a notion which he introduces, then uniform ground model definability holds for it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;: There is a single formula $\varphi(x,y)$ such that whenever $V$ is a model of ${\rm ZF}$ with a proper class of Löwenheim-Skolem cardinals and $V[G]$ is a set-forcing extension of $V$ by a poset $\mathbb P\in V_\kappa$ for a Lowenheim-Skolem cardinal $\kappa$, then $V$ is defined in the extension $V[G]$ by $\varphi(x,V_\kappa)$.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Usuba's proof is another modification of the arguments using cover and approximation, where he replaces the notion of cardinality by a rough measure on sets, defining for a set $x$ that the measure $|\!|x|\!|$ is the least ordinal $\alpha$ such that there is a surjection from $V_\alpha$ onto $x$.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
An uncountable cardinal $\kappa$ is a &lt;em&gt;Löwenheim-Skolem&lt;/em&gt; (${\rm LS}$) &lt;em&gt;cardinal&lt;/em&gt; if for every $\gamma&lt;\kappa\leq\alpha$ and $x\in V_\alpha$, there is $\beta&gt;\alpha$ and an elementary $X\prec V_\beta$ such that
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$V_\gamma\subseteq X$,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$x\in X$,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the transitive collapse of $X$ belongs to $V_\kappa$,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$(X\cap V_\alpha)^{V_\gamma}\subseteq X$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
In a model of ${\rm ZFC}$, the ${\rm LS}$ cardinals are precisely the $\beth$-fixed point cardinals, and so in particular there are proper class many ${\rm LS}$ cardinals. Let us say, following Woodin, that an uncountable cardinal $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;supercompact&lt;/em&gt; in a model of ${\rm ZF}$ if for every $\alpha\geq\kappa$, there is $\beta\geq\alpha$, a transitive set $N$ and an elementary embedding $j:V_\beta\to N$ such that the critical point of $j$ is $\kappa$, $\alpha &lt; j(\kappa)$, and $N^{V_\alpha}\subseteq N$. It is not difficult to see that every supercompact cardinal is an ${\rm LS}$ cardinal. So, for example, models of ${\rm ZF}$ with a proper class of supercompact cardinals satisfy uniform ground model definability. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The existence of ${\rm LS}$ cardinals is absolute throughout the generic multiverse (missing reference). It follows that if we can force choice over a ${\rm ZF}$-universe, then since its forcing extension has a proper class of ${\rm LS}$ cardinals, it must have a proper class of ${\rm LS}$ cardinals as well. Thus, in particular, ground model definability holds for any ${\rm ZF}$-universe, such as $L(\mathbb R)$, over which we can force the axiom of choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the same time, it is known that there are ${\rm ZF}$ universes without any ${\rm LS}$-cardinals. Let's explain how. Usuba showed that if $\kappa$ is an ${\rm LS}$-cardinal, then the club filter on $\kappa^+$ must be $\kappa$-complete &lt;a href=&quot;#Usuba:ZFGroundModelDefinability&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;. Asaf Karagila showed that every model $V$ of ${\rm ZFC}$ satisfying ${\rm GCH}$ has an extension to a model of ${\rm ZF}$ with the same cofinalities in which the club filter is not $\sigma$-complete on every regular cardinal $\kappa$ &lt;a href=&quot;#karagila:Fodor&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;. This model cannot have any ${\rm LS}$ cardinals because if $\kappa$ in it was an ${\rm LS}$-cardinal, then $\kappa^+$ would be a regular cardinal (since cofinalities from $V$ are preserved) with a $\kappa$-complete club filter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One important consequence of uniform ground model definability is that it makes it possible to define in a first-order way the collection of all grounds of a ${\rm ZFC}$-universe. A priori this is a collection of classes, a second-order notion, but using ground model definability we can write down a first-order formula $\psi(x,y)$ such that for every set $a$, the class $W_a=\{x\mid \psi(x,a)\}$ is a ground of $V$ and for every $W$ ground of $V$, there is a set $a$ such that $W=W_a$. The first-order definability of the collection of grounds makes it possible to study their structure in ${\rm ZFC}$. This has led to the very fruitful subject of set-theoretic geology, initiated by Fuchs, Hamkins, and Reitz, which explores the structure of grounds of a set-theoretic universe. Ground model definability for ${\rm ZF}$ would allow us to extend the same analysis to ${\rm ZF}$-universes, and Usuba's theorem has now made such an analysis possible for a large collection of models, namely those with a proper class of ${\rm LS}$ cardinals. 

We will have to wait to find out whether ground definability holds fully in ${\rm ZF}$.


&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;laver:groundmodel&quot;&gt;R. Laver, “Certain very large cardinals are not created in small forcing
              extensions,” &lt;i&gt;Ann. Pure Appl. Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 149, no. 1-3, pp. 1–6, 2007. Available at: http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.apal.2007.07.002&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;woodin:groundmodel&quot;&gt;H. Woodin, “Recent developments on Cantor’s Continuum Hypothesis,” in &lt;i&gt;Proceedings of the continuum in Philosophy and Mathematics&lt;/i&gt;, 2004. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;hamkins:coverandapproximations&quot;&gt;J. D. Hamkins, “Extensions with the approximation and cover properties have no
              new large cardinals,” &lt;i&gt;Fund. Math.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 180, no. 3, pp. 257–277, 2003. Available at: http://dx.doi.org/10.4064/fm180-3-4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;gitmanjohnstone:groundmodels&quot;&gt;V. Gitman and T. A. Johnstone, “On ground model definability,” in &lt;i&gt;Infinity, Computability, and Metamathematics: Festschrift in honour of the 60th birthdays of Peter Koepke and Philip Welch&lt;/i&gt;, London, GB: College publications, 2014. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Usuba:ZFGroundModelDefinability&quot;&gt;T. Usuba, “Choiceless Löwenheim-Skolem property and uniform definability of grounds.” &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;karagila:Fodor&quot;&gt;A. Karagila, “Fodor’s lemma can fail everywhere,” &lt;i&gt;Acta Math. Hungar.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 154, no. 1, pp. 231–242, 2018. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1007/s10474-017-0768-5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the Joint Mathematics Meeting, special session on 'Choiceless Set Theory and related areas', University of Denver, January 15-16, 2020.Slides</summary></entry></feed>