<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-03-07T15:14:58-05:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">Victoria Gitman</title><entry><title type="html">Parameter-free schemes in second-order arithmetic</title><link href="/publications/2024/01/18/parameter-free-schemes-in-second-order-arithmetic.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Parameter-free schemes in second-order arithmetic" /><published>2024-01-18T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-01-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/publications/2024/01/18/parameter-free-schemes-in-second-order-arithmetic</id><content type="html" xml:base="/publications/2024/01/18/parameter-free-schemes-in-second-order-arithmetic.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Gitman:parameterFreeSchemes&quot;&gt;V. Gitman, “Parameter-free schemes in second-order arithmetic,” &lt;i&gt;Manuscript&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The strength of a second-order arithmetic theory depends mostly on the amount of comprehension that the theory admits. A comprehension scheme
specifies which formulas give collections that turn out to be sets in the model. At the lower extreme, the second-order theory ${\rm ACA}_0$
includes comprehension for all first-order formulas and at the higher extreme, full second-order arithmetic ${\rm Z}_2$ includes comprehension
for all (second-order) formulas. In between, we have $\Sigma^1_n$-comprehension schemes for second-order formulas of complexity $\Sigma^1_n$
($n$ alternations of set quantifiers followed by a first-order formula). A precise formulation of these comprehension schemes should mention
that the specified formulas are allowed to use set parameters from the model. But how significant really are parameters in comprehension? What
if we formulate the comprehension schemes without parameters, do we get equivalent theories, perhaps, equiconsistent theories?
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Let ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}$ be the version of full second-order arithmetic ${\rm Z}_2$, where we do not allow parameters in the comprehension scheme.
Friedman showed in &lt;a href=&quot;#Friedman:parameterFreeComprehension&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; (Lemma 3.1.7) that given a model of ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}$, we can appropriately
restrict its sets to get a model of ${\rm Z}_2$. Thus, the theories ${\rm Z}_2$ and ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}$ are equiconsistent. In a recent work
&lt;a href=&quot;#LyubetskyKanovei:parameterFreeComprehension&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;, Lyubetsky and Kanovei separated the theories ${\rm Z}_2$ and ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}$ by
constructing models of ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}$ with various failures of comprehension with parameters. They constructed a model of ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}$
in which the sets were not even closed under complement, showing that comprehension without parameters does not even give  comprehension with
parameters for $\Sigma^0_0$-assertions. They next considered whether it was possible to have a model of ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}$ with enough
comprehension with parameters to carry out most standard constructions, but still have comprehension with parameters fail somewhere above.
They argued that a reasonable amount of comprehension with parameters for general mathematical purposes is the  $\Sigma^1_2$-comprehension
scheme and constructed a model of ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}$ with the $\Sigma^1_2$-comprehension scheme and a failure of $\Sigma^1_4$-comprehension. The
model was constructed in a forcing extension by a (non-linear) tree iteration of Sacks forcing. Lyubetsky and Kanovei asked whether the result can be
improved to obtain the optimal failure of $\Sigma^1_3$-comprehension &lt;a href=&quot;#LyubetskyKanovei:parameterFreeComprehension&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt; (Problem 8.2).
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
In this article, I answer their question positively by constructing a model with the required properties, similarly to how the model of
&lt;a href=&quot;#LyubetskyKanovei:parameterFreeComprehension&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt; was constructed, in a forcing extension by a tree iteration of Jensen's forcing. Jensen's
forcing is a subposet of Sacks forcing constructed in $L$ using the $\diamondsuit$-principle. Jensen's forcing has the ccc and adds a unique
generic real whose singleton is $\Pi^1_2$-definable. A similar forcing can be constructed in any universe in which the
$\diamondsuit$-principle holds, not just in $L$, and we retain its properties except for, possibly, $\Pi^1_2$-definability of the generic
singleton. Jensen originally introduced the forcing because it gives a forcing extension of $L$ in which there is a $\Pi^1_2$-definable
non-constructible singleton real &lt;a href=&quot;#jensen:real&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;:
It is consistent that there is a model of ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}$ together with $\Sigma^1_2$-comprehension and a failure of
$\Sigma^1_3$-comprehension.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
If the first-order part of a second-order arithmetic model satisfies ${\rm PA}$, then via Gödel's pairing function, we can view any set in the
model as a collection of $n$-tuples, for some $n\lt\omega$, of elements of the model. Among these collections are orderings of the first-order
domain of the model, which the model believes are well-orders. In a model of ${\rm Z}_2$, these well-orders are comparable in that given any two
of them, there is a set coding an isomorphism of one of them with an initial segment of the other. Using coding, a model of ${\rm Z}_2$ can
construct an initial segment of the $L$-hierarchy along any of its well-orders, and these initial segments are similarly coherent (for details of the construction, see  &lt;a href=&quot;#simpson:second-orderArithmetic&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt; (Chapter VII)). We will call a real of a model of ${\rm Z}_2$
&lt;em&gt;constructible&lt;/em&gt; if it appears in an initial segment of the $L$-hierarchy of the model. Similarly, in a model of ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}$, we can
show that any two definable without parameters well-orders are comparable and we can construct an initial segment of the $L$-hierarchy along
any such well-order so that the resulting structures are coherent.  We will call a real of a model of ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}$ &lt;em&gt;constructible&lt;/em&gt; if
it appears in an initial segment of the $L$-hierarchy constructed along a definable without parameters well-order.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
The theory ${\rm Z}_2$ can be further strengthened by adding the choice scheme ${\rm AC}$, which is a set choice principle asserting for every
second-order formula $\varphi(n,X,A)$ (with set parameter $A$) that if for every $n$, there is a set $X$ such that $\varphi(n,X,A)$ holds,
then there is a single set $Y$ whose $n$-th slice $Y_n$ is a witness for $n$. It is not difficult to see that the scheme ${\rm AC}$ actually
implies ${\rm Z}_2$ over ${\rm ACA}_0$. The collection of the constructible reals of a model of ${\rm Z}_2$ satisfies ${\rm Z}_2+{\rm AC}$ (see &lt;a href=&quot;#simpson:second-orderArithmetic&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;, Section VII.6), giving that the two theories are equiconsistent. Friedman's sub-collection of a model
of ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}$, which he showed satisfies ${\rm Z}_2$, was precisely the constructible reals of the model, as defined above, coming from
the initial segments of the $L$-hierarchy constructed along definable without parameters well-orders. His argument additionally showed that
the collection of the constructible reals satisfies ${\rm AC}$. Thus, the theories ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}$ and ${\rm Z}_2+{\rm AC}$ are equiconsistent.
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;
Let ${\rm AC}^{-p}$ denote the parameter-free choice scheme. Because standard arguments that the choice scheme ${\rm AC}$ implies comprehension over
${\rm ACA}_0$ require parameters, it is probably not the case that ${\rm AC}^{-p}$ implies ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}$ over ${\rm ACA}_0$. The reals of the
Feferman-Lévy model of ${\rm ZF}$ (a symmetric submodel of a forcing extension), in which $\omega_1^L$ is countable for every $n\lt\omega$ and
$\omega_\omega^L$ is the first uncountable cardinal &lt;a href=&quot;#levy:choicescheme&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;, is a model of ${\rm Z}_2$ in which ${\rm AC}^{-p}$ fails. In this
model (the code of) $L_{\omega_n^L}$ exists for every $n\lt\omega$, but (the code of) $L_{\omega_\omega^L}$ does not exist, because
$\omega_\omega^L$ is uncountable in the Feferman-Lévy model, and therefore cannot be coded by a real. Guzicki constructed a model of ${\rm
ZF}$ (again a symmetric submodel of a forcing extension) whose reals are a model satisfying ${\rm Z}_2+{\rm AC}^{-p}$ in which ${\rm AC}$ fails
&lt;a href=&quot;#guzicki:choiceScheme&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;, separating the two principles. Recently Lyubetsky and Kanovei showed how to obtain these results
involving ${\rm AC}^{-p}$ starting with a model of ${\rm Z}_2$ instead of ${\rm ZFC}$ &lt;a href=&quot;#LyubetskyKanovei:parameterFreeChoice&quot;&gt;[7]&lt;/a&gt;.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Vladimir Kanovei suggested that I should try to construct a model of ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}+{\rm AC}^{-p}$ together with $\Sigma^1_2$-comprehension in which there is a failure of $\Sigma^1_3$-comprehension. However, the best I was able to get is the following theorem.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;:
It is consistent that there is a model of ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}+{\rm AC}^{-p}$ together with $\Sigma^1_2$-comprehension in which there is a failure of
$\Sigma^1_4$-comprehension.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A set existence principle closely related to the choice scheme is the collection scheme ${\rm Coll}$, which asserts for every second-order formula $\varphi(n,X,A)$ (with set parameter $A$) that if for every $n$, there is a set $X$ such that $\varphi(n,X,A)$ holds, then there is a set $Y$ whose slices are a collecting set for the witnesses $X$. A slice of $Y$ may not be one of the witnesses and a witness for $n$ may be on some slice $m\neq n$. It is easy to see that over ${\rm Z}_2$, ${\rm Coll}$ is equivalent to ${\rm AC}$. Over ${\rm ACA}_0$, ${\rm Coll}$ implies ${\rm Z}_2$, and hence, over ${\rm ACA}_0$, ${\rm Coll}$ is equivalent to ${\rm AC}$. Let ${\rm Coll}^{-p}$ be the parameter-free collection scheme.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;:
It is consistent that there is a model of ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}+{\rm Coll}^{-p}$ together with $\Sigma^1_2$-comprehension in which there is a failure of
$\Sigma^1_4$-comprehension and a failure of ${\rm AC}^{-p}$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
 Thus, we get:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;:
The schemes ${\rm Coll}^{-p}$ and ${\rm AC}^{-p}$ are not equivalent over $\rm Z_2^{-p}$. 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Friedman:parameterFreeComprehension&quot;&gt;H. Friedman, “On the necessary use of abstract set theory,” &lt;i&gt;Adv. in Math.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 41, no. 3, pp. 209–280, 1981. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1016/0001-8708(81)90021-9&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;LyubetskyKanovei:parameterFreeComprehension&quot;&gt;V. Kanovei and V. Lyubetsky, “The parameterfree Comprehension does not imply the full Comprehension in the 2nd order Peano arithmetic,” &lt;i&gt;Manuscript&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;jensen:real&quot;&gt;R. Jensen, “Definable sets of minimal degree,” in &lt;i&gt;Mathematical logic and foundations of set theory (Proc.
              Internat. Colloq., Jerusalem, 1968)&lt;/i&gt;, North-Holland, Amsterdam, 1970, pp. 122–128. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;simpson:second-orderArithmetic&quot;&gt;S. G. Simpson, &lt;i&gt;Subsystems of second order arithmetic&lt;/i&gt;, Second. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge; Association for
              Symbolic Logic, Poughkeepsie, NY, 2009, p. xvi+444. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;levy:choicescheme&quot;&gt;A. Lévy, “Definability in axiomatic set theory. II,” in &lt;i&gt;Mathematical Logic and Foundations of Set Theory
              (Proc. Internat. Colloq., Jerusalem, 1968)&lt;/i&gt;, North-Holland, Amsterdam, 1970, pp. 129–145. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;guzicki:choiceScheme&quot;&gt;W. Guzicki, “On weaker forms of choice in second order arithmetic,” &lt;i&gt;Fund. Math.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 93, no. 2, pp. 131–144, 1976. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;LyubetskyKanovei:parameterFreeChoice&quot;&gt;V. Kanovei and V. Lyubetsky, “On the Significance of Parameters in the Choice and Collection Schemata in the 2nd Order Peano Arithmetic,” &lt;i&gt;Mathematics&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 11, no. 3, p. 726, 2023. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">{% reference page.ref %} The strength of a second-order arithmetic theory depends mostly on the amount of comprehension that the theory admits. A comprehension scheme specifies which formulas give collections that turn out to be sets in the model. At the lower extreme, the second-order theory ${\rm ACA}_0$ includes comprehension for all first-order formulas and at the higher extreme, full second-order arithmetic ${\rm Z}_2$ includes comprehension for all (second-order) formulas. In between, we have $\Sigma^1_n$-comprehension schemes for second-order formulas of complexity $\Sigma^1_n$ ($n$ alternations of set quantifiers followed by a first-order formula). A precise formulation of these comprehension schemes should mention that the specified formulas are allowed to use set parameters from the model. But how significant really are parameters in comprehension? What if we formulate the comprehension schemes without parameters, do we get equivalent theories, perhaps, equiconsistent theories? Let ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}$ be the version of full second-order arithmetic ${\rm Z}_2$, where we do not allow parameters in the comprehension scheme. Friedman showed in {% cite Friedman:parameterFreeComprehension %} (Lemma 3.1.7) that given a model of ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}$, we can appropriately restrict its sets to get a model of ${\rm Z}_2$. Thus, the theories ${\rm Z}_2$ and ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}$ are equiconsistent. In a recent work {% cite LyubetskyKanovei:parameterFreeComprehension %}, Lyubetsky and Kanovei separated the theories ${\rm Z}_2$ and ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}$ by constructing models of ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}$ with various failures of comprehension with parameters. They constructed a model of ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}$ in which the sets were not even closed under complement, showing that comprehension without parameters does not even give comprehension with parameters for $\Sigma^0_0$-assertions. They next considered whether it was possible to have a model of ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}$ with enough comprehension with parameters to carry out most standard constructions, but still have comprehension with parameters fail somewhere above. They argued that a reasonable amount of comprehension with parameters for general mathematical purposes is the $\Sigma^1_2$-comprehension scheme and constructed a model of ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}$ with the $\Sigma^1_2$-comprehension scheme and a failure of $\Sigma^1_4$-comprehension. The model was constructed in a forcing extension by a (non-linear) tree iteration of Sacks forcing. Lyubetsky and Kanovei asked whether the result can be improved to obtain the optimal failure of $\Sigma^1_3$-comprehension {% cite LyubetskyKanovei:parameterFreeComprehension %} (Problem 8.2). In this article, I answer their question positively by constructing a model with the required properties, similarly to how the model of {% cite LyubetskyKanovei:parameterFreeComprehension %} was constructed, in a forcing extension by a tree iteration of Jensen's forcing. Jensen's forcing is a subposet of Sacks forcing constructed in $L$ using the $\diamondsuit$-principle. Jensen's forcing has the ccc and adds a unique generic real whose singleton is $\Pi^1_2$-definable. A similar forcing can be constructed in any universe in which the $\diamondsuit$-principle holds, not just in $L$, and we retain its properties except for, possibly, $\Pi^1_2$-definability of the generic singleton. Jensen originally introduced the forcing because it gives a forcing extension of $L$ in which there is a $\Pi^1_2$-definable non-constructible singleton real {% cite jensen:real %}. Theorem: It is consistent that there is a model of ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}$ together with $\Sigma^1_2$-comprehension and a failure of $\Sigma^1_3$-comprehension. If the first-order part of a second-order arithmetic model satisfies ${\rm PA}$, then via Gödel's pairing function, we can view any set in the model as a collection of $n$-tuples, for some $n\lt\omega$, of elements of the model. Among these collections are orderings of the first-order domain of the model, which the model believes are well-orders. In a model of ${\rm Z}_2$, these well-orders are comparable in that given any two of them, there is a set coding an isomorphism of one of them with an initial segment of the other. Using coding, a model of ${\rm Z}_2$ can construct an initial segment of the $L$-hierarchy along any of its well-orders, and these initial segments are similarly coherent (for details of the construction, see {% cite simpson:second-orderArithmetic %} (Chapter VII)). We will call a real of a model of ${\rm Z}_2$ constructible if it appears in an initial segment of the $L$-hierarchy of the model. Similarly, in a model of ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}$, we can show that any two definable without parameters well-orders are comparable and we can construct an initial segment of the $L$-hierarchy along any such well-order so that the resulting structures are coherent. We will call a real of a model of ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}$ constructible if it appears in an initial segment of the $L$-hierarchy constructed along a definable without parameters well-order. The theory ${\rm Z}_2$ can be further strengthened by adding the choice scheme ${\rm AC}$, which is a set choice principle asserting for every second-order formula $\varphi(n,X,A)$ (with set parameter $A$) that if for every $n$, there is a set $X$ such that $\varphi(n,X,A)$ holds, then there is a single set $Y$ whose $n$-th slice $Y_n$ is a witness for $n$. It is not difficult to see that the scheme ${\rm AC}$ actually implies ${\rm Z}_2$ over ${\rm ACA}_0$. The collection of the constructible reals of a model of ${\rm Z}_2$ satisfies ${\rm Z}_2+{\rm AC}$ (see {% cite simpson:second-orderArithmetic %}, Section VII.6), giving that the two theories are equiconsistent. Friedman's sub-collection of a model of ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}$, which he showed satisfies ${\rm Z}_2$, was precisely the constructible reals of the model, as defined above, coming from the initial segments of the $L$-hierarchy constructed along definable without parameters well-orders. His argument additionally showed that the collection of the constructible reals satisfies ${\rm AC}$. Thus, the theories ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}$ and ${\rm Z}_2+{\rm AC}$ are equiconsistent. Let ${\rm AC}^{-p}$ denote the parameter-free choice scheme. Because standard arguments that the choice scheme ${\rm AC}$ implies comprehension over ${\rm ACA}_0$ require parameters, it is probably not the case that ${\rm AC}^{-p}$ implies ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}$ over ${\rm ACA}_0$. The reals of the Feferman-Lévy model of ${\rm ZF}$ (a symmetric submodel of a forcing extension), in which $\omega_1^L$ is countable for every $n\lt\omega$ and $\omega_\omega^L$ is the first uncountable cardinal {%cite levy:choicescheme %}, is a model of ${\rm Z}_2$ in which ${\rm AC}^{-p}$ fails. In this model (the code of) $L_{\omega_n^L}$ exists for every $n\lt\omega$, but (the code of) $L_{\omega_\omega^L}$ does not exist, because $\omega_\omega^L$ is uncountable in the Feferman-Lévy model, and therefore cannot be coded by a real. Guzicki constructed a model of ${\rm ZF}$ (again a symmetric submodel of a forcing extension) whose reals are a model satisfying ${\rm Z}_2+{\rm AC}^{-p}$ in which ${\rm AC}$ fails {% cite guzicki:choiceScheme %}, separating the two principles. Recently Lyubetsky and Kanovei showed how to obtain these results involving ${\rm AC}^{-p}$ starting with a model of ${\rm Z}_2$ instead of ${\rm ZFC}$ {% cite LyubetskyKanovei:parameterFreeChoice %}. Vladimir Kanovei suggested that I should try to construct a model of ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}+{\rm AC}^{-p}$ together with $\Sigma^1_2$-comprehension in which there is a failure of $\Sigma^1_3$-comprehension. However, the best I was able to get is the following theorem. Theorem: It is consistent that there is a model of ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}+{\rm AC}^{-p}$ together with $\Sigma^1_2$-comprehension in which there is a failure of $\Sigma^1_4$-comprehension. A set existence principle closely related to the choice scheme is the collection scheme ${\rm Coll}$, which asserts for every second-order formula $\varphi(n,X,A)$ (with set parameter $A$) that if for every $n$, there is a set $X$ such that $\varphi(n,X,A)$ holds, then there is a set $Y$ whose slices are a collecting set for the witnesses $X$. A slice of $Y$ may not be one of the witnesses and a witness for $n$ may be on some slice $m\neq n$. It is easy to see that over ${\rm Z}_2$, ${\rm Coll}$ is equivalent to ${\rm AC}$. Over ${\rm ACA}_0$, ${\rm Coll}$ implies ${\rm Z}_2$, and hence, over ${\rm ACA}_0$, ${\rm Coll}$ is equivalent to ${\rm AC}$. Let ${\rm Coll}^{-p}$ be the parameter-free collection scheme. Theorem: It is consistent that there is a model of ${\rm Z}_2^{-p}+{\rm Coll}^{-p}$ together with $\Sigma^1_2$-comprehension in which there is a failure of $\Sigma^1_4$-comprehension and a failure of ${\rm AC}^{-p}$. Thus, we get: Theorem: The schemes ${\rm Coll}^{-p}$ and ${\rm AC}^{-p}$ are not equivalent over $\rm Z_2^{-p}$. References {% bibliography --cited %}</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Cardinal correct extendible cardinals</title><link href="/research/2023/12/19/cardinal-correct-extendible-cardinals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cardinal correct extendible cardinals" /><published>2023-12-19T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-12-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/research/2023/12/19/cardinal-correct-extendible-cardinals</id><content type="html" xml:base="/research/2023/12/19/cardinal-correct-extendible-cardinals.html">&lt;p&gt;
There is little argument out there that first-order logic is the best candidate for the formal system underlying mathematical reasoning. No formal system exists entirely outside of the mathematics it tries to formalize, but first-order logic uses a very small fragment of the background set theoretic universe - only that recursion works on the natural numbers. It also has many almost magical properties such as the Compactness theorem and the downward and upward Löwenheim-Skolem theorems. In fact, by Lindström's theorem, first-order logic is unique among the logics satisfying both the Compactness and the downward Löwenheim-Skolem theorems &lt;a href=&quot;#ChangKeisler:ModelTheory&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. The other classical logics studied by set theorists, such as infinitary logics or second-order logic, are much too strong to be compact. But there is a more general notion of compactness that they can satisfy, and surprisingly whether these strong logics have the generalized compactness depends on which large cardinals exist in the universe. A cardinal $\kappa$ is a &lt;em&gt;strong compactness cardinal&lt;/em&gt; for a logic $\mathcal L$ if every $\lt\kappa$-satisfiable $\mathcal L$-theory is satisfiable. Tarski was the first to make a connection between strong compactness cardinals and large cardinals when he showed that a cardinal $\kappa$ is a strong compactness cardinal for the infinitary logic $\mathbb L_{\kappa,\kappa}$ if and only if $\kappa$ is strongly compact &lt;a href=&quot;#Tarski:compactness&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. Magidor showed that the least strong compactness cardinal for second-order logic $\mathbb L^2$ is the least extendible cardinal (least is important here because of the observation that if $\kappa$ is a strong compactness cardinal for $\mathcal L$, then every $\gamma&gt;\kappa$ is also a strong compactness cardinal) &lt;a href=&quot;#Magidor:Logics&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;. Magidor also showed that a cardinal $\kappa$ is a strong compactness cardinal for the infinitary logic $\mathbb L_{\omega_1,\omega_1}$ or the well-foundedness logic $\mathbb L(Q^{WF})$ (having the quatifier for identifying well-founded definable relations) if and only if $\kappa$ is $\omega_1$-strongly compact (every $\kappa$-complete filter can be extended to a countably complete ultrafilter). The most intractible logic in terms of characterizing its strong compactness cardinals has proven to be the equicardinality logic $\mathbb L(I)$ (having the quantifier for identifying whether two definable collections have the same cardinality). Very little was known until recently about the strong compactness cardinals for $\mathbb L(I)$. In a joint work with Jonathan Osinski, we introduce a new large cardinal notion that is naturally connected to the niceness properties of $\mathbb L(I)$ &lt;a href=&quot;#GitmanOsinski:ULS&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt; (see this &lt;a href=&quot;/publications/2023/12/14/upward-lowenheim-skolem-numbers-for-abstract-logics.html&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Goldberg and Thei recently showed that (assuming the existence of a strongly compact cardinal) it is inconsistent to have an elementary embedding $j:V\to M$, where $M$ is an inner model that is correct about the cardinals (see this &lt;a href=&quot;https://nylogic.github.io/set-theory-seminar/2023/04/14/cardinal-preserving-embeddings-and-strongly-compact-cardinals.html&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt;). But let's consider a set version of this inconsistent large cardinal property. We define that a cardinal $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;cardinal correct extendible&lt;/em&gt; if for every $\alpha&gt;\kappa$, there is an elementary embedding $j:V_\alpha\to M$ with $\text{crit}(j)=\kappa$, $j(\kappa)&gt;\alpha$ and $M$ correct about cardinals. For example, extendible cardinals are clearly cardinal correct extendible. It is not difficult to show that a cardinal correct extendible $\kappa$ is strongly compact &lt;a href=&quot;#GitmanOsinski:ULS&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;. It is at least consistent that the least cardinal correct extendible is above the least supercompact cardinal (this result was pointed out to us by Alejandro Poveda, but we give a generalized argument in &lt;a href=&quot;#GitmanOsinski:ULS&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;). So, in particular, supercompact cardinals are not always cardinal correct extendible. But there are many interesting and seemingly difficult questions about this new large cardinal notion. While the assumption that $j(\kappa)&gt;\alpha$ comes for free in the case of extendible cardinals, we don't know whether this is the case with cardinal correct extendibles. So we make the following two other definitions in case they don't all turn out to be equivalent. We define that a cardinal $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;weakly cardinal correct extendible&lt;/em&gt; if we remove the assumption that $j(\kappa)&gt;\alpha$. A weakly cardinal correct extendible $\kappa$ is either strongly compact or $j(\kappa)$ is inaccessible and $V_{j(\kappa)}$ is a model with a strongly compact cardinal. If $\kappa$ is weakly cardinal correct extendible, but not cardinal correct extendible, then there must be some ordinal $\gamma$ such that for every $\alpha&gt;\kappa$ and embedding $j:V_\alpha\to M$ with $\text{crit}(j)=\kappa$ and $M$ correct about cardinals, $j^n(\kappa)\lt\gamma$ for every $n\lt\omega$. It is not clear whether this situation is even consistent. Finally, we define that $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;cardinal correct extendible pushing up some $\delta\geq\kappa$&lt;/em&gt; if for every $\alpha&gt;\delta$, there is $j:V_\alpha\to M$ with $\text{crit}(j)=\kappa$, $j(\delta)&gt;\alpha$ and $M$ correct about cardinals. In other words, the embeddings may not map $\kappa$ arbitrarily high, but they do map $\delta$ arbitrarily high. This last version of the large cardinal is particularly important in the context of the properites of the logic $\mathbb L(I)$.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt; Here are some other questions we have about cardinal correct extendibles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Question&lt;/strong&gt;: Is every cardinal correct extendible actually extendible? (unlikely)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Question&lt;/strong&gt;: Are cardinal correct extendibles and extendibles equiconsistent? (possible)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question&lt;/strong&gt;: Can the least cardinal correct extendible be the least measurable? (possible)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So how did this large cardinal notion come up in the first place? With Jonathan Osinski, we considered upward Löwenheim-Skolem properties for general logics. The following weak version of the upward Löwenheim-Skolem theorem holds for every logic. The &lt;em&gt;Hanf number&lt;/em&gt; of a logic $\mathcal L$ is the least cardinal $\delta$ such that for every $\mathcal L$-sentence $\varphi$ if there is a model $M\models\varphi$ of size at least $\delta$, then there are models of $\varphi$ of arbitrarily large cardinalities. It is a theorem of ${\rm ZFC}$ that every logic has a Hanf number. Galeotti, Khomskii and Väänänen strengthened the notion of the Hanf number by adding the requirement that the arbitarily large models of $\varphi$ had $M$ as a (not necessarily elementary) substructure and called the stronger notion the &lt;em&gt;upward Löwenheim-Skolem number&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#GaleottiKhomskiiVaananen:upwardLowenheimSkolem&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;. They showed that if $\mathbb L^2$ had an upward Löwenheim-Skolem number, then there was a partially extendible cardinal, thus showing that unlike the Hanf number, the existence of the upward Löwenheim-Skolem number could have large cardinal strength. We also considered the full generalized version of the upward Löwenheim-Skolem theorem by defining that a &lt;em&gt;strong upward Löwenheim-Skolem number&lt;/em&gt; of a logic $\mathcal L$ is the least cardinal $\delta$ such that if $M$ is a model of size at least $\delta$, then it has elementary superstructures of arbitrarily large cardinalities. We were able to characterize the upward Löwenheim-Skolem and the strong upward Löwenheim-Skolem numbers of several classical logics such as second-order logic, well-foundedness logic, infinitary logics, and sort logics. The hardest turned out, not suprisingly, to be once again the equicardinality logic. We showed that if there is a cardinal correct extendible cardinal $\kappa$ pushing up some $\delta\geq\kappa$, then the strong upward Löwenheim-Skolem number for $\mathbb L(I)$ exists and is bounded by $\delta$. We also showed that if the upward Löwenheim-Skolem number for $\mathbb L(I)$ exists, then there is a cardinal $\kappa$ and some $\delta\geq\kappa$ such that $\kappa$ is cardinal correct extendible pushing up $\delta$. Finally, we showed that a strong compactness cardinal for $\mathbb L(I)$ is a mixture of cardinal correct extendible and $\delta$-strongly compact.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem:&lt;/strong&gt; For every $\gamma &gt; \delta$ there is $\alpha \geq \gamma$, a transitive set $M$ and an elementary embedding $j: V_\alpha \rightarrow M$ such that $M$ is cardinal correct, $\text{crit}(j) \leq \delta$ and there exists $d \in M$ such that $j''\gamma \subseteq d$ and $M \models |d| \lt j(\delta)$.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;ChangKeisler:ModelTheory&quot;&gt;C. C. Chang and H. J. Keisler, &lt;i&gt;Model theory&lt;/i&gt;, Third., vol. 73. North-Holland Publishing Co., Amsterdam, 1990, p. xvi+650. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Tarski:compactness&quot;&gt;A. Tarski, “Some problems and results relevant to the foundations of set theory,” in &lt;i&gt;Logic, Methodology and Philosophy of Science, Proceedings of the 1960 International Congress&lt;/i&gt;, 1962. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Magidor:Logics&quot;&gt;M. Magidor, “On the role of supercompact and extendible cardinals in logic,” &lt;i&gt;Israel Journal of Mathematics&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 10, pp. 147–157, 1971. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;GitmanOsinski:ULS&quot;&gt;V. Gitman and J. Osinski, “Upward Löwenheim-Skolem numbers for abstract logics,” &lt;i&gt;Manuscript&lt;/i&gt;, 2023. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;GaleottiKhomskiiVaananen:upwardLowenheimSkolem&quot;&gt;L. Galeotti, Y. Khomskii, and J. Väänänen, “Bounded Symbiosis and Upwards Reflection,” &lt;i&gt;Manuscript&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">There is little argument out there that first-order logic is the best candidate for the formal system underlying mathematical reasoning. No formal system exists entirely outside of the mathematics it tries to formalize, but first-order logic uses a very small fragment of the background set theoretic universe - only that recursion works on the natural numbers. It also has many almost magical properties such as the Compactness theorem and the downward and upward Löwenheim-Skolem theorems. In fact, by Lindström's theorem, first-order logic is unique among the logics satisfying both the Compactness and the downward Löwenheim-Skolem theorems {% cite ChangKeisler:ModelTheory %}. The other classical logics studied by set theorists, such as infinitary logics or second-order logic, are much too strong to be compact. But there is a more general notion of compactness that they can satisfy, and surprisingly whether these strong logics have the generalized compactness depends on which large cardinals exist in the universe. A cardinal $\kappa$ is a strong compactness cardinal for a logic $\mathcal L$ if every $\lt\kappa$-satisfiable $\mathcal L$-theory is satisfiable. Tarski was the first to make a connection between strong compactness cardinals and large cardinals when he showed that a cardinal $\kappa$ is a strong compactness cardinal for the infinitary logic $\mathbb L_{\kappa,\kappa}$ if and only if $\kappa$ is strongly compact {% cite Tarski:compactness %}. Magidor showed that the least strong compactness cardinal for second-order logic $\mathbb L^2$ is the least extendible cardinal (least is important here because of the observation that if $\kappa$ is a strong compactness cardinal for $\mathcal L$, then every $\gamma&gt;\kappa$ is also a strong compactness cardinal) {% cite Magidor:Logics %}. Magidor also showed that a cardinal $\kappa$ is a strong compactness cardinal for the infinitary logic $\mathbb L_{\omega_1,\omega_1}$ or the well-foundedness logic $\mathbb L(Q^{WF})$ (having the quatifier for identifying well-founded definable relations) if and only if $\kappa$ is $\omega_1$-strongly compact (every $\kappa$-complete filter can be extended to a countably complete ultrafilter). The most intractible logic in terms of characterizing its strong compactness cardinals has proven to be the equicardinality logic $\mathbb L(I)$ (having the quantifier for identifying whether two definable collections have the same cardinality). Very little was known until recently about the strong compactness cardinals for $\mathbb L(I)$. In a joint work with Jonathan Osinski, we introduce a new large cardinal notion that is naturally connected to the niceness properties of $\mathbb L(I)$ {% cite GitmanOsinski:ULS %} (see this post). Goldberg and Thei recently showed that (assuming the existence of a strongly compact cardinal) it is inconsistent to have an elementary embedding $j:V\to M$, where $M$ is an inner model that is correct about the cardinals (see this talk). But let's consider a set version of this inconsistent large cardinal property. We define that a cardinal $\kappa$ is cardinal correct extendible if for every $\alpha&gt;\kappa$, there is an elementary embedding $j:V_\alpha\to M$ with $\text{crit}(j)=\kappa$, $j(\kappa)&gt;\alpha$ and $M$ correct about cardinals. For example, extendible cardinals are clearly cardinal correct extendible. It is not difficult to show that a cardinal correct extendible $\kappa$ is strongly compact {% cite GitmanOsinski:ULS %}. It is at least consistent that the least cardinal correct extendible is above the least supercompact cardinal (this result was pointed out to us by Alejandro Poveda, but we give a generalized argument in {% cite GitmanOsinski:ULS %}). So, in particular, supercompact cardinals are not always cardinal correct extendible. But there are many interesting and seemingly difficult questions about this new large cardinal notion. While the assumption that $j(\kappa)&gt;\alpha$ comes for free in the case of extendible cardinals, we don't know whether this is the case with cardinal correct extendibles. So we make the following two other definitions in case they don't all turn out to be equivalent. We define that a cardinal $\kappa$ is weakly cardinal correct extendible if we remove the assumption that $j(\kappa)&gt;\alpha$. A weakly cardinal correct extendible $\kappa$ is either strongly compact or $j(\kappa)$ is inaccessible and $V_{j(\kappa)}$ is a model with a strongly compact cardinal. If $\kappa$ is weakly cardinal correct extendible, but not cardinal correct extendible, then there must be some ordinal $\gamma$ such that for every $\alpha&gt;\kappa$ and embedding $j:V_\alpha\to M$ with $\text{crit}(j)=\kappa$ and $M$ correct about cardinals, $j^n(\kappa)\lt\gamma$ for every $n\lt\omega$. It is not clear whether this situation is even consistent. Finally, we define that $\kappa$ is cardinal correct extendible pushing up some $\delta\geq\kappa$ if for every $\alpha&gt;\delta$, there is $j:V_\alpha\to M$ with $\text{crit}(j)=\kappa$, $j(\delta)&gt;\alpha$ and $M$ correct about cardinals. In other words, the embeddings may not map $\kappa$ arbitrarily high, but they do map $\delta$ arbitrarily high. This last version of the large cardinal is particularly important in the context of the properites of the logic $\mathbb L(I)$. Here are some other questions we have about cardinal correct extendibles. Question: Is every cardinal correct extendible actually extendible? (unlikely) Question: Are cardinal correct extendibles and extendibles equiconsistent? (possible) Question: Can the least cardinal correct extendible be the least measurable? (possible) So how did this large cardinal notion come up in the first place? With Jonathan Osinski, we considered upward Löwenheim-Skolem properties for general logics. The following weak version of the upward Löwenheim-Skolem theorem holds for every logic. The Hanf number of a logic $\mathcal L$ is the least cardinal $\delta$ such that for every $\mathcal L$-sentence $\varphi$ if there is a model $M\models\varphi$ of size at least $\delta$, then there are models of $\varphi$ of arbitrarily large cardinalities. It is a theorem of ${\rm ZFC}$ that every logic has a Hanf number. Galeotti, Khomskii and Väänänen strengthened the notion of the Hanf number by adding the requirement that the arbitarily large models of $\varphi$ had $M$ as a (not necessarily elementary) substructure and called the stronger notion the upward Löwenheim-Skolem number {% cite GaleottiKhomskiiVaananen:upwardLowenheimSkolem %}. They showed that if $\mathbb L^2$ had an upward Löwenheim-Skolem number, then there was a partially extendible cardinal, thus showing that unlike the Hanf number, the existence of the upward Löwenheim-Skolem number could have large cardinal strength. We also considered the full generalized version of the upward Löwenheim-Skolem theorem by defining that a strong upward Löwenheim-Skolem number of a logic $\mathcal L$ is the least cardinal $\delta$ such that if $M$ is a model of size at least $\delta$, then it has elementary superstructures of arbitrarily large cardinalities. We were able to characterize the upward Löwenheim-Skolem and the strong upward Löwenheim-Skolem numbers of several classical logics such as second-order logic, well-foundedness logic, infinitary logics, and sort logics. The hardest turned out, not suprisingly, to be once again the equicardinality logic. We showed that if there is a cardinal correct extendible cardinal $\kappa$ pushing up some $\delta\geq\kappa$, then the strong upward Löwenheim-Skolem number for $\mathbb L(I)$ exists and is bounded by $\delta$. We also showed that if the upward Löwenheim-Skolem number for $\mathbb L(I)$ exists, then there is a cardinal $\kappa$ and some $\delta\geq\kappa$ such that $\kappa$ is cardinal correct extendible pushing up $\delta$. Finally, we showed that a strong compactness cardinal for $\mathbb L(I)$ is a mixture of cardinal correct extendible and $\delta$-strongly compact. Theorem: For every $\gamma &gt; \delta$ there is $\alpha \geq \gamma$, a transitive set $M$ and an elementary embedding $j: V_\alpha \rightarrow M$ such that $M$ is cardinal correct, $\text{crit}(j) \leq \delta$ and there exists $d \in M$ such that $j''\gamma \subseteq d$ and $M \models |d| \lt j(\delta)$. References {% bibliography --cited %}</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">New large cardinal chart of Ramsey-like cardinals</title><link href="/research/2023/12/18/new-large-cardinal-chart-of-ramsey-like-cardinals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New large cardinal chart of Ramsey-like cardinals" /><published>2023-12-18T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-12-18T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/research/2023/12/18/new-large-cardinal-chart-of-ramsey-like-cardinals</id><content type="html" xml:base="/research/2023/12/18/new-large-cardinal-chart-of-ramsey-like-cardinals.html">&lt;p&gt;In our article &quot;Between Ramsey and Measurable cardinals&quot; with Philipp Schlicht &lt;a href=&quot;#GitmanSchlicht:babyMeasurableCardinals&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; (see this &lt;a href=&quot;/publications/2023/11/20/between-ramsey-and-measurable-cardinals.html&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;), we explored new large cardinal hierarchies between Ramsey and measurable cardinals. Most large cardinal notions $\kappa$ below a measurable cardinal are defined via the following template: for every $A\subseteq \kappa$, there is a transitive model $M$ of size $\kappa$ satisfying ${\rm ZFC}^-$ (${\rm ZFC}$ without powerset) with $V_\kappa\cup\{\kappa\}\subseteq M$ for which there is a (uniform) filter $U$ measuring all subsets of $\kappa$ in $M$ that is normal for $\kappa$-length sequences from $M$ and satisfies some additional niceness properties (e.g. the ultrapower by $U$ is well-founded, $U$ is amenable to $M$, $U$ is iterable, the intersection of any countable collection of elements of $U$ has a non-empty intersection, etc.) While in this scheme, $M$ is a model of the ${\rm ZFC}$ axioms without powerset (and often a model of full ${\rm ZFC}$), the ${\rm ZFC}$ axioms can fail very badly in the structure $\langle M,\in, U\rangle$ together with a predicate for $U$. It turns out that the larger the fragment of ${\rm ZFC}^-$ that the structure $\langle M,\in, U\rangle$ satisfies the stronger the large cardinal axiom given by the above characterization. If $\kappa$ is weakly compact, then the structures $\langle M,\in, U\rangle$ may not even satisfy $\Sigma_0$-separation. If the structures $\langle M,\in, U\rangle$ satisfy $\Sigma_0$-separation, even if the ultrapower is not guaranteed to be well-founded, we get a large cardinal that is larger than a weakly ineffable and consistency-wise stronger than an ineffable. If the structures $\langle M,\in, U\rangle$ satisfy $\Sigma_0$-separation and $\Sigma_0$-collection, we get a large cardinal notion that is much stronger than Ramsey, and, so, in particular, outside of $L$. Some of the new large cardinal notions in this chart arise from considering the characterizations where the structures $\langle M,\in, U\rangle$ satisfy larger and larger fragments of ${\rm ZFC}^-$. Others arise from combining the existence of strong structures $\langle M,\in, U\rangle$ with with game-theoretic properties introduced by Peter Holy and Philipp Schlicht in &lt;a href=&quot;#HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/LargeCardinalChart.jpg&quot; /&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;GitmanSchlicht:babyMeasurableCardinals&quot;&gt;V. Gitman and P. Schlicht, “Between Ramsey and measurable cardinals,” &lt;i&gt;Manuscript&lt;/i&gt;, 2023. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;P. Holy and P. Schlicht, “A hierarchy of Ramsey-like cardinals,” &lt;i&gt;Fund. Math.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 242, no. 1, pp. 49–74, 2018. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">In our article &quot;Between Ramsey and Measurable cardinals&quot; with Philipp Schlicht {% cite GitmanSchlicht:babyMeasurableCardinals %} (see this post), we explored new large cardinal hierarchies between Ramsey and measurable cardinals. Most large cardinal notions $\kappa$ below a measurable cardinal are defined via the following template: for every $A\subseteq \kappa$, there is a transitive model $M$ of size $\kappa$ satisfying ${\rm ZFC}^-$ (${\rm ZFC}$ without powerset) with $V_\kappa\cup\{\kappa\}\subseteq M$ for which there is a (uniform) filter $U$ measuring all subsets of $\kappa$ in $M$ that is normal for $\kappa$-length sequences from $M$ and satisfies some additional niceness properties (e.g. the ultrapower by $U$ is well-founded, $U$ is amenable to $M$, $U$ is iterable, the intersection of any countable collection of elements of $U$ has a non-empty intersection, etc.) While in this scheme, $M$ is a model of the ${\rm ZFC}$ axioms without powerset (and often a model of full ${\rm ZFC}$), the ${\rm ZFC}$ axioms can fail very badly in the structure $\langle M,\in, U\rangle$ together with a predicate for $U$. It turns out that the larger the fragment of ${\rm ZFC}^-$ that the structure $\langle M,\in, U\rangle$ satisfies the stronger the large cardinal axiom given by the above characterization. If $\kappa$ is weakly compact, then the structures $\langle M,\in, U\rangle$ may not even satisfy $\Sigma_0$-separation. If the structures $\langle M,\in, U\rangle$ satisfy $\Sigma_0$-separation, even if the ultrapower is not guaranteed to be well-founded, we get a large cardinal that is larger than a weakly ineffable and consistency-wise stronger than an ineffable. If the structures $\langle M,\in, U\rangle$ satisfy $\Sigma_0$-separation and $\Sigma_0$-collection, we get a large cardinal notion that is much stronger than Ramsey, and, so, in particular, outside of $L$. Some of the new large cardinal notions in this chart arise from considering the characterizations where the structures $\langle M,\in, U\rangle$ satisfy larger and larger fragments of ${\rm ZFC}^-$. Others arise from combining the existence of strong structures $\langle M,\in, U\rangle$ with with game-theoretic properties introduced by Peter Holy and Philipp Schlicht in {% cite HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals%}. References {% bibliography --cited %}</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Upward Löwenheim-Skolem numbers for abstract logics</title><link href="/publications/2023/12/14/upward-lowenheim-skolem-numbers-for-abstract-logics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Upward Löwenheim-Skolem numbers for abstract logics" /><published>2023-12-14T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-12-14T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/publications/2023/12/14/upward-lowenheim-skolem-numbers-for-abstract-logics</id><content type="html" xml:base="/publications/2023/12/14/upward-lowenheim-skolem-numbers-for-abstract-logics.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;GitmanOsinski:ULS&quot;&gt;V. Gitman and J. Osinski, “Upward Löwenheim-Skolem numbers for abstract logics,” &lt;i&gt;Manuscript&lt;/i&gt;, 2023. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We tend to think of first-order logic, the generally accepted system for formalizing mathematics, as existing entirely outside of mathematics. But even first-order logic relies, however minimally, on the set-theoretic background universe in which we work because it uses properties of natural numbers. Tarski's definition of truth, for instance, requires recursion. The dependence on the set-theoretic background becomes more apparent when we consider stronger logics, such as infinitary logics and second-order logic. In these logics, we can express more properties of the models at the cost of having to use higher levels of the set-theoretic universe to define the logic itself. Niceness properties of strong logics have been shown to be connected to and often equivalent to the existence of large cardinals. For many classical strong logics, for instance, the existence of a strong compactness cardinal is equivalent to the existence of some classical large cardinal. In this article, we investigate upwards Löwenheim-Skolem principles for various classical logics and show that these principles are equivalent to the existence of large cardinals, some classical and some new.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;upwards Löwenheim-Skolem Theorem&lt;/em&gt; for first-order logic says that any infinite structure has arbitrarily large elementary superstructures. A very weak version of the upwards Löwenheim-Skolem Theorem holds for all logics. Recall that the &lt;em&gt;Hanf number&lt;/em&gt; of a logic $\mathcal L$ is the least cardinal $\delta$ such that for every language $\tau$ and $\mathcal L(\tau)$-sentence $\varphi$, if a $\tau$-structure $M\models_{\mathcal L}\varphi$ has size $\gamma\geq\delta$, then for every cardinal $\overline\gamma&gt;\gamma$, there is a $\tau$-structure $\overline M$ of size at least $\overline\gamma$ such that $\overline M\models_{\mathcal L}\varphi$. The upwards Löwenheim-Skolem Theorem implies, in particular, that the Hanf number of first-order logic is $\omega$. ${\rm ZFC}$ proves that every logic has a Hanf number (see, for instance, (missing reference)). Galeotti, Khomskii and Väänänen strengthened the notion of the Hanf number by requiring that the model $\overline M\models_{\mathcal L}\varphi$ of size at least $\overline\gamma$ is a (not necessarily elementary) superstructure of $M$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Definition&lt;/strong&gt;: (&lt;a href=&quot;#GaleottiKhomskiiVaananen:upwardLowenheimSkolem&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;)
Fix a logic $\mathcal L$. The &lt;em&gt;upward Löwenheim-Skolem number&lt;/em&gt; ${\rm ULS}(\mathcal L)$, if it exists, is the least cardinal $\delta$ such that for every language $\tau$ and $\mathcal L(\tau)$-sentence $\varphi$, if a $\tau$-structure $M\models_{\mathcal L}\varphi$ has size $\gamma\geq\delta$, then for every cardinal $\overline\gamma&gt;\gamma$, there is a $\tau$-structure $\overline M$ of size at least $\overline\gamma$ such that $\overline M\models_{\mathcal L}\varphi$ and $M\subseteq \overline M$ is a substructure of $\overline M$.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Galeotti, Khomskii and Väänänen showed that the existence of the ${\rm ULS}$ number for second-order logic, ${\rm ULS}(\mathbb L^2)$, implies the existence of very strong large cardinals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;: (&lt;a href=&quot;#GaleottiKhomskiiVaananen:upwardLowenheimSkolem&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;)
If ${\rm ULS}(\mathbb L^2)$ exists, then for every $n \in  \omega$ there is an $n$-extendible cardinal $\lambda \leq {\rm ULS}(\mathbb L^2)$.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
They further conjectured that the strength of the existence of ${\rm ULS}(\mathbb L^2)$ is exactly that of an extendible cardinal. We positively answer their conjecture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;:
If ${\rm ULS}(\mathbb L^2)$ exists, then it is the least extendible cardinal.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

We can further strengthen the notion of the ${\rm ULS}$ number to capture the full power of the upwards Löwenheim-Skolem Theorem.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Definition&lt;/strong&gt;:
Fix a logic $\mathcal L$. The &lt;em&gt;strong upward Löwenheim-Skolem number&lt;/em&gt; ${\rm SULS}(\mathcal L)$, if it exists, is the least cardinal $\delta$ such that for every language $\tau$ and every $\tau$-structure $M$ of size $\gamma\geq\delta$, for every cardinal $\overline\gamma &gt; \gamma$, there is a $\tau$-structure $\overline M$ of size at least $\overline\tau$ such that $M\prec_{\mathcal L} \overline M$ is an $\mathcal L$-elementary substructure of $\overline M$.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Notice that we could equivalently define the strong upward Löwenheim-Skolem number analogously to the upward Löwenheim-Skolem number but preserving theories instead of single sentences.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We pinpoint large cardinal notions that are equivalent to the existence of the ${\rm ULS}$ and strong ${\rm ULS}$ numbers for second-order logic, Väänänen's $\Sigma_n$-sort logics $\mathbb L^{s,n}$, the logic $\mathbb L(Q^{WF})$ - first-order logic augmented with the well-foundedness quantifier, the infinitary logics $\mathbb L_{\kappa,\kappa}$, and the logic $\mathbb L(I)$ - first-order logic augmented with the equicardinality quantifier.


&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;GaleottiKhomskiiVaananen:upwardLowenheimSkolem&quot;&gt;L. Galeotti, Y. Khomskii, and J. Väänänen, “Bounded Symbiosis and Upwards Reflection,” &lt;i&gt;Manuscript&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">{% reference page.ref %} We tend to think of first-order logic, the generally accepted system for formalizing mathematics, as existing entirely outside of mathematics. But even first-order logic relies, however minimally, on the set-theoretic background universe in which we work because it uses properties of natural numbers. Tarski's definition of truth, for instance, requires recursion. The dependence on the set-theoretic background becomes more apparent when we consider stronger logics, such as infinitary logics and second-order logic. In these logics, we can express more properties of the models at the cost of having to use higher levels of the set-theoretic universe to define the logic itself. Niceness properties of strong logics have been shown to be connected to and often equivalent to the existence of large cardinals. For many classical strong logics, for instance, the existence of a strong compactness cardinal is equivalent to the existence of some classical large cardinal. In this article, we investigate upwards Löwenheim-Skolem principles for various classical logics and show that these principles are equivalent to the existence of large cardinals, some classical and some new. The upwards Löwenheim-Skolem Theorem for first-order logic says that any infinite structure has arbitrarily large elementary superstructures. A very weak version of the upwards Löwenheim-Skolem Theorem holds for all logics. Recall that the Hanf number of a logic $\mathcal L$ is the least cardinal $\delta$ such that for every language $\tau$ and $\mathcal L(\tau)$-sentence $\varphi$, if a $\tau$-structure $M\models_{\mathcal L}\varphi$ has size $\gamma\geq\delta$, then for every cardinal $\overline\gamma&gt;\gamma$, there is a $\tau$-structure $\overline M$ of size at least $\overline\gamma$ such that $\overline M\models_{\mathcal L}\varphi$. The upwards Löwenheim-Skolem Theorem implies, in particular, that the Hanf number of first-order logic is $\omega$. ${\rm ZFC}$ proves that every logic has a Hanf number (see, for instance, {% cite Marker:InfinitaryModelTheory %}). Galeotti, Khomskii and Väänänen strengthened the notion of the Hanf number by requiring that the model $\overline M\models_{\mathcal L}\varphi$ of size at least $\overline\gamma$ is a (not necessarily elementary) superstructure of $M$. Definition: ({% cite GaleottiKhomskiiVaananen:upwardLowenheimSkolem %}) Fix a logic $\mathcal L$. The upward Löwenheim-Skolem number ${\rm ULS}(\mathcal L)$, if it exists, is the least cardinal $\delta$ such that for every language $\tau$ and $\mathcal L(\tau)$-sentence $\varphi$, if a $\tau$-structure $M\models_{\mathcal L}\varphi$ has size $\gamma\geq\delta$, then for every cardinal $\overline\gamma&gt;\gamma$, there is a $\tau$-structure $\overline M$ of size at least $\overline\gamma$ such that $\overline M\models_{\mathcal L}\varphi$ and $M\subseteq \overline M$ is a substructure of $\overline M$. Galeotti, Khomskii and Väänänen showed that the existence of the ${\rm ULS}$ number for second-order logic, ${\rm ULS}(\mathbb L^2)$, implies the existence of very strong large cardinals. Theorem: ({% cite GaleottiKhomskiiVaananen:upwardLowenheimSkolem %}) If ${\rm ULS}(\mathbb L^2)$ exists, then for every $n \in \omega$ there is an $n$-extendible cardinal $\lambda \leq {\rm ULS}(\mathbb L^2)$. They further conjectured that the strength of the existence of ${\rm ULS}(\mathbb L^2)$ is exactly that of an extendible cardinal. We positively answer their conjecture. Theorem: If ${\rm ULS}(\mathbb L^2)$ exists, then it is the least extendible cardinal. We can further strengthen the notion of the ${\rm ULS}$ number to capture the full power of the upwards Löwenheim-Skolem Theorem. Definition: Fix a logic $\mathcal L$. The strong upward Löwenheim-Skolem number ${\rm SULS}(\mathcal L)$, if it exists, is the least cardinal $\delta$ such that for every language $\tau$ and every $\tau$-structure $M$ of size $\gamma\geq\delta$, for every cardinal $\overline\gamma &gt; \gamma$, there is a $\tau$-structure $\overline M$ of size at least $\overline\tau$ such that $M\prec_{\mathcal L} \overline M$ is an $\mathcal L$-elementary substructure of $\overline M$. Notice that we could equivalently define the strong upward Löwenheim-Skolem number analogously to the upward Löwenheim-Skolem number but preserving theories instead of single sentences. We pinpoint large cardinal notions that are equivalent to the existence of the ${\rm ULS}$ and strong ${\rm ULS}$ numbers for second-order logic, Väänänen's $\Sigma_n$-sort logics $\mathbb L^{s,n}$, the logic $\mathbb L(Q^{WF})$ - first-order logic augmented with the well-foundedness quantifier, the infinitary logics $\mathbb L_{\kappa,\kappa}$, and the logic $\mathbb L(I)$ - first-order logic augmented with the equicardinality quantifier. References {% bibliography --cited %}</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Between Ramsey and measurable cardinals</title><link href="/publications/2023/11/20/between-ramsey-and-measurable-cardinals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Between Ramsey and measurable cardinals" /><published>2023-11-20T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-11-20T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/publications/2023/11/20/between-ramsey-and-measurable-cardinals</id><content type="html" xml:base="/publications/2023/11/20/between-ramsey-and-measurable-cardinals.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;GitmanSchlicht:babyMeasurableCardinals&quot;&gt;V. Gitman and P. Schlicht, “Between Ramsey and measurable cardinals,” &lt;i&gt;Manuscript&lt;/i&gt;, 2023. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; 
Measurable cardinals and most stronger large cardinals are defined by the existence of elementary embeddings $j:V\to M$ from the universe $V$ into an inner model $M$ with that cardinal as the critical point. Stronger large cardinal axioms impose additional assumptions on the target model $M$ that allow it to capture more and more sets from $V$. Weakly compact and many other smaller large cardinals are defined via combinatorial properties, often involving existence of large homogeneous sets for colorings. But almost all of them also have elementary embedding characterizations that, like the larger large cardinals, follow prescribed patterns as consistency strength grows. These smaller large cardinals $\kappa$ are characterized by elementary embeddings of models $\langle M,\in\rangle\models{\rm ZFC}^-$ of size $\kappa$, most often transitive, with critical point $\kappa$, and usually, but not always, with well-founded targets. ${\rm ZFC}^-$ is the theory ${\rm ZFC}$ with the powerset axiom removed, the collection scheme in place of the replacement scheme, and the version of the axiom of choice which states that every set can be well-ordered.(Without the powerset axiom, collection and replacement schemes are not equivalent and neither are the various forms of the axiom of choice. See &lt;a href=&quot;#zarach:unions_of_zfminus_models&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;#zfcminus:gitmanhamkinsjohnstone&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;.) In many cases, the existence of these embeddings can be equivalently expressed in terms of the existence of certain ultrafilters on the subsets of $\kappa$ contained in $M$.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Suppose $\langle M,\in\rangle \models{\rm ZFC}^-$ is a transitive model of size $\kappa$ with $\kappa\in M$. We call such structures &lt;em&gt;weak $\kappa$-models&lt;/em&gt;. We will call a filter $U$, on the subsets of $\kappa$ of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$, an &lt;em&gt;$M$-ultrafilter&lt;/em&gt; if the structure $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$, together with a predicate for $U$, satisfies that $U$ is a uniform, normal ultrafilter on $\kappa$. What this says is that $U$ is an ultrafilter on the subsets of $\kappa$ that live in $M$ and if a $\kappa$-length sequence of elements of $U$ is an element of $M$, then its diagonal intersection is in $U$. Łoś' Theorem holds for ultrapowers by an $M$-ultrafilter, but the ultrapower need not be well-founded. Note that the filter $U$ may not be countably complete for sequences outside of $M$. The $M$-ultrafilter $U$, is in most interesting cases, external to $M$ and even though $\langle M,\in\rangle\models{\rm ZFC}^-$, separation and replacement can fail completely in the structure $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$ once we let $M$ know about $U$. In the same way that making the inner model $M$ closer to $V$ in the characterizations of larger large cardinals increases strength, for the smaller large cardinals, we increase strength by making $M$ be more compatible with $U$, which amounts to $M$ being more correct about the properties of $U$ or to having more of the ${\rm ZFC}^-$ axioms in the structure $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Let's look at some examples. A cardinal $\kappa$ is weakly compact if and only if it is inaccessible and every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ for which there is an $M$-ultrafilter with a well-founded ultrapower. It turns out that it is equivalent to assume the a priori stronger assertion that every $A\subseteq \kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model for which there is a (externally) countably complete $M$-ultrafilter $U$. In particular, the ultrapower is well-founded. A cardinal $\kappa$ is $1$-iterable if every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ for which there is an $M$-ultrafilter $U$ such that $\la M,\in, U\ra$ satisfies $\Sigma_0$-separation and the ultrapower is well-founded &lt;a href=&quot;#gitman:welch&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;. The $1$-iterable cardinals are stronger than ineffable cardinals, and therefore much stronger than weakly compact cardinals. They are however still compatible with $L$. Thus, the additional requirement that the structure $\langle M,\in, U\rangle$ satisfies $\Sigma_0$-separation pushes up the consistency strength. A cardinal $\kappa$ is Ramsey if and only if every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ for which there is an $M$-ultrafilter $U$ such that $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$ satisfies $\Sigma_0$-separation and which is (externally) countably complete  &lt;a href=&quot;#mitchell:ramsey&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;. Ramsey cardinals sit much higher in the hierarchy than $1$-iterable cardinals. Thus, in particular, in the presence of the requirement of $\Sigma_0$-separation for the structure $\langle M,\in, U\rangle$ for the $M$-ultrafilter $U$, having $U$ be countably complete is much stronger than having it just produce a well-founded ultrapower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In this article, motivated by the work of Bovykin and McKenzie &lt;a href=&quot;#BovykinMcKenzie:RamseyLikeNFUM&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;, we consider a hierarchy of large cardinal notions characterized by the existence, for weak $\kappa$-models $M$, of $M$-ultrafilters $U$ such that the structure $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$ satisfies fragments up to full ${\rm ZFC}^-$. Following Bovykin and McKenzie, we call such cardinals &lt;em&gt;$n$-baby measurable&lt;/em&gt; where the fragment is ${\rm ZFC}^-_n$ (the separation and collection schemes are restricted to $\Sigma_n$-formulas).
Baby measurable cardinals and some variants were introduced by Bovykin and McKenzie in &lt;a href=&quot;#BovykinMcKenzie:RamseyLikeNFUM&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt; and used to obtain the following application to the theory ${\rm NFUM}$.
This theory is a natural strengthening of ${\rm NFU}$ due to Holmes (see &lt;a href=&quot;#BovykinMcKenzie:RamseyLikeNFUM&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;) that aims to facilitate mathematics in ${\rm NFU}$, the latter being a variant of Quine's &lt;em&gt;New Foundations&lt;/em&gt; with Urelements introduced by Jensen.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;: (Bovykin, McKenzie &lt;a href=&quot;#BovykinMcKenzie:RamseyLikeNFUM&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;)
The following theories are equiconsistent.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
${\rm ZFC}$ together with the scheme consisting of the assertions for every $n\in \omega$:&lt;br&gt;
&lt;p align=&quot;center&quot;&gt;There exists an $n$-baby measurable cardinal $\kappa$ such that $V_\kappa\prec_{\Sigma_n} V$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; ${\rm NFUM}$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We show in that increasing levels of collection and separation for the structures $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$ increase the large cardinal strength. For example, adding even $\Sigma_0$-replacement to the characterization of $1$-iterable cardinals pushes consistency strength well beyond a Ramsey cardinal, and hence beyond $L$. We then provide a fine analysis of the resulting hierarchies.
Surprisingly, the closure of the models does not play a role when working solely with fragments of collection.
However, closure conditions do induce a strict hierarchy for the setting of ${\rm ZFC}^-_n$ with both the collection and separation schemes restricted to $\Sigma_n$-formulas.
We show this with the help of filter games resembling those introduced by Holy and the second-listed author &lt;a href=&quot;#HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;. We thus arrive at similar patterns of large cardinal notions as the one around strongly Ramsey cardinals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/images/babyMeasChart.jpg&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We show that some of these new large cardinal notions are robust under forcing. Finally, we will see that these notions are naturally connected to models of Kelley-Morse set theory in which ${\rm Ord}$ is measurable and help us to understand the structure of these second-order models.
In particular, we apply the above methods to show that the theory of structures of the form $V_\kappa^M$, where $M$ is a model of ${\rm ZFC}^-$ or ${\rm ZFC}$ where $\kappa$ is measurable, is axiomatizable by the existence of large cardinals similar to the ones above.
These results shed light on the large cardinal hierarchy below measurable cardinals and provide a blueprint how to approximate a large cardinal notion from below by a natural hierarchy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;zarach:unions_of_zfminus_models&quot;&gt;A. Zarach, “Unions of ${\rm ZF}^{-}$-models which are themselves
              ${\rm ZF}^{-}$-models,” in &lt;i&gt;Logic Colloquium ’80 (Prague, 1980)&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 108, Amsterdam: North-Holland, 1982, pp. 315–342. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;zfcminus:gitmanhamkinsjohnstone&quot;&gt;V. Gitman, J. D. Hamkins, and T. A. Johnstone, “What is the theory $\mathsf {ZFC}$ without power set?,” &lt;i&gt;MLQ Math. Log. Q.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 62, no. 4-5, pp. 391–406, 2016. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;gitman:welch&quot;&gt;V. Gitman and P. D. Welch, “Ramsey-like cardinals II,” &lt;i&gt;The Journal of Symbolic Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 76, no. 2, pp. 541–560, 2011. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;mitchell:ramsey&quot;&gt;W. Mitchell, “Ramsey cardinals and constructibility,” &lt;i&gt;J. Symbolic Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 44, no. 2, pp. 260–266, 1979. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;BovykinMcKenzie:RamseyLikeNFUM&quot;&gt;A. Bovykin and Z. McKenzie, “Ramsey-like cardinals that characterize the exact consistency strength of NFUM,” &lt;i&gt;Manuscript&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;P. Holy and P. Schlicht, “A hierarchy of Ramsey-like cardinals,” &lt;i&gt;Fund. Math.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 242, no. 1, pp. 49–74, 2018. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">{% reference page.ref %} Measurable cardinals and most stronger large cardinals are defined by the existence of elementary embeddings $j:V\to M$ from the universe $V$ into an inner model $M$ with that cardinal as the critical point. Stronger large cardinal axioms impose additional assumptions on the target model $M$ that allow it to capture more and more sets from $V$. Weakly compact and many other smaller large cardinals are defined via combinatorial properties, often involving existence of large homogeneous sets for colorings. But almost all of them also have elementary embedding characterizations that, like the larger large cardinals, follow prescribed patterns as consistency strength grows. These smaller large cardinals $\kappa$ are characterized by elementary embeddings of models $\langle M,\in\rangle\models{\rm ZFC}^-$ of size $\kappa$, most often transitive, with critical point $\kappa$, and usually, but not always, with well-founded targets. ${\rm ZFC}^-$ is the theory ${\rm ZFC}$ with the powerset axiom removed, the collection scheme in place of the replacement scheme, and the version of the axiom of choice which states that every set can be well-ordered.(Without the powerset axiom, collection and replacement schemes are not equivalent and neither are the various forms of the axiom of choice. See {% cite zarach:unions_of_zfminus_models %} and {% cite zfcminus:gitmanhamkinsjohnstone %}.) In many cases, the existence of these embeddings can be equivalently expressed in terms of the existence of certain ultrafilters on the subsets of $\kappa$ contained in $M$. Suppose $\langle M,\in\rangle \models{\rm ZFC}^-$ is a transitive model of size $\kappa$ with $\kappa\in M$. We call such structures weak $\kappa$-models. We will call a filter $U$, on the subsets of $\kappa$ of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$, an $M$-ultrafilter if the structure $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$, together with a predicate for $U$, satisfies that $U$ is a uniform, normal ultrafilter on $\kappa$. What this says is that $U$ is an ultrafilter on the subsets of $\kappa$ that live in $M$ and if a $\kappa$-length sequence of elements of $U$ is an element of $M$, then its diagonal intersection is in $U$. Łoś' Theorem holds for ultrapowers by an $M$-ultrafilter, but the ultrapower need not be well-founded. Note that the filter $U$ may not be countably complete for sequences outside of $M$. The $M$-ultrafilter $U$, is in most interesting cases, external to $M$ and even though $\langle M,\in\rangle\models{\rm ZFC}^-$, separation and replacement can fail completely in the structure $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$ once we let $M$ know about $U$. In the same way that making the inner model $M$ closer to $V$ in the characterizations of larger large cardinals increases strength, for the smaller large cardinals, we increase strength by making $M$ be more compatible with $U$, which amounts to $M$ being more correct about the properties of $U$ or to having more of the ${\rm ZFC}^-$ axioms in the structure $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$. Let's look at some examples. A cardinal $\kappa$ is weakly compact if and only if it is inaccessible and every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ for which there is an $M$-ultrafilter with a well-founded ultrapower. It turns out that it is equivalent to assume the a priori stronger assertion that every $A\subseteq \kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model for which there is a (externally) countably complete $M$-ultrafilter $U$. In particular, the ultrapower is well-founded. A cardinal $\kappa$ is $1$-iterable if every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ for which there is an $M$-ultrafilter $U$ such that $\la M,\in, U\ra$ satisfies $\Sigma_0$-separation and the ultrapower is well-founded {% cite gitman:welch %}. The $1$-iterable cardinals are stronger than ineffable cardinals, and therefore much stronger than weakly compact cardinals. They are however still compatible with $L$. Thus, the additional requirement that the structure $\langle M,\in, U\rangle$ satisfies $\Sigma_0$-separation pushes up the consistency strength. A cardinal $\kappa$ is Ramsey if and only if every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ for which there is an $M$-ultrafilter $U$ such that $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$ satisfies $\Sigma_0$-separation and which is (externally) countably complete {% cite mitchell:ramsey %}. Ramsey cardinals sit much higher in the hierarchy than $1$-iterable cardinals. Thus, in particular, in the presence of the requirement of $\Sigma_0$-separation for the structure $\langle M,\in, U\rangle$ for the $M$-ultrafilter $U$, having $U$ be countably complete is much stronger than having it just produce a well-founded ultrapower. In this article, motivated by the work of Bovykin and McKenzie {% cite BovykinMcKenzie:RamseyLikeNFUM %}, we consider a hierarchy of large cardinal notions characterized by the existence, for weak $\kappa$-models $M$, of $M$-ultrafilters $U$ such that the structure $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$ satisfies fragments up to full ${\rm ZFC}^-$. Following Bovykin and McKenzie, we call such cardinals $n$-baby measurable where the fragment is ${\rm ZFC}^-_n$ (the separation and collection schemes are restricted to $\Sigma_n$-formulas). Baby measurable cardinals and some variants were introduced by Bovykin and McKenzie in {% cite BovykinMcKenzie:RamseyLikeNFUM %} and used to obtain the following application to the theory ${\rm NFUM}$. This theory is a natural strengthening of ${\rm NFU}$ due to Holmes (see {% cite BovykinMcKenzie:RamseyLikeNFUM %}) that aims to facilitate mathematics in ${\rm NFU}$, the latter being a variant of Quine's New Foundations with Urelements introduced by Jensen. Theorem: (Bovykin, McKenzie {% cite BovykinMcKenzie:RamseyLikeNFUM %}) The following theories are equiconsistent. ${\rm ZFC}$ together with the scheme consisting of the assertions for every $n\in \omega$: There exists an $n$-baby measurable cardinal $\kappa$ such that $V_\kappa\prec_{\Sigma_n} V$. ${\rm NFUM}$ We show in that increasing levels of collection and separation for the structures $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$ increase the large cardinal strength. For example, adding even $\Sigma_0$-replacement to the characterization of $1$-iterable cardinals pushes consistency strength well beyond a Ramsey cardinal, and hence beyond $L$. We then provide a fine analysis of the resulting hierarchies. Surprisingly, the closure of the models does not play a role when working solely with fragments of collection. However, closure conditions do induce a strict hierarchy for the setting of ${\rm ZFC}^-_n$ with both the collection and separation schemes restricted to $\Sigma_n$-formulas. We show this with the help of filter games resembling those introduced by Holy and the second-listed author {% cite HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals %}. We thus arrive at similar patterns of large cardinal notions as the one around strongly Ramsey cardinals. We show that some of these new large cardinal notions are robust under forcing. Finally, we will see that these notions are naturally connected to models of Kelley-Morse set theory in which ${\rm Ord}$ is measurable and help us to understand the structure of these second-order models. In particular, we apply the above methods to show that the theory of structures of the form $V_\kappa^M$, where $M$ is a model of ${\rm ZFC}^-$ or ${\rm ZFC}$ where $\kappa$ is measurable, is axiomatizable by the existence of large cardinals similar to the ones above. These results shed light on the large cardinal hierarchy below measurable cardinals and provide a blueprint how to approximate a large cardinal notion from below by a natural hierarchy. References {% bibliography --cited %}</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Upward Löwenheim-Skolem numbers for abstract logics</title><link href="/talks/2023/11/10/upward-lowenheim-skolem-numbers-for-abstract-logics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Upward Löwenheim-Skolem numbers for abstract logics" /><published>2023-11-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2023-11-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/talks/2023/11/10/upward-lowenheim-skolem-numbers-for-abstract-logics</id><content type="html" xml:base="/talks/2023/11/10/upward-lowenheim-skolem-numbers-for-abstract-logics.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the CUNY Logic Workshop, CUNY Graduate Center, November 10, 2023.&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/ULSTalk.pdf&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Galeotti, Khomskii and Väänänen recently introduced the notion of the upward Löwenheim Skolem (ULS) number for an abstract logic. A cardinal $\kappa$ is the upward Lowenheim Skolem number for a logic $\mathcal L$ if it is the least cardinal with the property that whenever $M$ is a model of size at least $\kappa$ satisfying a sentence $\varphi$ in $\mathcal L$, then there are arbitrarily large models $N$ satisfying $\varphi$ and having $M$ as a substructure (not necessarily elementary). If we remove the requirement that $M$ has to be a substructure of $N$, we get the classic notion of a Hanf number. While $\rm ZFC$ proves that every logic has a Hanf number, having a ULS number often turns out to have large cardinal strength. In a joint work with Jonathan Osinski, we study the ULS numbers for several classical logics. We introduce a strengthening of the ULS number, the strong upward Löwenheim Skolem number SULS which strengthens the requirement that $M$ is a substructure to full elementarity in the logic $\mathcal L$. It is easy to see that both the ULS and the SULS number for a logic $\mathcal L$ are bounded by the least strong compactness cardinal for $\mathcal L$, if it exists. 
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the CUNY Logic Workshop, CUNY Graduate Center, November 10, 2023.Slides</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An overview of virtual large cardinals</title><link href="/talks/2023/07/21/an-overview-of-virtual-large-cardinals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An overview of virtual large cardinals" /><published>2023-07-21T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-07-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/talks/2023/07/21/an-overview-of-virtual-large-cardinals</id><content type="html" xml:base="/talks/2023/07/21/an-overview-of-virtual-large-cardinals.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the University of Konstanz, July 21, 2023.&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/KonstanzVirtualLargeCardinals.pdf&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Measurable cardinals and stronger large cardinals, such as strong and supercompact cardinals, are characterized by the existence of elementary embeddings $j:V\to M$ with the large cardinal as the critical point. Imposing closure properties on $M$, which make $M$ closer to $V$, results in stronger notions. The subject of generic large cardinals bridges the study of the large cardinal hierarchy and forcing by asking what large cardinal notions can be  obtained if the embeddings characterizing a given large cardinal notion exist in a forcing extension. For instance, a cardinal $\kappa$ is said to be &lt;em&gt;generically measurable&lt;/em&gt; if some forcing extension has an embedding $j:V\to M$ with critical point $\kappa$, but $M$ not necessarily contained in $V$. These generic large cardinals are consistency-wise at least as strong as measurable cardinals, but suprisingly very small cardinal like $\omega_1$ can be generally measurable (or supercompact).
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Although the most familiar characterizations of large cardinals are in terms of embeddings on the whole universe $V$, all these notions can be equivalently characterized by the existence of set-sized embeddings $j_\lambda:V_\lambda\to M_\lambda$ (usually for cofinally many $\lambda$). Despite the historic interest in generic large cardinals charactized by the existence of embeddings on all of $V$ in the forcing extension, recent attempts to find large cardinal notions for equiconsistency results have resulted in a shift of focus to generic large cardinals defined by asking for the existence of set-sized embeddings characterizing a given large cardinal notion. Surprisingly these set focused generic large cardinals, although they retain many reflecting properties of their actual counterparts, are typically much weaker in consistency strength, and indeed are usually consistent with $L$.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
The most unifying concept among these new generic large cardinals has been the notion of &lt;em&gt;virtual&lt;/em&gt; large cardinals. These are generic large cardinals defined by taking a characterization of a large cardinal notion in terms of the existence of set embeddings $j_\lambda:V_\lambda\to M_\lambda$ and asking that the target $M_\lambda$ exists in $V$ and has the required the closure properties from the perspective of $V$, while only the embedding exists in the forcing extension. The requirement that the target $M_\lambda$ of the embedding is an element of $V$ ensures that the virtual large cardinals are actual large cardinals, they are completely ineffable and more, but usually bounded by the $\omega$-Erdős cardinal.  The virtual large cardinal hierarchy is therefore compatible with $L$. In fact, the hierarchy even includes virtual versions of large cardinals that are known to be incompatible with ${\rm ZFC}$ (but still believed to be consistent with ${\rm ZF}$).
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
In this talk, I will give an overview of both the generic and the virtual large cardinal notions that have been defined recently and explain how they arose out of establishing equiconsistency results. I will discuss in which ways the virtual large cardinals mirror the properties of their original counterparts and in which way they differ from them.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the University of Konstanz, July 21, 2023.Slides</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A gentle introduction to class forcing</title><link href="/talks/2023/07/21/a-gentle-introduction-to-class-forcing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A gentle introduction to class forcing" /><published>2023-07-21T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-07-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/talks/2023/07/21/a-gentle-introduction-to-class-forcing</id><content type="html" xml:base="/talks/2023/07/21/a-gentle-introduction-to-class-forcing.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the Konstanz Logik Kolloquium, University of Konstanz, July 21, 2023.&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/KonstanzClassForcing.pdf&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The technique of forcing, discovered by Paul Cohen in the 1960's, is one of the most widely used in modern set theory. Using a cleverly chosen partial order in a universe of set theory (model of ZFC) together with an external object, the generic filter for that partial order, we can extend the universe to a larger universe, the forcing extension, satisfying some desired property or list of properties. While using set partial orders allows us to control the local properties of a forcing extension, such as the size of the powerset of a single cardinal or a set of cardinals, in order to globally modify how our universe looks, by, for example, getting the generalized continuum hypothesis to fail at every cardinal, we need to use class partial orders.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
As class forcing began to be used more widely in set theoretic constructions, set theorists began trying to systematically study its properties. It quickly became obvious that first-order set theory, where classes are merely objects in the meta-theory, is not the correct framework for formalizing and studying the properties of class forcing, which is fundamentally about class objects. Class forcing, as any concept that operates on classes, is best understood in the framework of second-order set theory in which both sets and classes are objects. It has since turned out that properties of class forcing are indeed determined by which classes exist around them, namely which second-order class existence axioms hold.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Although set theorists have successfully used class partial orders to construct numerous interesting universes, class forcing does not generally work anywhere near as nicely as set forcing. Most significantly, class forcing does not necessarily preserve ZFC and satisfies the forcing theorem (the assertion that the forcing relation is definable) only in strong enough second-order set theories. Many other widely used results about set forcing can fail for class forcing as well, even in strong second-order theories.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
In this talk, I will explain how to formalize class forcing in the context of second-order set theory and discuss how the familiar properties of set forcing hold up or fail for class partial orders.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/kon1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/kon2.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the Konstanz Logik Kolloquium, University of Konstanz, July 21, 2023.Slides</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Jensen forcing at an inaccessible and a model of Kelley-Morse satisfying ${\rm CC}$ but not ${\rm DC}_\omega$</title><link href="/publications/2023/05/01/jensen-forcing-at-an-inaccessible.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jensen forcing at an inaccessible and a model of Kelley-Morse satisfying ${&amp;#92;rm CC}$ but not ${&amp;#92;rm DC}_&amp;#92;omega$" /><published>2023-05-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-05-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/publications/2023/05/01/jensen-forcing-at-an-inaccessible</id><content type="html" xml:base="/publications/2023/05/01/jensen-forcing-at-an-inaccessible.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;FriedmanGitman:ModelOfACNotDCInaccessible&quot;&gt;S.-D. Friedman and V. Gitman, “Jensen forcing at an inaccessible and a
model of Kelley-Morse satisfying ${\rm CC}$ but not ${\rm DC}_ω$,” &lt;i&gt;Manuscript&lt;/i&gt;, 2023. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Second-order set theory has two types of objects: sets and classes. Unlike in first-order set theory, where classes are relegated to the meta-theory, in second-order set theory we are able to formally study properties of classes. Second-order set theory is formalized in a two-sorted logic with separate sorts (variables and quantifiers) for sets and classes. To distinguish between the two types of objects, we will use lower case letters for sets and upper case letters for classes. Complexity of formulas in second-order set theory is determined by the number of alternations of class quantifiers. A second-order formula is $\Sigma^1_n$ (or $\Pi^1_n$) if it has the form an alternation of $n$ class quantifiers followed by a first-order formula. A model of second-order set theory is a triple $\mathscr V=(V,\in, \mathcal C)$, where $V$ consists of the sets, $\mathcal C$ consists of the classes, and $\in$ is the membership relation between sets and between sets and classes. Each element of $\mathcal C$ is viewed as a sub-collection of $V$ consisting of those elements which are $\in$-related to it.  An axiomatization for second-order set theory consists of axioms for sets, classes, and the interactions between the two sorts. A typical axiomatization consists of the basic axioms: ${\rm ZFC}$ axioms for sets, extensionality for classes, the class replacement axiom asserting that every class function restricted to a set is a set, the global well-order axiom asserting that there is a class well-ordering of all sets, together with some class existence axioms. The most common class existence axioms take the form of comprehension axioms, asserting that collections defined by formulas of some complexity are classes. One of the weakest second-order axiomatizations is the theory ${\rm GBC}$, which consists of the above mentioned basic axioms together with comprehension for first-order formulas. The theory ${\rm GBC}$ is equiconsistent with ${\rm ZFC}$ because every model of ${\rm ZFC}$ that has a definable global well-order (such as the constructible universe $L$), when taken together with its definable collections, is a model of ${\rm GBC}$. We get increasingly stronger second-order theories by extending the amount of available comprehension to formulas of higher complexity. This hierarchy of theories culminates in the theory Kelley-Morse ${\rm KM}$, which consists of the basic axioms together with comprehension for all second-order formulas. The theory ${\rm KM}$ has consistency strength greater than ${\rm ZFC}$, but less than ${\rm ZFC}$ with the existence of an inaccessible cardinal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Although, in terms of comprehension, ${\rm KM}$ is the strongest possible second-order theory, it can be made much more robust by adding choice axioms for classes. Analogously to how sets have much more structure in models of ${\rm ZFC}$ than in models of ${\rm ZF}$, classes have much more structure in models of ${\rm KM}$ together with class choice axioms than they do in models of just ${\rm KM}$. The two most common choice principles used in the second-order context are the choice scheme ${\rm CC}$ and the dependent choice schemes ${\rm DC}_\alpha$ (for a regular cardinal $\alpha$ or $\alpha={\rm Ord}$). The &lt;em&gt;choice scheme&lt;/em&gt; asserts for every second-order formula $\varphi(x,X,A)$, with parameter $A$, that if for every set $x$, there is a class $X$ such that $\varphi(x,X,A)$ holds, then there is a single class $Y$ collecting on its slices witnesses for every set $x$, namely, for every set $x$, $\varphi(x,Y_x,A)$ holds, where $Y_x=\{y\mid \langle x,y\rangle\in Y\}$ is the $x$'s slice of $Y$. Given a regular cardinal $\alpha$ or $\alpha={\rm Ord}$, the &lt;em&gt;dependent choice scheme&lt;/em&gt; ${\rm DC}_\alpha$ asserts for every second-order formula $\psi(X,Y,A)$, with parameter $A$, that if $\psi$ defines a relation without terminal nodes (for every class $X$, there is a class $Y$ such that $\psi(X,Y,A)$ holds), then we can make $\alpha$-many dependent choices along $\psi$, namely, there is a class $F$ such that for every $\xi\lt\alpha$, $\psi(F\upharpoonright\xi, F_\xi,A)$ holds, where $F_\xi$ is the $\xi$-th slice of $F$ and $F\upharpoonright\xi$ is the restriction of the class $F$ to slices indexed by ordinals $\eta\lt\xi$ ($F\upharpoonright \xi=\{\langle \eta,y\rangle\in F\mid \eta\lt\xi\}$). The choice scheme is viewed as the analogue of ${\rm AC}$ for classes  and the ${\rm DC}_\alpha$-scheme is viewed as the analogue of dependent choice ${\rm DC}_\alpha$. The second author and Hamkins showed that the theory ${\rm KM}$ is not strong enough to prove even the weakest instances of the choice scheme, those where we make only $\omega$-many choices for a first-order formula. That is, it is consistent that there is a model of ${\rm KM}$ and a first-order assertion $\varphi(x,X)$ such that in the model, for every $n\in\omega$, there is a class $X$ such that $\varphi(n,X)$ holds, but there is no class $Y$ such that $\varphi(n,Y_n)$ holds for every $n\in\omega$ &lt;a href=&quot;#GitmanHamkinsJohnstone:KMplus&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. Given this situation, the next natural question which arises is whether the theory Kelley-Morse together with the choice scheme ${\rm KM}+{\rm CC}$ proves ${\rm DC}_\omega$, the weakest of the dependent choice principles. The axiom of choice ${\rm AC}$, of course, implies all the dependent choice axioms ${\rm DC}_\alpha$ over ${\rm ZF}$, but results from second-order arithmetic suggested that ${\rm KM}+{\rm CC}$ may not be able to prove at least some of the dependent choice principles ${\rm DC}_\alpha$. The study of the two fields has shown that there are many parallels as well as some differences between these mathematical domains, with second-order arithmetic being the more well-developed of the two because of its connections to analysis.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Second-order arithmetic has two types of objects: numbers and sets of numbers (which we think of as the reals). A typical axiomatization of second-order arithmetic consists of the basic axioms: the ${\rm PA}$ axioms for numbers and the set induction axiom asserting that induction holds for every set, together with some set existence axioms. The primary set existence axioms are again comprehension axioms and choice principles for sets. The choice scheme ${\rm CC}$, in this context, is the exact analogue of the choice scheme in second-order set theory and the dependent choice scheme ${\rm DC}$ is the exact analogue of ${\rm DC}_\omega$. The analogue of ${\rm GBC}$ is the second-order arithmetic theory ${\rm ACA}_0$, which is equiconsistent with ${\rm PA}$, and the analogue of ${\rm KM}$ is the theory ${\rm Z}_2$, which has comprehension for all second-order formulas. An argument, using Shoenfield absoluteness, shows that ${\rm Z}_2$ implies ${\rm CC}$ for $\Sigma^1_2$-formulas (note the contrast with the ${\rm KM}$ situation, where ${\rm KM}$ does not prove ${\rm CC}$ even for first-order formulas) and that ${\rm Z}_2+{\rm CC}$ implies ${\rm DC}$ for $\Sigma^1_2$-formulas &lt;a href=&quot;#simpson:second-orderArithmetic&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. Feferman and Levy constructed a model of ${\rm ZF}$ in which $\omega_1$ is a countable union of countable sets as a symmetric submodel of a forcing extension by the finite-support product $\Pi_{n\lt\omega}{\rm Coll}(\omega,\aleph_n)$ of collapse forcings &lt;a href=&quot;#levy:choicescheme&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;. The reals of this classical choiceless model form a model of ${\rm Z}_2$ in which ${\rm CC}$ optimally fails for a $\Pi^1_2$-assertion. The authors of the present article, together with Kanovei, showed that it is consistent that there is a model of ${\rm Z}_2+{\rm CC}$ in which ${\rm DC}$ fails for a $\Pi^1_2$-assertion. The model was obtained as the reals of a symmetric submodel of a forcing extension by a tree iteration of Jensen's forcing &lt;a href=&quot;#FriedmanGitmanKanovei:ModelOfACNotDC&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Jensen's forcing $\mathbb J$ is a subposet of Sacks forcing that was constructed by Jensen in $L$ using the guessing principle $\diamondsuit$. The forcing $\mathbb J$ has two key properties: it has the ccc and it adds a unique ($\Pi^1_2$-singleton) generic real over $L$. Jensen used the forcing $\mathbb J$ to show that it is consistent to have a $\Pi^1_2$-singleton non-constructible real (every $\Sigma^1_2$-singleton is in $L$ by Shoenfield's absoluteness) &lt;a href=&quot;#jensen:real&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;. Since then his forcing has found a number of other applications. While $\diamondsuit$ is crucial to the construction of a poset with the two key properties of $\mathbb J$, the constructible universe is not. A subposet of Sacks forcing with the ccc that adds a unique generic real can be constructed in any universe with $\diamondsuit$, with only the complexity of the generic real possibly being lost.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lyubetsky and Kanovei extended the &quot;unique generics&quot; property of Jensen's forcing to a finite-support $\omega$-length product $\mathbb J^{\lt\omega}$ of $\mathbb J$. They showed that in any forcing extension $L[G]$ by $\mathbb J^{\lt\omega}$, the only generic reals for $\mathbb J$ are those added by the slices of $G$ &lt;a href=&quot;#kanovei:productOfJensenReals&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;. Abraham showed that, for $n\lt\omega$, a finite $n$-length iteration $\mathbb J_n$ of $\mathbb J$ adds a unique $n$-length generic sequence of reals (missing reference). The authors of the current article and Kanovei showed that certain tree iterations of $\mathbb J$ have a &quot;unique generics&quot; property, and this property was instrumental in obtaining the model of second-order arithmetic satisfying ${\rm AC}$ but not ${\rm DC}$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this paper, we generalize Jensen's construction from $\omega$ to an inaccessible cardinal $\kappa$ to define an analogue of Jensen's forcing with perfect $\kappa$-trees. We show that if $\kappa$ is an inaccessible cardinal and the guessing principle $\diamondsuit_{\kappa^+}(\mathrm{Cof}(\kappa))$ holds, then there is a poset $\mathbb J(\kappa)$, whose elements are perfect $\kappa$-trees ordered by the subset relation, with the three key properties: it is $\lt\kappa$-closed, it has the $\kappa^+$-cc, and it adds a unique generic subset of $\kappa$. A number of obstacles needed to be overcome to make Jensen's construction work for perfect $\kappa$-trees. Perfect trees have several nice properties properties, like the existence of greatest lower bounds for compatible conditions, which fail for perfect $\kappa$-trees, and these properties played a significant role in the construction of Jensen's forcing. Another problem which did not arise in the original construction was presented by the $\lt\kappa$-closure requirement. The poset $\mathbb J$ is built up as the union of a continuous chain of posets of length $\omega_1$ with maximal antichains being sealed at stages given by $\diamondsuit$ along the way. In the case of the poset $\mathbb J(\kappa)$, we couldn't simply take unions at the limit stages of building up the analogous chain because then we would lose $\lt\kappa$-closure, but closing the union under $\lt\kappa$-sequences could potentially unseal maximal antichains. We shall argue that this doesn't happen. We also define finite iterations and tree iterations of the poset $\mathbb J(\kappa)$ partially analogously to how finite iterations $\mathbb J_n$ and tree iterations of $\mathbb J$ were defined in &lt;a href=&quot;#FriedmanGitmanKanovei:ModelOfACNotDC&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We show that bounded-support $\kappa$-length products of $\mathbb J(\kappa)$, finite iterations of $\mathbb J(\kappa)$, and certain tree iterations of $\mathbb J(\kappa)$ have &quot;unique generics&quot; properties analogous to those of Jensen's forcing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;: Suppose that $\kappa$ is an inaccessible cardinal and $\diamondsuit_{\kappa^+}(\mathrm{Cof}(\kappa))$ holds. There is a poset $\mathbb J(\kappa)$ whose elements are perfect $\kappa$-trees ordered by the subset relation with the following three properties:
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
$\mathbb J(\kappa)$ is $\lt\kappa$-closed.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$\mathbb J(\kappa)$ has the $\kappa^+$-cc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;In any forcing extension by $\mathbb J(\kappa)$, there is a unique generic subset of $\kappa$. If the starting universe is $L$, then the unique generic subset is a $\Pi^1_1$-singleton.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Let $\mathbb J(\kappa)^{\lt\kappa}$ denote the bounded-support $\kappa$-length product of the poset $\mathbb J(\kappa)$ and let $\mathbb J(\kappa)_n$, for $n\lt\omega$, denote the $n$-length iteration of $\mathbb J(\kappa)$.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;: Suppose that $\kappa$ is an inaccessible cardinal and $\diamondsuit_{\kappa^+}(\mathrm{Cof}(\kappa))$ holds. In a forcing extension $V[G]$ by $\mathbb J(\kappa)^{\lt\kappa}$, the only generic subsets of $\kappa$ for $\mathbb J(\kappa)$ are those added by the slices of $G$.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;: Suppose that $\kappa$ is an inaccessible cardinal, $\diamondsuit_{\kappa^+}(\mathrm{Cof}(\kappa))$ holds, and $n\in\omega$. The iteration $\mathbb J(\kappa)_n$ of the poset $\mathbb J(\kappa)$ of length $n$ adds a unique $n$-length generic sequence of subsets of $\kappa$.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;: Suppose that $\kappa$ is an inaccessible cardinal and $\diamondsuit_{\kappa^+}(\mathrm{Cof}(\kappa))$ holds. In any forcing extension by the tree iteration of $\mathbb J(\kappa)$ along the tree $(\kappa^+)^{\lt\omega}$, for every $n\in\omega$, the only $n$-length generic sequences of subsets of $\kappa$ for the iteration $\mathbb J(\kappa)_n$ are those arising from the $n$-length nodes of the generic tree.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We construct a symmetric submodel of a forcing extension by the tree iteration of $\mathbb J(\kappa)$ along the tree $(\kappa^+)^{\lt\omega}$ such that in this model $\mathscr V=(V_\kappa,\in, V_{\kappa+1})$ is a model of ${\rm KM}+{\rm CC}$ in which the scheme ${\rm DC}_\omega$ fails.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;: It is consistent that there is a model of ${\rm KM}+{\rm CC}+\neg{\rm DC}_\omega$.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;GitmanHamkinsJohnstone:KMplus&quot;&gt;V. Gitman and J. D. Hamkins, “Kelley-Morse set theory and choice principles for classes.” &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;simpson:second-orderArithmetic&quot;&gt;S. G. Simpson, &lt;i&gt;Subsystems of second order arithmetic&lt;/i&gt;, Second. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge; Association for
              Symbolic Logic, Poughkeepsie, NY, 2009, p. xvi+444. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;levy:choicescheme&quot;&gt;A. Lévy, “Definability in axiomatic set theory. II,” in &lt;i&gt;Mathematical Logic and Foundations of Set Theory
              (Proc. Internat. Colloq., Jerusalem, 1968)&lt;/i&gt;, North-Holland, Amsterdam, 1970, pp. 129–145. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;FriedmanGitmanKanovei:ModelOfACNotDC&quot;&gt;S.-D. Friedman, V. Gitman, and V. Kanovei, “A model of second-order arithmetic satisfying AC but not
              DC,” &lt;i&gt;J. Math. Log.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 19, no. 1, pp. 1850013, 39, 2019. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;jensen:real&quot;&gt;R. Jensen, “Definable sets of minimal degree,” in &lt;i&gt;Mathematical logic and foundations of set theory (Proc.
              Internat. Colloq., Jerusalem, 1968)&lt;/i&gt;, North-Holland, Amsterdam, 1970, pp. 122–128. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;kanovei:productOfJensenReals&quot;&gt;V. G. Kanovei and V. A. Lyubetski, “A definable countable set containing no definable elements,” &lt;i&gt;Mat. Zametki&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 102, no. 3, pp. 369–382, 2017. Available at: https://doi.org/10.4213/mzm10842&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">{% reference page.ref %} Second-order set theory has two types of objects: sets and classes. Unlike in first-order set theory, where classes are relegated to the meta-theory, in second-order set theory we are able to formally study properties of classes. Second-order set theory is formalized in a two-sorted logic with separate sorts (variables and quantifiers) for sets and classes. To distinguish between the two types of objects, we will use lower case letters for sets and upper case letters for classes. Complexity of formulas in second-order set theory is determined by the number of alternations of class quantifiers. A second-order formula is $\Sigma^1_n$ (or $\Pi^1_n$) if it has the form an alternation of $n$ class quantifiers followed by a first-order formula. A model of second-order set theory is a triple $\mathscr V=(V,\in, \mathcal C)$, where $V$ consists of the sets, $\mathcal C$ consists of the classes, and $\in$ is the membership relation between sets and between sets and classes. Each element of $\mathcal C$ is viewed as a sub-collection of $V$ consisting of those elements which are $\in$-related to it. An axiomatization for second-order set theory consists of axioms for sets, classes, and the interactions between the two sorts. A typical axiomatization consists of the basic axioms: ${\rm ZFC}$ axioms for sets, extensionality for classes, the class replacement axiom asserting that every class function restricted to a set is a set, the global well-order axiom asserting that there is a class well-ordering of all sets, together with some class existence axioms. The most common class existence axioms take the form of comprehension axioms, asserting that collections defined by formulas of some complexity are classes. One of the weakest second-order axiomatizations is the theory ${\rm GBC}$, which consists of the above mentioned basic axioms together with comprehension for first-order formulas. The theory ${\rm GBC}$ is equiconsistent with ${\rm ZFC}$ because every model of ${\rm ZFC}$ that has a definable global well-order (such as the constructible universe $L$), when taken together with its definable collections, is a model of ${\rm GBC}$. We get increasingly stronger second-order theories by extending the amount of available comprehension to formulas of higher complexity. This hierarchy of theories culminates in the theory Kelley-Morse ${\rm KM}$, which consists of the basic axioms together with comprehension for all second-order formulas. The theory ${\rm KM}$ has consistency strength greater than ${\rm ZFC}$, but less than ${\rm ZFC}$ with the existence of an inaccessible cardinal. Although, in terms of comprehension, ${\rm KM}$ is the strongest possible second-order theory, it can be made much more robust by adding choice axioms for classes. Analogously to how sets have much more structure in models of ${\rm ZFC}$ than in models of ${\rm ZF}$, classes have much more structure in models of ${\rm KM}$ together with class choice axioms than they do in models of just ${\rm KM}$. The two most common choice principles used in the second-order context are the choice scheme ${\rm CC}$ and the dependent choice schemes ${\rm DC}_\alpha$ (for a regular cardinal $\alpha$ or $\alpha={\rm Ord}$). The choice scheme asserts for every second-order formula $\varphi(x,X,A)$, with parameter $A$, that if for every set $x$, there is a class $X$ such that $\varphi(x,X,A)$ holds, then there is a single class $Y$ collecting on its slices witnesses for every set $x$, namely, for every set $x$, $\varphi(x,Y_x,A)$ holds, where $Y_x=\{y\mid \langle x,y\rangle\in Y\}$ is the $x$'s slice of $Y$. Given a regular cardinal $\alpha$ or $\alpha={\rm Ord}$, the dependent choice scheme ${\rm DC}_\alpha$ asserts for every second-order formula $\psi(X,Y,A)$, with parameter $A$, that if $\psi$ defines a relation without terminal nodes (for every class $X$, there is a class $Y$ such that $\psi(X,Y,A)$ holds), then we can make $\alpha$-many dependent choices along $\psi$, namely, there is a class $F$ such that for every $\xi\lt\alpha$, $\psi(F\upharpoonright\xi, F_\xi,A)$ holds, where $F_\xi$ is the $\xi$-th slice of $F$ and $F\upharpoonright\xi$ is the restriction of the class $F$ to slices indexed by ordinals $\eta\lt\xi$ ($F\upharpoonright \xi=\{\langle \eta,y\rangle\in F\mid \eta\lt\xi\}$). The choice scheme is viewed as the analogue of ${\rm AC}$ for classes and the ${\rm DC}_\alpha$-scheme is viewed as the analogue of dependent choice ${\rm DC}_\alpha$. The second author and Hamkins showed that the theory ${\rm KM}$ is not strong enough to prove even the weakest instances of the choice scheme, those where we make only $\omega$-many choices for a first-order formula. That is, it is consistent that there is a model of ${\rm KM}$ and a first-order assertion $\varphi(x,X)$ such that in the model, for every $n\in\omega$, there is a class $X$ such that $\varphi(n,X)$ holds, but there is no class $Y$ such that $\varphi(n,Y_n)$ holds for every $n\in\omega$ {% cite GitmanHamkinsJohnstone:KMplus %}. Given this situation, the next natural question which arises is whether the theory Kelley-Morse together with the choice scheme ${\rm KM}+{\rm CC}$ proves ${\rm DC}_\omega$, the weakest of the dependent choice principles. The axiom of choice ${\rm AC}$, of course, implies all the dependent choice axioms ${\rm DC}_\alpha$ over ${\rm ZF}$, but results from second-order arithmetic suggested that ${\rm KM}+{\rm CC}$ may not be able to prove at least some of the dependent choice principles ${\rm DC}_\alpha$. The study of the two fields has shown that there are many parallels as well as some differences between these mathematical domains, with second-order arithmetic being the more well-developed of the two because of its connections to analysis. Second-order arithmetic has two types of objects: numbers and sets of numbers (which we think of as the reals). A typical axiomatization of second-order arithmetic consists of the basic axioms: the ${\rm PA}$ axioms for numbers and the set induction axiom asserting that induction holds for every set, together with some set existence axioms. The primary set existence axioms are again comprehension axioms and choice principles for sets. The choice scheme ${\rm CC}$, in this context, is the exact analogue of the choice scheme in second-order set theory and the dependent choice scheme ${\rm DC}$ is the exact analogue of ${\rm DC}_\omega$. The analogue of ${\rm GBC}$ is the second-order arithmetic theory ${\rm ACA}_0$, which is equiconsistent with ${\rm PA}$, and the analogue of ${\rm KM}$ is the theory ${\rm Z}_2$, which has comprehension for all second-order formulas. An argument, using Shoenfield absoluteness, shows that ${\rm Z}_2$ implies ${\rm CC}$ for $\Sigma^1_2$-formulas (note the contrast with the ${\rm KM}$ situation, where ${\rm KM}$ does not prove ${\rm CC}$ even for first-order formulas) and that ${\rm Z}_2+{\rm CC}$ implies ${\rm DC}$ for $\Sigma^1_2$-formulas {% cite simpson:second-orderArithmetic %}. Feferman and Levy constructed a model of ${\rm ZF}$ in which $\omega_1$ is a countable union of countable sets as a symmetric submodel of a forcing extension by the finite-support product $\Pi_{n\lt\omega}{\rm Coll}(\omega,\aleph_n)$ of collapse forcings {% cite levy:choicescheme %}. The reals of this classical choiceless model form a model of ${\rm Z}_2$ in which ${\rm CC}$ optimally fails for a $\Pi^1_2$-assertion. The authors of the present article, together with Kanovei, showed that it is consistent that there is a model of ${\rm Z}_2+{\rm CC}$ in which ${\rm DC}$ fails for a $\Pi^1_2$-assertion. The model was obtained as the reals of a symmetric submodel of a forcing extension by a tree iteration of Jensen's forcing {% cite FriedmanGitmanKanovei:ModelOfACNotDC %}. Jensen's forcing $\mathbb J$ is a subposet of Sacks forcing that was constructed by Jensen in $L$ using the guessing principle $\diamondsuit$. The forcing $\mathbb J$ has two key properties: it has the ccc and it adds a unique ($\Pi^1_2$-singleton) generic real over $L$. Jensen used the forcing $\mathbb J$ to show that it is consistent to have a $\Pi^1_2$-singleton non-constructible real (every $\Sigma^1_2$-singleton is in $L$ by Shoenfield's absoluteness) {% cite jensen:real %}. Since then his forcing has found a number of other applications. While $\diamondsuit$ is crucial to the construction of a poset with the two key properties of $\mathbb J$, the constructible universe is not. A subposet of Sacks forcing with the ccc that adds a unique generic real can be constructed in any universe with $\diamondsuit$, with only the complexity of the generic real possibly being lost. Lyubetsky and Kanovei extended the &quot;unique generics&quot; property of Jensen's forcing to a finite-support $\omega$-length product $\mathbb J^{\lt\omega}$ of $\mathbb J$. They showed that in any forcing extension $L[G]$ by $\mathbb J^{\lt\omega}$, the only generic reals for $\mathbb J$ are those added by the slices of $G$ {% cite kanovei:productOfJensenReals %}. Abraham showed that, for $n\lt\omega$, a finite $n$-length iteration $\mathbb J_n$ of $\mathbb J$ adds a unique $n$-length generic sequence of reals {% cite abraham:jensenRealsIterations %}. The authors of the current article and Kanovei showed that certain tree iterations of $\mathbb J$ have a &quot;unique generics&quot; property, and this property was instrumental in obtaining the model of second-order arithmetic satisfying ${\rm AC}$ but not ${\rm DC}$. In this paper, we generalize Jensen's construction from $\omega$ to an inaccessible cardinal $\kappa$ to define an analogue of Jensen's forcing with perfect $\kappa$-trees. We show that if $\kappa$ is an inaccessible cardinal and the guessing principle $\diamondsuit_{\kappa^+}(\mathrm{Cof}(\kappa))$ holds, then there is a poset $\mathbb J(\kappa)$, whose elements are perfect $\kappa$-trees ordered by the subset relation, with the three key properties: it is $\lt\kappa$-closed, it has the $\kappa^+$-cc, and it adds a unique generic subset of $\kappa$. A number of obstacles needed to be overcome to make Jensen's construction work for perfect $\kappa$-trees. Perfect trees have several nice properties properties, like the existence of greatest lower bounds for compatible conditions, which fail for perfect $\kappa$-trees, and these properties played a significant role in the construction of Jensen's forcing. Another problem which did not arise in the original construction was presented by the $\lt\kappa$-closure requirement. The poset $\mathbb J$ is built up as the union of a continuous chain of posets of length $\omega_1$ with maximal antichains being sealed at stages given by $\diamondsuit$ along the way. In the case of the poset $\mathbb J(\kappa)$, we couldn't simply take unions at the limit stages of building up the analogous chain because then we would lose $\lt\kappa$-closure, but closing the union under $\lt\kappa$-sequences could potentially unseal maximal antichains. We shall argue that this doesn't happen. We also define finite iterations and tree iterations of the poset $\mathbb J(\kappa)$ partially analogously to how finite iterations $\mathbb J_n$ and tree iterations of $\mathbb J$ were defined in {% cite FriedmanGitmanKanovei:ModelOfACNotDC %}. We show that bounded-support $\kappa$-length products of $\mathbb J(\kappa)$, finite iterations of $\mathbb J(\kappa)$, and certain tree iterations of $\mathbb J(\kappa)$ have &quot;unique generics&quot; properties analogous to those of Jensen's forcing. Theorem: Suppose that $\kappa$ is an inaccessible cardinal and $\diamondsuit_{\kappa^+}(\mathrm{Cof}(\kappa))$ holds. There is a poset $\mathbb J(\kappa)$ whose elements are perfect $\kappa$-trees ordered by the subset relation with the following three properties: $\mathbb J(\kappa)$ is $\lt\kappa$-closed. $\mathbb J(\kappa)$ has the $\kappa^+$-cc. In any forcing extension by $\mathbb J(\kappa)$, there is a unique generic subset of $\kappa$. If the starting universe is $L$, then the unique generic subset is a $\Pi^1_1$-singleton. Let $\mathbb J(\kappa)^{\lt\kappa}$ denote the bounded-support $\kappa$-length product of the poset $\mathbb J(\kappa)$ and let $\mathbb J(\kappa)_n$, for $n\lt\omega$, denote the $n$-length iteration of $\mathbb J(\kappa)$. Theorem: Suppose that $\kappa$ is an inaccessible cardinal and $\diamondsuit_{\kappa^+}(\mathrm{Cof}(\kappa))$ holds. In a forcing extension $V[G]$ by $\mathbb J(\kappa)^{\lt\kappa}$, the only generic subsets of $\kappa$ for $\mathbb J(\kappa)$ are those added by the slices of $G$. Theorem: Suppose that $\kappa$ is an inaccessible cardinal, $\diamondsuit_{\kappa^+}(\mathrm{Cof}(\kappa))$ holds, and $n\in\omega$. The iteration $\mathbb J(\kappa)_n$ of the poset $\mathbb J(\kappa)$ of length $n$ adds a unique $n$-length generic sequence of subsets of $\kappa$. Theorem: Suppose that $\kappa$ is an inaccessible cardinal and $\diamondsuit_{\kappa^+}(\mathrm{Cof}(\kappa))$ holds. In any forcing extension by the tree iteration of $\mathbb J(\kappa)$ along the tree $(\kappa^+)^{\lt\omega}$, for every $n\in\omega$, the only $n$-length generic sequences of subsets of $\kappa$ for the iteration $\mathbb J(\kappa)_n$ are those arising from the $n$-length nodes of the generic tree. We construct a symmetric submodel of a forcing extension by the tree iteration of $\mathbb J(\kappa)$ along the tree $(\kappa^+)^{\lt\omega}$ such that in this model $\mathscr V=(V_\kappa,\in, V_{\kappa+1})$ is a model of ${\rm KM}+{\rm CC}$ in which the scheme ${\rm DC}_\omega$ fails. Theorem: It is consistent that there is a model of ${\rm KM}+{\rm CC}+\neg{\rm DC}_\omega$. References {% bibliography --cited %}</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Jensen’s forcing at an inaccessible</title><link href="/talks/2023/04/10/jensens-forcing-at-an-inaccessible.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jensen’s forcing at an inaccessible" /><published>2023-04-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2023-04-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/talks/2023/04/10/jensens-forcing-at-an-inaccessible</id><content type="html" xml:base="/talks/2023/04/10/jensens-forcing-at-an-inaccessible.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the Rutgers Logic Seminar, Rutgers University, April 10, 2023.&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/JensenInaccessibleTalkRutgers.pdf&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The talk is similar to the talk in this &lt;a href=&quot;/talks/2021/09/14/jensen-forcing-at-an-inaccessible.html&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the Rutgers Logic Seminar, Rutgers University, April 10, 2023.Slides</summary></entry></feed>