<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-08-28T15:20:11-04:00</updated><id>/</id><title type="html">Victoria Gitman</title><entry><title type="html">A version of Jensen’s forcing for an inaccessible cardinal</title><link href="/research/2022/08/21/a-version-of-Jensens-forcing-for-an-inaccessible-cardinal.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A version of Jensen's forcing for an inaccessible cardinal" /><published>2022-08-21T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-08-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/research/2022/08/21/a-version-of-Jensens-forcing-for-an-inaccessible-cardinal</id><content type="html" xml:base="/research/2022/08/21/a-version-of-Jensens-forcing-for-an-inaccessible-cardinal.html">&lt;p&gt;
Jensen's forcing is a subposet of Sacks forcing with two key properties (1) it has the ccc and (2) it adds a unique generic real. Another ccc forcing adding a generic real is, of course, Cohen's original forcing, but, as is well known, once you have added a Cohen generic, you have actually added continuum many of them, so no uniqueness is to be had there. Unlike Cohen's forcing, you cannot construct Jensen's forcing in any universe $V$, you need the guessing principle $\diamondsuit$, so, in particular, you are stuck with universes satisfying ${\rm CH}$. Although, in $L$, we can specify a unique Jensen's forcing, as we will see later, there is are variables in the construction that can result in different forcing notions, all with the  required two properties. We will refer to any forcing constructed according to the recipe of Jensen's forcing (which we will sketch below) as $\mathbb J$. As the name suggests, the forcing $\mathbb J$ was discovered by Jensen in 1970, who used it to show that it is consistent to have a $\Pi^1_2$-definable non-constructible (sigleton) real &lt;a href=&quot;#jensen:real&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. Namely, you force with $\mathbb J$ over $L$, adding the unique generic real $r$ and argue that in $L[r]$, the singleton $\{r\}$ is $\Pi^1_2$-definable. This is the best possible result because, by Shoenfield's Absoluteness, every $\Sigma^1_2$-definable real has to be in $L$.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
More recently, Lyubetsky and Kanovei generalized the 'uniqueness of generic reals' property of Jensen's forcing to finite support $\omega$-length products of $\mathbb J$, showing that in a forcing extension by the finite support $\omega$-length product of $\mathbb J$, the only generic reals for $\mathbb J$ are the $\omega$-many slices of the generic filter &lt;a href=&quot;#kanovei:productOfJensenReals&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. Lyubetsky and Kanovei used their result to show that there can be a countable hereditarily ordinal definable set of reals without any definable members, namely the set consisting of the $\omega$-many generic reals in a forcing extension by the finite-support $\omega$-length product of $\mathbb J$. This answered a question posed on &lt;a href='https://mathoverflow.net/questions/17608/a-question-about-ordinal-definable-real-numbers'&gt;Math Overflow&lt;/a&gt; that the set theory community found quite exciting.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Together with Sy Friedman, we defined the notion of 'finite iterations' $\mathbb J_n$ (of length $n$) of Jensen's forcing, for $n\lt\omega$, and showed that these too have unique generics. This notion is a bit more complicated than simply forcing with a name for a forcing constructed according to Jensen's recipe in the extension, because in order to ensure uniqueness we have to be more careful about what goes into the forcing. For such a carefully constructed finite iteration $\mathbb J_n$, there is a unique $n$-length sequence of generic reals. The uniqueness property for the finite iterations $\mathbb J_n$ comes out of a more complicated result about tree iterations of Jensen's forcing. Given a tree $\mathcal T$ of height $\omega$, such as say $\omega^{\lt\omega}$ or $\omega_1^{\lt\omega}$, we define that a condition in the iteration $\mathbb J_{\mathcal T}$ of Jensen's forcing along the tree $\mathcal T$ is a function $f$ from a finite subtree $T$ of $\mathcal T$ into $\bigcup_{n\lt\omega}\mathbb J_n$ such that for a node $s$ of length $n$ in $T$, $f(s)\in \mathbb J_n$ and having the coherence property that whenever $s\lt$ are nodes in $T$, then $f(t)$ restricted to the length of $s$ is equal to $f(s)$. Forcing with $\mathbb J_{\mathcal T}$ adds a tree whose nodes on level $n$ are (mutually) generic for $\mathbb J_n$. The uniqueness property is that in a forcing extension by $\mathbb J_{\mathcal T}$, the only finite sequences of reals that are generic for $\mathbb J_n$ are those coming from the nodes on level $n$ of the generic tree. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We showed (with Kanovei) that a forcing extension of $L$ by the tree iteration $\mathbb J_{\omega_1^{\lt\omega}}$ has a symmetric submodel in which ${\rm AC}_\omega$ holds, but ${\rm DC}$ fails &lt;a href=&quot;#FriedmanGitman:ModelOfACNotDC&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;. The symmetric model has the tree of the generic sequences for $\mathbb J_n$ but it doesn't have a branch through it, witnessing a violation of ${\rm DC}$. Moreover, the violation of ${\rm DC}$ is definable over $H_{\omega_1}$ of the symmetric submodel because we can express what it means for a sequence to be $L$-generic for $\mathbb J_n$ and the ordering on the sequences in the tree is just end-extension. It follows that the model of full second-order arithmetic (satisfying comprehension for all second-order definable assertions) consisting of the reals of the symmetric submodel satisfies the Choice Scheme, but not the Dependent Choice Scheme. The Choice Scheme and the Dependent Choice Scheme are choice principles for classes in the second-order context. The &lt;em&gt;Choice Scheme&lt;/em&gt; asserts for any second-order formula $\varphi(n,X)$ that if for every number $n$, there is a class $X$ satisfying $\varphi(n,X)$, then there is a single class $Z$ coding a witness for $n$ on its $n$-th slice $Z_n$. The &lt;em&gt;Dependent Choice scheme&lt;/em&gt; asserts that we can make $\omega$-many dependent choices over any second-order definable relation $\varphi(X,Y)$ on classes which doesn't have terminal nodes. It also shows that there is a model of ${\rm ZFC}^-$ (${\rm ZFC}$ without powerset), namely the $H_{\omega_1}$ of the symmetric submodel, in which the ${\rm DC}_\omega$-scheme fails. In first-order, the ${\rm DC}_{\alpha}$-&lt;em&gt;scheme&lt;/em&gt;, for a regular cardinal $\alpha$, is a strengthening of ${\rm DC}_\alpha$, which asserts that we can make $\alpha$-many dependent choices over any definable relation without terminal nodes. It is easy to see that having powerset implies that the ${\rm DC}_\alpha$-scheme holds for every regular $\alpha$ by reflecting the relation to a large enough $V_\beta$.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Jensen's forcing is a subposet of Sacks forcing, so its elements are perfect trees ordered by the subtree relation. So what is the recipe for constructing Jensen's forcing? The construction is certainly not straightforward. We construct a continuous chain of countable subposets  $\mathbb J_\xi$ of Sacks forcing, for $\xi\lt\omega_1$, in $\omega_1$-many steps, using $\diamondsuit$ to seal maximal antichains and have $\mathbb J$ be the union of the chain. Along the way, a $\diamondsuit$-sequence gives us codes for 'nice' countable transitive models $M_\xi$ containing $\mathbb J_\xi$ and we force over $M_\xi$ to add an $M_\xi$-generic perfect tree, which together with $\mathbb J_\xi$ generates $\mathbb J_{\xi+1}$. Generic filters for the models $M_\xi$ exist in $V$ itself because the models are countable. The choice of the $\diamondsuit$-sequence and of the generic filters for the models $M_\xi$ can yield different posets $\mathbb J$ but each will have the required two properties. An extension $V[r]$ by $\mathbb J$ continues to satisfy $\diamondsuit$ because $\mathbb J$ is ccc. So we can construct in $V[r]$, a $\mathbb J$-like forcing following the same recipe. However, in order to construct the iterations $\mathbb J_n$, we don't use just any such forcing. In constructing the $\mathbb J$-like forcings in $V[r]$, we use forcing extensions of models $M_\xi$ chosen by the $\diamondsuit$-sequence from $V$.

&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The original project of constructing a model of full second-order arithmetic with the Choice Scheme in which the Dependent Choice scheme fails was motivated by an analogous question in second-order set theory. The second-order set theory Kelley-Morse is considered to be one of the strongest second-order theories because it includes comprehension for all second-order assertions. But it turns out that classes in second-order set theory behave much nicer if the theory also includes choice principles for them. Think about how much nicer it is to work in ${\rm ZFC}$ instead of ${\rm ZF}$ (not that there is anything wrong with ${\rm ZF}$, things just get much messier there). Among these useful choice principles for classes are the Choice Scheme and the $\alpha$-Dependent Choice schemes ($\alpha\in{\rm REG}$ or $\alpha={\rm Ord}$) and these basically generalize their second-order arithmetic counterparts. The &lt;em&gt;Choice Scheme&lt;/em&gt; asserts for every for second-order formula $\varphi(x,X)$ that if for every set $x$, there is a class $X$ witnessing $\varphi(x,X)$, then there is a single class $Z$ coding a witness for $x$ on its $x$-th slice $Z_x$. The $\alpha$-&lt;em&gt;Dependent Choice Scheme&lt;/em&gt; asserts that we can make $\alpha$-many dependent choices over any second-order definable relation on classes without terminal nodes. We showed with Joel Hamkins that Kelley-Morse does not prove the Choice Scheme even for first-order formulas and just $\omega$-many choices &lt;a href=&quot;#GitmanHamkinsJohnstone:KMplus&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;. The next question which arose was whether Kelley-Morse together with the Choice Scheme proved the $\omega$-Dependent Choice Scheme. The best way to start answering a question in second-order set theory is to search for its analogue in second-order arithmetic, where a great deal more work was done over the years. But it seemed that the analogous question in second-order arithmetic was not known! Simpson had claimed that full second-order arithmetic together with the Choice Scheme did not prove the Dependent Choice Scheme, but the proof appeared to be lost years ago. So Sy and I set out to prove it by generalizing the work of Lyubetsky and Kanovei on the uniqueness properties of products of $\mathbb J$ to tree iterations. It then turned out that Kanovei had already proved the result decades ago using (what else?) Jensen's forcing with a slightly different construction. So we ended up with a joint paper.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Now the task remained to generalize the construction to obtain the desired result in second-order set theory. The agenda was to get an analogue of Jensen's forcing on an inaccesible cardinal $\kappa$, obtain a uniqueness property for some form of tree iterations of it, and force with the tree iteration over $L$ to obtain a symmetric submodel which had the tree of height $\omega$ of finite sequences generic for iterations of the inaccessible Jensen's forcing, but had no branch through the tree. The $V_\kappa$ of this model was going to be the $V_\kappa$ of $L$, and it together with its subsets in the symmetric submodel would be the desired model of Kelley-Morse with the Choice Scheme in which the $\omega$-Depedent Choice Scheme failed.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There were two obstacles to generalizing the $\mathbb J$ construction to an inaccessible cardinal $\kappa$. The first was that perfect $\kappa$-trees do not behave as nicely as perfect trees because of the limit levels business. For instance, a union of perfect trees is a perfect tree, but a union of perfect $\kappa$-trees need not be a perfect $\kappa$-tree. Another nice property of perfect trees is that if any two of them are compatible, that is there is a perfect tree in their intersection, then there is a maximal such perfect tree. Two perfect $\kappa$-trees can have perfect $\kappa$-trees in their intersection but no maximal such tree. The second obstacle was that any useful generalization of Jensen's forcing to an inaccessible $\kappa$ had to be $\lt\kappa$-closed, but that meant that in the generalization of the construction we could not simply take the union posets at the limit stages because we would lose closure. But closing under sequences of length $\lt\kappa$ at limit stages could potentially unseal maximal antichains. This second obstacle seemed the more difficult to overcome, but it turned out that miraculously closing at limits to maintain a bunch of required closure properties did not unseal maximal antichains or cause any other trouble for the construction. The construction requires that $V$ satisfies $\diamondsuit_{\kappa^+}(\text{Cof}(\kappa))$ and in such a universe we have a recipe for constructing a subposet of the $\kappa$-Sacks forcing, let's call it $\mathbb J^{\kappa}$, with the properties that (1) it is $\lt\kappa$-closed, (2) it has the $\kappa^+$-cc and (3) it adds a unique generic subset of $\kappa$. We can also show that in a forcing extension by the bounded support product of length $\kappa$ of the $\mathbb J^{\kappa}$, the only $\mathbb J^{\kappa}$-generic subsets of $\kappa$ are those added on the slices of the generic filter. We can also construct finite iterations $\mathbb J^{\kappa}_n$, for $n\lt\omega$, of Jensen's forcing at an inaccessible $\kappa$ and show that they have unique generic filters. The uniqueness property is again a consequence of a more general uniqueness property for the tree iterations of $\mathbb J^{\kappa}$ along a tree of height $\omega$. Conditions in the tree iteration along a tree $\mathcal T$ are functions with domain some subtree of $\mathcal T$ of size $\lt\kappa$ and range $\bigcup_{n\lt\omega}\mathbb J^{\kappa}_n$ such that nodes on level $n$ get mapped to elements of $\mathbb J^{\kappa}_n$ and higher nodes cohere with lower nodes. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
At the moment, it seems that the details are going to work out to produce a model of Kelley-Morse together with the Choice Scheme in which the $\omega$-Dependent Choice Scheme fails. But I might have to retract (smiley face).
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;jensen:real&quot;&gt;R. Jensen, “Definable sets of minimal degree,” in &lt;i&gt;Mathematical logic and foundations of set theory (Proc.
              Internat. Colloq., Jerusalem, 1968)&lt;/i&gt;, North-Holland, Amsterdam, 1970, pp. 122–128. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;kanovei:productOfJensenReals&quot;&gt;V. Kanovei and V. Lyubetsky, “A countable definable set of reals containing no definable elements,” &lt;i&gt;Manuscript&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;FriedmanGitman:ModelOfACNotDC&quot;&gt;S.-D. Friedman, V. Gitman, and V. Kanovei, “A model of second-order arithmetic satisfying AC but not
              DC,” &lt;i&gt;J. Math. Log.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 19, no. 1, pp. 1850013, 39, 2019. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;GitmanHamkinsJohnstone:KMplus&quot;&gt;V. Gitman and J. D. Hamkins, “Kelley-Morse set theory and choice principles for classes.” &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Jensen's forcing is a subposet of Sacks forcing with two key properties (1) it has the ccc and (2) it adds a unique generic real. Another ccc forcing adding a generic real is, of course, Cohen's original forcing, but, as is well known, once you have added a Cohen generic, you have actually added continuum many of them, so no uniqueness is to be had there. Unlike Cohen's forcing, you cannot construct Jensen's forcing in any universe $V$, you need the guessing principle $\diamondsuit$, so, in particular, you are stuck with universes satisfying ${\rm CH}$. Although, in $L$, we can specify a unique Jensen's forcing, as we will see later, there is are variables in the construction that can result in different forcing notions, all with the required two properties. We will refer to any forcing constructed according to the recipe of Jensen's forcing (which we will sketch below) as $\mathbb J$. As the name suggests, the forcing $\mathbb J$ was discovered by Jensen in 1970, who used it to show that it is consistent to have a $\Pi^1_2$-definable non-constructible (sigleton) real {% cite jensen:real %}. Namely, you force with $\mathbb J$ over $L$, adding the unique generic real $r$ and argue that in $L[r]$, the singleton $\{r\}$ is $\Pi^1_2$-definable. This is the best possible result because, by Shoenfield's Absoluteness, every $\Sigma^1_2$-definable real has to be in $L$. More recently, Lyubetsky and Kanovei generalized the 'uniqueness of generic reals' property of Jensen's forcing to finite support $\omega$-length products of $\mathbb J$, showing that in a forcing extension by the finite support $\omega$-length product of $\mathbb J$, the only generic reals for $\mathbb J$ are the $\omega$-many slices of the generic filter {% cite kanovei:productOfJensenReals %}. Lyubetsky and Kanovei used their result to show that there can be a countable hereditarily ordinal definable set of reals without any definable members, namely the set consisting of the $\omega$-many generic reals in a forcing extension by the finite-support $\omega$-length product of $\mathbb J$. This answered a question posed on Math Overflow that the set theory community found quite exciting. Together with Sy Friedman, we defined the notion of 'finite iterations' $\mathbb J_n$ (of length $n$) of Jensen's forcing, for $n\lt\omega$, and showed that these too have unique generics. This notion is a bit more complicated than simply forcing with a name for a forcing constructed according to Jensen's recipe in the extension, because in order to ensure uniqueness we have to be more careful about what goes into the forcing. For such a carefully constructed finite iteration $\mathbb J_n$, there is a unique $n$-length sequence of generic reals. The uniqueness property for the finite iterations $\mathbb J_n$ comes out of a more complicated result about tree iterations of Jensen's forcing. Given a tree $\mathcal T$ of height $\omega$, such as say $\omega^{\lt\omega}$ or $\omega_1^{\lt\omega}$, we define that a condition in the iteration $\mathbb J_{\mathcal T}$ of Jensen's forcing along the tree $\mathcal T$ is a function $f$ from a finite subtree $T$ of $\mathcal T$ into $\bigcup_{n\lt\omega}\mathbb J_n$ such that for a node $s$ of length $n$ in $T$, $f(s)\in \mathbb J_n$ and having the coherence property that whenever $s\lt$ are nodes in $T$, then $f(t)$ restricted to the length of $s$ is equal to $f(s)$. Forcing with $\mathbb J_{\mathcal T}$ adds a tree whose nodes on level $n$ are (mutually) generic for $\mathbb J_n$. The uniqueness property is that in a forcing extension by $\mathbb J_{\mathcal T}$, the only finite sequences of reals that are generic for $\mathbb J_n$ are those coming from the nodes on level $n$ of the generic tree. We showed (with Kanovei) that a forcing extension of $L$ by the tree iteration $\mathbb J_{\omega_1^{\lt\omega}}$ has a symmetric submodel in which ${\rm AC}_\omega$ holds, but ${\rm DC}$ fails {% cite FriedmanGitman:ModelOfACNotDC %}. The symmetric model has the tree of the generic sequences for $\mathbb J_n$ but it doesn't have a branch through it, witnessing a violation of ${\rm DC}$. Moreover, the violation of ${\rm DC}$ is definable over $H_{\omega_1}$ of the symmetric submodel because we can express what it means for a sequence to be $L$-generic for $\mathbb J_n$ and the ordering on the sequences in the tree is just end-extension. It follows that the model of full second-order arithmetic (satisfying comprehension for all second-order definable assertions) consisting of the reals of the symmetric submodel satisfies the Choice Scheme, but not the Dependent Choice Scheme. The Choice Scheme and the Dependent Choice Scheme are choice principles for classes in the second-order context. The Choice Scheme asserts for any second-order formula $\varphi(n,X)$ that if for every number $n$, there is a class $X$ satisfying $\varphi(n,X)$, then there is a single class $Z$ coding a witness for $n$ on its $n$-th slice $Z_n$. The Dependent Choice scheme asserts that we can make $\omega$-many dependent choices over any second-order definable relation $\varphi(X,Y)$ on classes which doesn't have terminal nodes. It also shows that there is a model of ${\rm ZFC}^-$ (${\rm ZFC}$ without powerset), namely the $H_{\omega_1}$ of the symmetric submodel, in which the ${\rm DC}_\omega$-scheme fails. In first-order, the ${\rm DC}_{\alpha}$-scheme, for a regular cardinal $\alpha$, is a strengthening of ${\rm DC}_\alpha$, which asserts that we can make $\alpha$-many dependent choices over any definable relation without terminal nodes. It is easy to see that having powerset implies that the ${\rm DC}_\alpha$-scheme holds for every regular $\alpha$ by reflecting the relation to a large enough $V_\beta$. Jensen's forcing is a subposet of Sacks forcing, so its elements are perfect trees ordered by the subtree relation. So what is the recipe for constructing Jensen's forcing? The construction is certainly not straightforward. We construct a continuous chain of countable subposets $\mathbb J_\xi$ of Sacks forcing, for $\xi\lt\omega_1$, in $\omega_1$-many steps, using $\diamondsuit$ to seal maximal antichains and have $\mathbb J$ be the union of the chain. Along the way, a $\diamondsuit$-sequence gives us codes for 'nice' countable transitive models $M_\xi$ containing $\mathbb J_\xi$ and we force over $M_\xi$ to add an $M_\xi$-generic perfect tree, which together with $\mathbb J_\xi$ generates $\mathbb J_{\xi+1}$. Generic filters for the models $M_\xi$ exist in $V$ itself because the models are countable. The choice of the $\diamondsuit$-sequence and of the generic filters for the models $M_\xi$ can yield different posets $\mathbb J$ but each will have the required two properties. An extension $V[r]$ by $\mathbb J$ continues to satisfy $\diamondsuit$ because $\mathbb J$ is ccc. So we can construct in $V[r]$, a $\mathbb J$-like forcing following the same recipe. However, in order to construct the iterations $\mathbb J_n$, we don't use just any such forcing. In constructing the $\mathbb J$-like forcings in $V[r]$, we use forcing extensions of models $M_\xi$ chosen by the $\diamondsuit$-sequence from $V$. The original project of constructing a model of full second-order arithmetic with the Choice Scheme in which the Dependent Choice scheme fails was motivated by an analogous question in second-order set theory. The second-order set theory Kelley-Morse is considered to be one of the strongest second-order theories because it includes comprehension for all second-order assertions. But it turns out that classes in second-order set theory behave much nicer if the theory also includes choice principles for them. Think about how much nicer it is to work in ${\rm ZFC}$ instead of ${\rm ZF}$ (not that there is anything wrong with ${\rm ZF}$, things just get much messier there). Among these useful choice principles for classes are the Choice Scheme and the $\alpha$-Dependent Choice schemes ($\alpha\in{\rm REG}$ or $\alpha={\rm Ord}$) and these basically generalize their second-order arithmetic counterparts. The Choice Scheme asserts for every for second-order formula $\varphi(x,X)$ that if for every set $x$, there is a class $X$ witnessing $\varphi(x,X)$, then there is a single class $Z$ coding a witness for $x$ on its $x$-th slice $Z_x$. The $\alpha$-Dependent Choice Scheme asserts that we can make $\alpha$-many dependent choices over any second-order definable relation on classes without terminal nodes. We showed with Joel Hamkins that Kelley-Morse does not prove the Choice Scheme even for first-order formulas and just $\omega$-many choices {% cite GitmanHamkinsJohnstone:KMplus %}. The next question which arose was whether Kelley-Morse together with the Choice Scheme proved the $\omega$-Dependent Choice Scheme. The best way to start answering a question in second-order set theory is to search for its analogue in second-order arithmetic, where a great deal more work was done over the years. But it seemed that the analogous question in second-order arithmetic was not known! Simpson had claimed that full second-order arithmetic together with the Choice Scheme did not prove the Dependent Choice Scheme, but the proof appeared to be lost years ago. So Sy and I set out to prove it by generalizing the work of Lyubetsky and Kanovei on the uniqueness properties of products of $\mathbb J$ to tree iterations. It then turned out that Kanovei had already proved the result decades ago using (what else?) Jensen's forcing with a slightly different construction. So we ended up with a joint paper. Now the task remained to generalize the construction to obtain the desired result in second-order set theory. The agenda was to get an analogue of Jensen's forcing on an inaccesible cardinal $\kappa$, obtain a uniqueness property for some form of tree iterations of it, and force with the tree iteration over $L$ to obtain a symmetric submodel which had the tree of height $\omega$ of finite sequences generic for iterations of the inaccessible Jensen's forcing, but had no branch through the tree. The $V_\kappa$ of this model was going to be the $V_\kappa$ of $L$, and it together with its subsets in the symmetric submodel would be the desired model of Kelley-Morse with the Choice Scheme in which the $\omega$-Depedent Choice Scheme failed. There were two obstacles to generalizing the $\mathbb J$ construction to an inaccessible cardinal $\kappa$. The first was that perfect $\kappa$-trees do not behave as nicely as perfect trees because of the limit levels business. For instance, a union of perfect trees is a perfect tree, but a union of perfect $\kappa$-trees need not be a perfect $\kappa$-tree. Another nice property of perfect trees is that if any two of them are compatible, that is there is a perfect tree in their intersection, then there is a maximal such perfect tree. Two perfect $\kappa$-trees can have perfect $\kappa$-trees in their intersection but no maximal such tree. The second obstacle was that any useful generalization of Jensen's forcing to an inaccessible $\kappa$ had to be $\lt\kappa$-closed, but that meant that in the generalization of the construction we could not simply take the union posets at the limit stages because we would lose closure. But closing under sequences of length $\lt\kappa$ at limit stages could potentially unseal maximal antichains. This second obstacle seemed the more difficult to overcome, but it turned out that miraculously closing at limits to maintain a bunch of required closure properties did not unseal maximal antichains or cause any other trouble for the construction. The construction requires that $V$ satisfies $\diamondsuit_{\kappa^+}(\text{Cof}(\kappa))$ and in such a universe we have a recipe for constructing a subposet of the $\kappa$-Sacks forcing, let's call it $\mathbb J^{\kappa}$, with the properties that (1) it is $\lt\kappa$-closed, (2) it has the $\kappa^+$-cc and (3) it adds a unique generic subset of $\kappa$. We can also show that in a forcing extension by the bounded support product of length $\kappa$ of the $\mathbb J^{\kappa}$, the only $\mathbb J^{\kappa}$-generic subsets of $\kappa$ are those added on the slices of the generic filter. We can also construct finite iterations $\mathbb J^{\kappa}_n$, for $n\lt\omega$, of Jensen's forcing at an inaccessible $\kappa$ and show that they have unique generic filters. The uniqueness property is again a consequence of a more general uniqueness property for the tree iterations of $\mathbb J^{\kappa}$ along a tree of height $\omega$. Conditions in the tree iteration along a tree $\mathcal T$ are functions with domain some subtree of $\mathcal T$ of size $\lt\kappa$ and range $\bigcup_{n\lt\omega}\mathbb J^{\kappa}_n$ such that nodes on level $n$ get mapped to elements of $\mathbb J^{\kappa}_n$ and higher nodes cohere with lower nodes. At the moment, it seems that the details are going to work out to produce a model of Kelley-Morse together with the Choice Scheme in which the $\omega$-Dependent Choice Scheme fails. But I might have to retract (smiley face). References {% bibliography --cited %}</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Can a Cohen extension have an $\omega_1$-sequence of successively more generic Cohen reals?</title><link href="/research/2022/08/15/can-a-cohen-extension-have-an-omega-1-sequence-of-successively-more-generic-cohen-reals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can a Cohen extension have an $\omega_1$-sequence of successively more generic Cohen reals?" /><published>2022-08-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-08-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/research/2022/08/15/can-a-cohen-extension-have-an-omega-1-sequence-of-successively-more-generic-cohen-reals</id><content type="html" xml:base="/research/2022/08/15/can-a-cohen-extension-have-an-omega-1-sequence-of-successively-more-generic-cohen-reals.html">&lt;p&gt;
A forcing extension $V[g]$ by the Cohen forcing ${\rm Add}(\omega,1)$ has continuum many Cohen generic reals. Indeed, as &lt;a href='http://jdh.hamkins.org/'&gt;Joel Hamkins&lt;/a&gt; explains in this &lt;a href='https://mathoverflow.net/questions/99013/reals-added-after-cohen-forcing'&gt;Math Overflow answer&lt;/a&gt;, a Cohen extension has a perfect set of Cohen generic reals such that any two finite subsets of them are mutually generic. Since adding a Cohen real is isomorphic to adding $\omega$-many Cohen reals, a Cohen forcing extension also has countable sequences $\langle r_n\mid n\lt\omega\rangle$ of Cohen reals such that for every $n\lt\omega$, $r_n$ is Cohen generic over $V[\langle r_i\mid i\lt n\rangle]$. Can we push this to obtain a sequence $\langle r_\xi\mid\xi\lt\omega_1\rangle$ such that for every $\alpha\lt\omega_1$, $r_\alpha$ is Cohen generic over $V[\langle r_\xi\mid\xi\lt\alpha\rangle]$? This question arose out of my work with Richard Matthews on ${\rm ZFC}^-$-models and we were stumped on it for some time. My intuition was that the answer should be yes; after all, we are not asking that the sequence is generic for an $\omega_1$-product of Cohen reals. It turns out that Andreas Blass already solved the question years ago and my intuition was all wrong!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem:&lt;/strong&gt; (Blass &lt;a href=&quot;#blass:increasinglyGenericCohen&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;)
A Cohen forcing extension cannot have a sequence of Cohen reals $\langle r_\xi\mid\xi\lt\omega_1\rangle$ such that for every $\alpha\lt\omega_1$, $r_\alpha$ is Cohen generic over $V[\langle r_\xi\mid\xi\lt\alpha\rangle]$.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The proof sketch I give here is my modification of Blass's proof which will allow us to generalize the argument to the forcing ${\rm Add}(\kappa,1)$, adding a Cohen subset to $\kappa$, for an inaccessible $\kappa$.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Proof:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Let $\mathbb B$ be the Boolean completion of ${\rm Add}(\omega,1)$. In particular, $\mathbb B$ has a dense subset of size $\omega$. Now suppose that a forcing extension by $\mathbb B$ (equivalentely ${\rm Add}(\omega,1))$ has a sequence $\langle r_\xi\mid \xi\lt\omega_1\rangle$ of Cohen reals such that for every $\alpha\lt\omega_1$, $r_\alpha$ is Cohen generic over $V[\langle r_\xi\mid\xi\lt\alpha\rangle]$. The model $V[\langle r_\xi\mid\xi\lt\omega_1\rangle]$ is a generic extension of $V$ by a complete subalgebra $\mathbb D$ of $\mathbb B$ by the Intermediate Model Theorem of Solovay &lt;a href=&quot;#Grigorieff:IntermediateModels&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. Let's argue that $\mathbb D$ also has a dense subset of size $\omega$. Given a condition $p\in {\rm Add}(\omega,1)$, let $q_p$ be the infima of $b$ in $\mathbb D$ such that $p\leq b$. Each $q_p$ is in $\mathbb D$ by completeness and the conditions $q_p$ are dense in $\mathbb D$.  Let $\dot R$ be a $\mathbb D$-name such that it is forced by $1$ that (1) $\dot R$ is an $\omega_1$-sequence of successively more generic Cohen reals and (2) the extension by $\mathbb D$ is equal to the extension $V[\dot R]$. Then it is easy to see that the Boolean values $[[n\in \dot R(\xi)]]$ for $n\lt\omega$ and $\xi\lt\omega_1$ must generate $\mathbb D$. Next, observe that since $\mathbb D$ has a countable dense subset, there must be some $\alpha\lt\omega_1$ such that $\mathbb D$ is generated by the Boolean values $[[n\in \dot R(\xi)]]$ for $n\lt\omega$ and $\xi\lt\alpha$. But this means that if $V[G]$ is $\mathbb D$-generic, then $G$ can be recovered from the sequence $\langle R(\xi)\mid\xi\lt\alpha\rangle\, (R=\dot R_G)$, which contradicts that $R(\alpha)$ is $V[\langle R(\xi)\mid\xi\lt\alpha\rangle]$-generic. $\square$
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The proof easily generalizes to give the following result for an inaccessible cardinal $\kappa$.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem:&lt;/strong&gt; A forcing extension by ${\rm Add}(\kappa,1)$ cannot have a sequence, $\langle A_\xi\mid\xi\lt\kappa^+\rangle$ of subsets of $\kappa$ such that for every $\alpha\lt\kappa^+$, $A_\alpha$ is ${\rm Add}(\kappa,1)$-generic over $V[\langle A_\xi\mid\xi\lt\alpha\rangle]$.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I don't know whether the result holds for every regular cardinal $\kappa$ because the current argument relies on $\kappa^{\lt\kappa}=\kappa$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Question:&lt;/strong&gt;
Does the above result hold true for any regular cardinal $\kappa$?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Question&lt;/strong&gt;: Can Blass's theorem be proved using partial orders without reference to Boolean algebras? 
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;blass:increasinglyGenericCohen&quot;&gt;A. Blass, “The model of set theory generated by countably many generic
              reals,” &lt;i&gt;J. Symbolic Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 46, no. 4, pp. 732–752, 1981. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Grigorieff:IntermediateModels&quot;&gt;S. Grigorieff, “Intermediate submodels and generic extensions in set theory,” &lt;i&gt;Ann. Math. (2)&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 101, pp. 447–490, 1975. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">A forcing extension $V[g]$ by the Cohen forcing ${\rm Add}(\omega,1)$ has continuum many Cohen generic reals. Indeed, as Joel Hamkins explains in this Math Overflow answer, a Cohen extension has a perfect set of Cohen generic reals such that any two finite subsets of them are mutually generic. Since adding a Cohen real is isomorphic to adding $\omega$-many Cohen reals, a Cohen forcing extension also has countable sequences $\langle r_n\mid n\lt\omega\rangle$ of Cohen reals such that for every $n\lt\omega$, $r_n$ is Cohen generic over $V[\langle r_i\mid i\lt n\rangle]$. Can we push this to obtain a sequence $\langle r_\xi\mid\xi\lt\omega_1\rangle$ such that for every $\alpha\lt\omega_1$, $r_\alpha$ is Cohen generic over $V[\langle r_\xi\mid\xi\lt\alpha\rangle]$? This question arose out of my work with Richard Matthews on ${\rm ZFC}^-$-models and we were stumped on it for some time. My intuition was that the answer should be yes; after all, we are not asking that the sequence is generic for an $\omega_1$-product of Cohen reals. It turns out that Andreas Blass already solved the question years ago and my intuition was all wrong! Theorem: (Blass {% cite blass:increasinglyGenericCohen %}) A Cohen forcing extension cannot have a sequence of Cohen reals $\langle r_\xi\mid\xi\lt\omega_1\rangle$ such that for every $\alpha\lt\omega_1$, $r_\alpha$ is Cohen generic over $V[\langle r_\xi\mid\xi\lt\alpha\rangle]$. The proof sketch I give here is my modification of Blass's proof which will allow us to generalize the argument to the forcing ${\rm Add}(\kappa,1)$, adding a Cohen subset to $\kappa$, for an inaccessible $\kappa$. Proof: Let $\mathbb B$ be the Boolean completion of ${\rm Add}(\omega,1)$. In particular, $\mathbb B$ has a dense subset of size $\omega$. Now suppose that a forcing extension by $\mathbb B$ (equivalentely ${\rm Add}(\omega,1))$ has a sequence $\langle r_\xi\mid \xi\lt\omega_1\rangle$ of Cohen reals such that for every $\alpha\lt\omega_1$, $r_\alpha$ is Cohen generic over $V[\langle r_\xi\mid\xi\lt\alpha\rangle]$. The model $V[\langle r_\xi\mid\xi\lt\omega_1\rangle]$ is a generic extension of $V$ by a complete subalgebra $\mathbb D$ of $\mathbb B$ by the Intermediate Model Theorem of Solovay {% cite Grigorieff:IntermediateModels %}. Let's argue that $\mathbb D$ also has a dense subset of size $\omega$. Given a condition $p\in {\rm Add}(\omega,1)$, let $q_p$ be the infima of $b$ in $\mathbb D$ such that $p\leq b$. Each $q_p$ is in $\mathbb D$ by completeness and the conditions $q_p$ are dense in $\mathbb D$. Let $\dot R$ be a $\mathbb D$-name such that it is forced by $1$ that (1) $\dot R$ is an $\omega_1$-sequence of successively more generic Cohen reals and (2) the extension by $\mathbb D$ is equal to the extension $V[\dot R]$. Then it is easy to see that the Boolean values $[[n\in \dot R(\xi)]]$ for $n\lt\omega$ and $\xi\lt\omega_1$ must generate $\mathbb D$. Next, observe that since $\mathbb D$ has a countable dense subset, there must be some $\alpha\lt\omega_1$ such that $\mathbb D$ is generated by the Boolean values $[[n\in \dot R(\xi)]]$ for $n\lt\omega$ and $\xi\lt\alpha$. But this means that if $V[G]$ is $\mathbb D$-generic, then $G$ can be recovered from the sequence $\langle R(\xi)\mid\xi\lt\alpha\rangle\, (R=\dot R_G)$, which contradicts that $R(\alpha)$ is $V[\langle R(\xi)\mid\xi\lt\alpha\rangle]$-generic. $\square$ The proof easily generalizes to give the following result for an inaccessible cardinal $\kappa$. Theorem: A forcing extension by ${\rm Add}(\kappa,1)$ cannot have a sequence, $\langle A_\xi\mid\xi\lt\kappa^+\rangle$ of subsets of $\kappa$ such that for every $\alpha\lt\kappa^+$, $A_\alpha$ is ${\rm Add}(\kappa,1)$-generic over $V[\langle A_\xi\mid\xi\lt\alpha\rangle]$. I don't know whether the result holds for every regular cardinal $\kappa$ because the current argument relies on $\kappa^{\lt\kappa}=\kappa$. Question: Does the above result hold true for any regular cardinal $\kappa$? Question: Can Blass's theorem be proved using partial orders without reference to Boolean algebras? References {% bibliography --cited %}</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">ZFC without Power Set II: Reflection Strikes Back</title><link href="/publications/2022/08/03/zfc-without-powerset-ii-reflection-strikes-back.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="ZFC without Power Set II: Reflection Strikes Back" /><published>2022-08-03T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2022-08-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/publications/2022/08/03/zfc-without-powerset-ii-reflection-strikes-back</id><content type="html" xml:base="/publications/2022/08/03/zfc-without-powerset-ii-reflection-strikes-back.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;GitmanMatthews:ZFCwithoutPowersetII&quot;&gt;V. Gitman and R. Matthews, “ZFC without Power Set II: Reflection Strikes Back,” &lt;i&gt;Manuscript&lt;/i&gt;, 2022. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Many natural set-theoretic structures satisfy all the axioms of ${\rm ZFC}$ excluding the power set axiom. These include the structures $H_{\kappa^+}$ (the collection of all sets whose transitive closure has size at most $\kappa$ for a cardinal $\kappa$), forcing extensions of models of ${\rm ZFC}$ by pretame (but not tame) class forcing, and first-order structures bi-interpretable with models of the strong second-order set theory Kelley-Morse together with the choice scheme. The set theory that these structures satisfy is the theory ${\rm ZFC}^-$, whose axioms consist of the axioms of ${\rm ZFC}$ with the collection scheme in place of the replacement scheme and with the well-ordering principle (the assertion that every set can be well-ordered) in place of the axiom of choice (the assertion that every non-empty family of sets has a choice function). The reason for the particular choice of axioms comprising ${\rm ZFC}^-$ is that without the existence of power sets we lose certain equivalences between set theoretic assertions that we tend to take for granted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Definition:&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; Let ${\rm ZF}\text{-}$ be the theory ${\rm ZF}$ with the power set axiom removed. That is, ${\rm ZF}\text{-}$ consists of the axioms: extensionality, empty set, pairing, unions, infinity, the foundation scheme, the separation scheme and the replacement scheme.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let ${\rm ZFC}\text{-}$ denote the theory ${\rm ZF}\text{-}$ plus the well-ordering principle.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Let $\rm{ZF(C)}^-$ denote the theory $\rm{ZF(C)}^-$ plus the collection scheme.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Szczepaniak showed that the axiom of choice is not equivalent to the well-ordering principle over ${\rm ZF}^-$ (see &lt;a href=&quot;#zarach:unions_of_zfminus_models&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;) and therefore we choose to take the stronger principle when formulating the theory ${\rm ZFC}^-$. Zarach showed that the theory ${\rm ZFC}\text{-}$ does not imply the collection scheme &lt;a href=&quot;#Zarach1996:ReplacmentDoesNotImplyCollection&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. The first author et al. showed in &lt;a href=&quot;#zfcminus:gitmanhamkinsjohnstone&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt; that the theory ${\rm ZFC}\text{-}$ has many other undesirable behaviors: there are models of ${\rm ZFC}\text{-}$ in which $\omega_1$ is singular, in which every set of reals is countable but $\omega_1$ exists, and in which the Łoś Theorem fails for (class) ultrapowers.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Although the theory ${\rm ZFC}^-$ avoids these pathological behaviors, there is a number of useful properties of models of full ${\rm ZFC}$ that fail or are not known to hold in models of ${\rm ZFC}^-$, mostly as a consequence of the absence in these models of a hierarchy akin to the von Neumann hierarchy. It is known that ground model definability, the assertion that the model is definable in its set forcing extensions, can fail in models of ${\rm ZFC}^-$ &lt;a href=&quot;#gitmanjohnstone:groundmodels&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;. The intermediate model theorem, the assertion that any intermediate model between the model and its set-forcing extension is also its set-forcing extension, can fail &lt;a href=&quot;#AntosFriedmanGitman:booleanclassforcing&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;. If there is a non-trivial elementary embedding $j\colon V_{\lambda+1}\to V_{\lambda+1}$, namely the large cardinal axiom $I_1$ holds, then it gives rise to an elementary embedding $j^+ \colon H_{\lambda^+}\to H_{\lambda^+}$ which witnesses that Kunen's Inconsistency can fail for models of ${\rm ZFC}^-$ &lt;a href=&quot;#matthews:takingReinhardsPowerAway&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;. It is an open question whether ${\rm HOD}$, the collection of all hereditarily ordinal definable sets, is definable in models of ${\rm ZFC}^-$.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
One of the main themes of this article is the various ways in which the scheme version of dependent choice can fail in models of ${\rm ZFC}^-$.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Definition:&lt;/strong&gt;
The ${\rm DC}_\delta$-&lt;em&gt;scheme&lt;/em&gt;, for an infinite cardinal $\delta$, asserts for every formula $\varphi(x,y,a)$ that if for every set $x$, there is a set $y$ such that $\varphi(x,y,a)$ holds, then there is a function $f$ on $\delta$ such that for every $\xi\lt\delta$, $\varphi(f\upharpoonright\xi,f(\xi),a)$ holds. The ${\rm DC}_{\lt\rm{Ord}}$-&lt;em&gt;scheme&lt;/em&gt; is the scheme asserting that the ${\rm DC}_\delta$-scheme holds for every cardinal $\delta$.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
In other words, the ${\rm DC}_\delta$ schemes states that we can make $\delta$-many dependent choices along any definable relation without terminal nodes. The ${\rm DC}_\delta$-scheme generalizes the dependent choice axiom ${\rm DC}_\delta$ which makes the analogous assertion for set relations. The ${\rm DC}_{\lt\rm{Ord}}$-scheme follows from ${\rm ZFC}$ by reflecting the definable relation in question to some $V_\alpha$, and then using a well-ordering of $V_\alpha$ to obtain the sequence of dependent choices. It follows that the ${\rm DC}_{\lt\rm{Ord}}$-scheme holds in every structure $H_{\kappa^+}$. Also, forcing extensions of a model of ${\rm ZFC}$ by pretame forcing satisfy the the ${\rm DC}_{\lt\rm{Ord}}$-scheme.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The ${\rm DC}_\delta$-schemes have numerous applications. Over ${\rm ZFC}^-$, the ${\rm DC}_{\omega}$-scheme is equivalent to the &lt;em&gt;reflection principle&lt;/em&gt; which is the assertion that every formula reflects to a transitive set (missing reference). Although, there is no known reformulation of the ${\rm DC}_\delta$-scheme for uncountable $\delta$ in terms of a reflection principle, such a reformulation exists under mild existence of power set assumptions. Over ${\rm ZFC}^-$, for a regular cardinal $\delta$, the ${\rm DC}_\delta$-scheme implies that every proper class surjects onto $\delta$. It is not difficult to see that in a model of ${\rm ZFC}$ the class partial order ${\rm Add}({\rm Ord},1)$, whose conditions are partial functions on the ordinals ordered by extension, forces a global well-order without adding sets. The forcing ${\rm Add}({\rm Ord},1)$ does not add sets because it is set-distributive. In a model of ${\rm ZFC}$, the forcing ${\rm Add}({\rm Ord},1)$ is set-distributive if and only if the ${\rm DC}_{\lt\rm{Ord}}$-scheme holds. Thus, in a model of ${\rm ZFC} + {\rm DC}_{\lt\rm{Ord}}$-scheme we can force a global well-order without adding sets, and actually conversely if we can force a global well-order without adding sets using some forcing, then ${\rm Add}({\rm Ord},1)$ must be set-distributive. Thus, over models of ${\rm ZFC}^-$, the ${\rm DC}_{\lt\rm{Ord}}$-scheme is equivalent to being able to force a global well-order without adding sets. We will see another application of the ${\rm DC}_{\lt\rm{Ord}}$-scheme shortly to establishing a form of Kunen's Inconsistency for models of ${\rm ZFC}^-$.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Friedman et al. (missing reference) showed that the ${\rm DC}_\omega$-scheme can fail in a model of ${\rm ZFC^-}$. The counterexample model is the $H_{\omega_1}$ of a symmetric submodel of a forcing extension by the iteration of Jensen's forcing along the tree $\omega_1^{\lt\omega}$, in particular, $\omega$ is the largest cardinal in this model.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In this article we obtain the following failures of the various ${\rm DC}_\delta$-schemes in models of ${\rm ZFC}^-$.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem 1:&lt;/strong&gt;
Suppose that $V\models{\rm ZFC}+{\rm CH}$. Then every Cohen forcing extension of $V$ has a proper class transitive submodel satisfying ${\rm ZFC}^-$ in which the ${\rm DC}_{\omega}$-scheme holds, but the ${\rm DC}_{\omega_2}$-scheme fails.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The model was constructed by Zarach in &lt;a href=&quot;#zarach:unions_of_zfminus_models&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, but we show that the ${\rm DC}_{\omega_2}$-scheme fails there. The status of the ${\rm DC}_{\omega_1}$-scheme in this model is open. Note that this model, unlike the counterexample model of (missing reference), must have unboundedly many cardinals by virtue of being a proper class transitive submodel of a model of ${\rm ZFC}$.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem 2:&lt;/strong&gt;
Suppose that $V \models {\rm ZFC} + 2^\delta = \delta^+$ for some regular cardinal $\delta$. Then every forcing extension of $V$ by the poset ${\rm Add}(\delta,1)$ has a proper class transitive submodel satisfying ${\rm ZFC}^-$ in which the ${\rm DC}_\delta$-scheme holds, but the ${\rm DC}_{\delta^{++}}$-scheme fails.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The model above is constructed by generalizing Zarach's construction, however in these models we are unable to determine the status of the ${\rm DC}_{\delta^+}$-scheme. On the other hand, we are able to remove this gap by using Jensen's forcing instead.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem 3:&lt;/strong&gt;
Every forcing extension of $L$ by the $\omega$-length finite support product of Jensen's forcing has a proper class submodel satisfying ${\rm ZFC}^-$ in which the ${\rm DC}_\omega$-scheme holds, but the ${\rm DC}_{\omega_1}$-scheme fails.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem 4:&lt;/strong&gt; 
Suppose that $\kappa$ is inaccessible in $L$. Every forcing extension of $L$ by the $\kappa$-length bounded support product of the inaccessible Jensen's forcing has a proper class transitive submodel satisfying ${\rm ZFC}^-$ in which the ${\rm DC}_{\kappa}$-scheme holds, but the ${\rm DC}_{\kappa^+}$-scheme fails.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The inaccessible Jensen's forcing is a generalization of Jensen's forcing to a sub-poset of the $\kappa$-Sacks forcing, for an inaccessible cardinal $\kappa$, that was recently developed in (missing reference). Using this idea of union models we extend the result of (missing reference) to obtain a model of ${\rm ZFC}^-$ in which the reflection principle fails and for which there are unboundedly many cardinals.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem 5:&lt;/strong&gt;
Every forcing extension of $L$ by the iteration of Jensen's forcing along the class tree ${\rm Ord}^{\lt\omega}$ has a proper class transitive submodel $N$ satisfying ${\rm ZFC}^-$, with unboundedly many cardinals, in which the ${\rm DC}_{\omega}$-scheme fails.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The results of this article were originally motivated by an open question from the work of the second author on Kunen's Inconsistency in models of ${\rm ZFC}^-$ &lt;a href=&quot;#matthews:takingReinhardsPowerAway&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;. Suppose that $W\models{\rm ZFC}^-$ and $A\subseteq W$. We will say that $W\models{\rm ZFC}^-_A$ if $W$ continues to satisfy ${\rm ZFC}^-$ in the language expanded by a predicate for $A$.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem 6:&lt;/strong&gt; Suppose that $W\models{\rm ZFC}^-$. There is no non-trivial, cofinal, $\Sigma_0$-elementary embedding $j \colon W\to W$ such that $V_{\text{crit}(j)}$ exists in $W$ and $W\models{\rm ZFC}^-_j$.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Thus, in particular, the elementary embedding $j^+ \colon H_{\lambda^+}\to H_{\lambda^+}$ resulting from an $I_1$-embedding $j \colon V_{\lambda+1}\to V_{\lambda+1}$ cannot be cofinal. Moreover, the second author showed that if the model $W$ additionally satisfies the ${\rm DC}_{\lt\rm{Ord}}$-scheme, then the existence of $V_{\text{crit}(j)}$ follows from the other assumptions &lt;a href=&quot;#matthews:takingReinhardsPowerAway&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;. Thus, we have:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem 7:&lt;/strong&gt;
Suppose that $W \models {\rm ZFC}^- + {\rm DC}_{\lt\rm{Ord}}$-scheme. There is no non-trivial, cofinal, $\Sigma_0$-elementary embedding $j \colon W\to W$ such that $W\models{\rm ZFC}^-_j$.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As a step toward determining whether the existence of $V_{\text{crit}(j)}$ is truly necessary for Theorem 6, the second author asked:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Question:&lt;/strong&gt;
Suppose that $W\models{\rm ZFC}^-_j$ for a non-trivial, cofinal $j \colon W\to M$ with $M\subseteq W$. Does $V_{\text{crit}(j)}$ exist in $W$, does $\mathcal P (\omega)$ exist in $W$?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We answer the question negatively here using models of ${\rm ZFC}^-$ in which the ${\rm DC}_\delta$-scheme fails for some $\delta$.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem:&lt;/strong&gt;
There is a model $W\models{\rm ZFC}^-$ in which $\mathcal P (\omega)$ does not exist and which has a definable, non-trivial, cofinal, elementary embedding $j \colon W\to M\subseteq W$.

&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;zarach:unions_of_zfminus_models&quot;&gt;A. Zarach, “Unions of ${\rm ZF}^{-}$-models which are themselves
              ${\rm ZF}^{-}$-models,” in &lt;i&gt;Logic Colloquium ’80 (Prague, 1980)&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 108, Amsterdam: North-Holland, 1982, pp. 315–342. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Zarach1996:ReplacmentDoesNotImplyCollection&quot;&gt;A. M. Zarach, “Replacement $\nrightarrow$ collection,” in &lt;i&gt;Gödel ’96 (Brno, 1996)&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 6, Berlin: Springer, 1996, pp. 307–322. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;zfcminus:gitmanhamkinsjohnstone&quot;&gt;V. Gitman, J. D. Hamkins, and T. A. Johnstone, “What is the theory $\mathsf {ZFC}$ without power set?,” &lt;i&gt;MLQ Math. Log. Q.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 62, no. 4-5, pp. 391–406, 2016. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;gitmanjohnstone:groundmodels&quot;&gt;V. Gitman and T. A. Johnstone, “On ground model definability,” in &lt;i&gt;Infinity, Computability, and Metamathematics: Festschrift in honour of the 60th birthdays of Peter Koepke and Philip Welch&lt;/i&gt;, London, GB: College publications, 2014. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;AntosFriedmanGitman:booleanclassforcing&quot;&gt;C. Antos, S.-D. Friedman, and V. Gitman, “Boolean-valued class forcing,” &lt;i&gt;Fund. Math.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 255, no. 3, pp. 231–254, 2021. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;matthews:takingReinhardsPowerAway&quot;&gt;R. Matthews, “Taking Reinhardt’s Power Away,” &lt;i&gt;Manuscript&lt;/i&gt;, 2020. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">{% reference page.ref %} Many natural set-theoretic structures satisfy all the axioms of ${\rm ZFC}$ excluding the power set axiom. These include the structures $H_{\kappa^+}$ (the collection of all sets whose transitive closure has size at most $\kappa$ for a cardinal $\kappa$), forcing extensions of models of ${\rm ZFC}$ by pretame (but not tame) class forcing, and first-order structures bi-interpretable with models of the strong second-order set theory Kelley-Morse together with the choice scheme. The set theory that these structures satisfy is the theory ${\rm ZFC}^-$, whose axioms consist of the axioms of ${\rm ZFC}$ with the collection scheme in place of the replacement scheme and with the well-ordering principle (the assertion that every set can be well-ordered) in place of the axiom of choice (the assertion that every non-empty family of sets has a choice function). The reason for the particular choice of axioms comprising ${\rm ZFC}^-$ is that without the existence of power sets we lose certain equivalences between set theoretic assertions that we tend to take for granted. Definition: Let ${\rm ZF}\text{-}$ be the theory ${\rm ZF}$ with the power set axiom removed. That is, ${\rm ZF}\text{-}$ consists of the axioms: extensionality, empty set, pairing, unions, infinity, the foundation scheme, the separation scheme and the replacement scheme. Let ${\rm ZFC}\text{-}$ denote the theory ${\rm ZF}\text{-}$ plus the well-ordering principle. Let $\rm{ZF(C)}^-$ denote the theory $\rm{ZF(C)}^-$ plus the collection scheme. Szczepaniak showed that the axiom of choice is not equivalent to the well-ordering principle over ${\rm ZF}^-$ (see {% cite zarach:unions_of_zfminus_models %}) and therefore we choose to take the stronger principle when formulating the theory ${\rm ZFC}^-$. Zarach showed that the theory ${\rm ZFC}\text{-}$ does not imply the collection scheme {% cite Zarach1996:ReplacmentDoesNotImplyCollection %}. The first author et al. showed in {% cite zfcminus:gitmanhamkinsjohnstone %} that the theory ${\rm ZFC}\text{-}$ has many other undesirable behaviors: there are models of ${\rm ZFC}\text{-}$ in which $\omega_1$ is singular, in which every set of reals is countable but $\omega_1$ exists, and in which the Łoś Theorem fails for (class) ultrapowers. Although the theory ${\rm ZFC}^-$ avoids these pathological behaviors, there is a number of useful properties of models of full ${\rm ZFC}$ that fail or are not known to hold in models of ${\rm ZFC}^-$, mostly as a consequence of the absence in these models of a hierarchy akin to the von Neumann hierarchy. It is known that ground model definability, the assertion that the model is definable in its set forcing extensions, can fail in models of ${\rm ZFC}^-$ {% cite gitmanjohnstone:groundmodels %}. The intermediate model theorem, the assertion that any intermediate model between the model and its set-forcing extension is also its set-forcing extension, can fail {% cite AntosFriedmanGitman:booleanclassforcing %}. If there is a non-trivial elementary embedding $j\colon V_{\lambda+1}\to V_{\lambda+1}$, namely the large cardinal axiom $I_1$ holds, then it gives rise to an elementary embedding $j^+ \colon H_{\lambda^+}\to H_{\lambda^+}$ which witnesses that Kunen's Inconsistency can fail for models of ${\rm ZFC}^-$ {% cite matthews:takingReinhardsPowerAway %}. It is an open question whether ${\rm HOD}$, the collection of all hereditarily ordinal definable sets, is definable in models of ${\rm ZFC}^-$. One of the main themes of this article is the various ways in which the scheme version of dependent choice can fail in models of ${\rm ZFC}^-$. Definition: The ${\rm DC}_\delta$-scheme, for an infinite cardinal $\delta$, asserts for every formula $\varphi(x,y,a)$ that if for every set $x$, there is a set $y$ such that $\varphi(x,y,a)$ holds, then there is a function $f$ on $\delta$ such that for every $\xi\lt\delta$, $\varphi(f\upharpoonright\xi,f(\xi),a)$ holds. The ${\rm DC}_{\lt\rm{Ord}}$-scheme is the scheme asserting that the ${\rm DC}_\delta$-scheme holds for every cardinal $\delta$. In other words, the ${\rm DC}_\delta$ schemes states that we can make $\delta$-many dependent choices along any definable relation without terminal nodes. The ${\rm DC}_\delta$-scheme generalizes the dependent choice axiom ${\rm DC}_\delta$ which makes the analogous assertion for set relations. The ${\rm DC}_{\lt\rm{Ord}}$-scheme follows from ${\rm ZFC}$ by reflecting the definable relation in question to some $V_\alpha$, and then using a well-ordering of $V_\alpha$ to obtain the sequence of dependent choices. It follows that the ${\rm DC}_{\lt\rm{Ord}}$-scheme holds in every structure $H_{\kappa^+}$. Also, forcing extensions of a model of ${\rm ZFC}$ by pretame forcing satisfy the the ${\rm DC}_{\lt\rm{Ord}}$-scheme. The ${\rm DC}_\delta$-schemes have numerous applications. Over ${\rm ZFC}^-$, the ${\rm DC}_{\omega}$-scheme is equivalent to the reflection principle which is the assertion that every formula reflects to a transitive set {% cite friedmangitmankanovei19 %}. Although, there is no known reformulation of the ${\rm DC}_\delta$-scheme for uncountable $\delta$ in terms of a reflection principle, such a reformulation exists under mild existence of power set assumptions. Over ${\rm ZFC}^-$, for a regular cardinal $\delta$, the ${\rm DC}_\delta$-scheme implies that every proper class surjects onto $\delta$. It is not difficult to see that in a model of ${\rm ZFC}$ the class partial order ${\rm Add}({\rm Ord},1)$, whose conditions are partial functions on the ordinals ordered by extension, forces a global well-order without adding sets. The forcing ${\rm Add}({\rm Ord},1)$ does not add sets because it is set-distributive. In a model of ${\rm ZFC}$, the forcing ${\rm Add}({\rm Ord},1)$ is set-distributive if and only if the ${\rm DC}_{\lt\rm{Ord}}$-scheme holds. Thus, in a model of ${\rm ZFC} + {\rm DC}_{\lt\rm{Ord}}$-scheme we can force a global well-order without adding sets, and actually conversely if we can force a global well-order without adding sets using some forcing, then ${\rm Add}({\rm Ord},1)$ must be set-distributive. Thus, over models of ${\rm ZFC}^-$, the ${\rm DC}_{\lt\rm{Ord}}$-scheme is equivalent to being able to force a global well-order without adding sets. We will see another application of the ${\rm DC}_{\lt\rm{Ord}}$-scheme shortly to establishing a form of Kunen's Inconsistency for models of ${\rm ZFC}^-$. Friedman et al. {% cite friedmangitmankanovei19 %} showed that the ${\rm DC}_\omega$-scheme can fail in a model of ${\rm ZFC^-}$. The counterexample model is the $H_{\omega_1}$ of a symmetric submodel of a forcing extension by the iteration of Jensen's forcing along the tree $\omega_1^{\lt\omega}$, in particular, $\omega$ is the largest cardinal in this model. In this article we obtain the following failures of the various ${\rm DC}_\delta$-schemes in models of ${\rm ZFC}^-$. Theorem 1: Suppose that $V\models{\rm ZFC}+{\rm CH}$. Then every Cohen forcing extension of $V$ has a proper class transitive submodel satisfying ${\rm ZFC}^-$ in which the ${\rm DC}_{\omega}$-scheme holds, but the ${\rm DC}_{\omega_2}$-scheme fails. The model was constructed by Zarach in {% cite zarach:unions_of_zfminus_models %}, but we show that the ${\rm DC}_{\omega_2}$-scheme fails there. The status of the ${\rm DC}_{\omega_1}$-scheme in this model is open. Note that this model, unlike the counterexample model of {% cite friedmangitmankanovei19 %}, must have unboundedly many cardinals by virtue of being a proper class transitive submodel of a model of ${\rm ZFC}$. Theorem 2: Suppose that $V \models {\rm ZFC} + 2^\delta = \delta^+$ for some regular cardinal $\delta$. Then every forcing extension of $V$ by the poset ${\rm Add}(\delta,1)$ has a proper class transitive submodel satisfying ${\rm ZFC}^-$ in which the ${\rm DC}_\delta$-scheme holds, but the ${\rm DC}_{\delta^{++}}$-scheme fails. The model above is constructed by generalizing Zarach's construction, however in these models we are unable to determine the status of the ${\rm DC}_{\delta^+}$-scheme. On the other hand, we are able to remove this gap by using Jensen's forcing instead. Theorem 3: Every forcing extension of $L$ by the $\omega$-length finite support product of Jensen's forcing has a proper class submodel satisfying ${\rm ZFC}^-$ in which the ${\rm DC}_\omega$-scheme holds, but the ${\rm DC}_{\omega_1}$-scheme fails. Theorem 4: Suppose that $\kappa$ is inaccessible in $L$. Every forcing extension of $L$ by the $\kappa$-length bounded support product of the inaccessible Jensen's forcing has a proper class transitive submodel satisfying ${\rm ZFC}^-$ in which the ${\rm DC}_{\kappa}$-scheme holds, but the ${\rm DC}_{\kappa^+}$-scheme fails. The inaccessible Jensen's forcing is a generalization of Jensen's forcing to a sub-poset of the $\kappa$-Sacks forcing, for an inaccessible cardinal $\kappa$, that was recently developed in {% cite FriedmanGitman:InaccessibleJensen %}. Using this idea of union models we extend the result of {% cite friedmangitmankanovei19 %} to obtain a model of ${\rm ZFC}^-$ in which the reflection principle fails and for which there are unboundedly many cardinals. Theorem 5: Every forcing extension of $L$ by the iteration of Jensen's forcing along the class tree ${\rm Ord}^{\lt\omega}$ has a proper class transitive submodel $N$ satisfying ${\rm ZFC}^-$, with unboundedly many cardinals, in which the ${\rm DC}_{\omega}$-scheme fails. The results of this article were originally motivated by an open question from the work of the second author on Kunen's Inconsistency in models of ${\rm ZFC}^-$ {% cite matthews:takingReinhardsPowerAway %}. Suppose that $W\models{\rm ZFC}^-$ and $A\subseteq W$. We will say that $W\models{\rm ZFC}^-_A$ if $W$ continues to satisfy ${\rm ZFC}^-$ in the language expanded by a predicate for $A$. Theorem 6: Suppose that $W\models{\rm ZFC}^-$. There is no non-trivial, cofinal, $\Sigma_0$-elementary embedding $j \colon W\to W$ such that $V_{\text{crit}(j)}$ exists in $W$ and $W\models{\rm ZFC}^-_j$. Thus, in particular, the elementary embedding $j^+ \colon H_{\lambda^+}\to H_{\lambda^+}$ resulting from an $I_1$-embedding $j \colon V_{\lambda+1}\to V_{\lambda+1}$ cannot be cofinal. Moreover, the second author showed that if the model $W$ additionally satisfies the ${\rm DC}_{\lt\rm{Ord}}$-scheme, then the existence of $V_{\text{crit}(j)}$ follows from the other assumptions {% cite matthews:takingReinhardsPowerAway %}. Thus, we have: Theorem 7: Suppose that $W \models {\rm ZFC}^- + {\rm DC}_{\lt\rm{Ord}}$-scheme. There is no non-trivial, cofinal, $\Sigma_0$-elementary embedding $j \colon W\to W$ such that $W\models{\rm ZFC}^-_j$. As a step toward determining whether the existence of $V_{\text{crit}(j)}$ is truly necessary for Theorem 6, the second author asked: Question: Suppose that $W\models{\rm ZFC}^-_j$ for a non-trivial, cofinal $j \colon W\to M$ with $M\subseteq W$. Does $V_{\text{crit}(j)}$ exist in $W$, does $\mathcal P (\omega)$ exist in $W$? We answer the question negatively here using models of ${\rm ZFC}^-$ in which the ${\rm DC}_\delta$-scheme fails for some $\delta$. Theorem: There is a model $W\models{\rm ZFC}^-$ in which $\mathcal P (\omega)$ does not exist and which has a definable, non-trivial, cofinal, elementary embedding $j \colon W\to M\subseteq W$. References {% bibliography --cited %}</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Set theory without powerset</title><link href="/talks/2021/11/10/set-theory-without-powerset.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Set theory without powerset" /><published>2021-11-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-11-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/talks/2021/11/10/set-theory-without-powerset</id><content type="html" xml:base="/talks/2021/11/10/set-theory-without-powerset.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the Models and Sets Seminar, University of Leeds, November 10, 2021 (virtual).&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/ZFCwithoutPowersetTalk.pdf&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Many natural set-theoretic structures satisfy the basic axioms of set theory, but not the powerset axiom. These include the collections $H_{\kappa^+}$ of sets whose transitive closure has size at most $\kappa$, forcing extensions of models of ${\rm ZFC}$ by pretame (but not tame) forcing, and first-order models that are morally equivalent to models of the second-order Kelley-Morse set theory (with class choice). It turns out that a reasonable set theory in the absence of the powerset axiom is not simply ${\rm ZFC}$ with the powerset axiom removed. Without the powerset axiom, the Replacement scheme is not equivalent to the Collection scheme, and the various forms of the Axiom of Choice are not equivalent. In this talk, I will give an overview of the properties of a robust set theory without powerset, ${\rm ZFC}^-$, whose axioms are ${\rm ZFC}$ without the powerset axiom, with the Collection scheme instead of the Replacement scheme and the Well-Ordering Principle instead of the Axiom of Choice. While a great deal of standard set theory can be carried out in ${\rm ZFC}^-$, for instance, forcing works mostly as it does in ${\rm ZFC},$ there are several important properties that are known to fail and some which we still don't know whether they hold. For example, the Intermediate Model Theorem fails for ${\rm ZFC}^-$, and so does ground model definability, and it is not known whether ${\rm HOD}$ is definable. I will also discuss a strengthening of ${\rm ZFC}^-$ obtained by adding the Dependent Choice Scheme, and some rather strange ${\rm ZFC}^-$-models.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the Models and Sets Seminar, University of Leeds, November 10, 2021 (virtual).Slides</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Indestructibility for Ramsey cardinals</title><link href="/talks/2021/09/28/indestructibility-for-ramsey-cardinals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Indestructibility for Ramsey cardinals" /><published>2021-09-28T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-09-28T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/talks/2021/09/28/indestructibility-for-ramsey-cardinals</id><content type="html" xml:base="/talks/2021/09/28/indestructibility-for-ramsey-cardinals.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the Minisymposium on ‘Large cardinals’, Joint Annual Conference of DMV and the ÖMG, University of Passau, September 28, 2021 (virtual).&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/indestructibleramseytalk.pdf&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Although Ramsey cardinals $\kappa$ were originally defined, as their name suggests, via a Ramsey-type coloring property, they can also be characterized by the existence of elementary embeddings on weak $\kappa$-models (transitive models $M\models{\rm ZFC}^-$ of size $\kappa$ with $\kappa\in M$). There is a standard toolbox of techniques for showing that a large cardinal characterized by the existence of some form of elementary embeddings is indestructible by a given forcing notion. The indestructibility arguments proceed by lifting an elementary embedding $j:M\to N$ with $\text{crit}(j)=\kappa$ of the type characterizing the large cardinal to an elementary embedding $j:M[G]\to N[H]$ in a forcing extension $V[G]$ by the desired forcing, and it is then verified that the lifted embedding is also of the type characterizing the large cardinal. The standard toolbox cannot be applied directly to elementary embeddings characterizing Ramsey cardinals (and other large cardinals in the vicinity of Ramsey cardinals) because the elementary embeddings $j:M\to N$ are on models that are not closed under $\lt\kappa$-sequences and standard arguments rely on the closure of the target model to build the $N$-generic filter $H$. Moreover, Ramsey-type embedding have special properties, which are not obviously preserved by the lifts. In this talk, I will provide techniques for lifting Ramsey-type elementary embeddings to a forcing extension. Using these techniques we can show that Ramsey cardinals are indestructible by the canonical forcing of the ${\rm GCH}$, that they can be made indestructible by the forcing ${\rm Add}(\kappa,\theta)$ (which implies that it is consistent for ${\rm GCH}$ to fail at a Ramsey cardinal), that they are indestructible by fast function forcing, and that they can be made indestructible by the club-shooting forcing, among other examples. This is joint work with Thomas Johnstone.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the Minisymposium on ‘Large cardinals’, Joint Annual Conference of DMV and the ÖMG, University of Passau, September 28, 2021 (virtual).Slides</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Jensen’s forcing at an inaccessible</title><link href="/talks/2021/09/14/jensen-forcing-at-an-inaccessible.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Jensen's forcing at an inaccessible" /><published>2021-09-14T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-09-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/talks/2021/09/14/jensen-forcing-at-an-inaccessible</id><content type="html" xml:base="/talks/2021/09/14/jensen-forcing-at-an-inaccessible.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the &lt;a href='https://conferences.cirm-math.fr/2370.html'&gt;16th International Luminy Workshop in Set Theory&lt;/a&gt;, CIRM, September 14, 2021 (virtual).&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/JensenInaccessibleTalk.pdf&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Jensen constructed in $L$, using $\diamondsuit$, a subposet of the Sacks forcing with the ccc and the property that it adds a unique generic real over $L$ (in contrast to, say, Cohen forcing which adds continuum many generic reals). He used what came to be known as Jensen's forcing to show that, consistently, there can be a $\Pi^1_2$-definable non-constructible real. The 'uniqueness of generic reals' property of Jensen's forcing can be extended to products of Jensen's forcing and in some form to iterations, when forcing over $L$. Indeed, a Jensen-like forcing with the uniqueness properties can be constructed in any universe with a $\diamondsuit$-sequence. In a joint work with Friedman and Kanovei, we used a tree iteration of Jensen's forcing to construct (in a symmetric submodel of the forcing extension) a model of full second-order arithmetic ${\rm Z}_2$ with the choice scheme in which the dependent choice scheme failed for a $\Pi^1_2$-assertion (this is optimal because ${\rm Z}_2$ with the choice scheme implies dependent choice for $\Sigma^1_2$-assertions). In this talk, I will present a generalization of Jensen's forcing to a sub-forcing of the $\kappa$-Sacks forcing for an inaccessible cardinal $\kappa$. I will show that Jensen's forcing at an inaccessible has some of the same 'uniqueness of generics' properties as Jensen's forcing. One of the goals of this work is to prove an analogue of the second-order arithmetic result for second-order set theory by showing that the dependent choice scheme is independent of the second-order Kelley-Morse set theory with the choice scheme. This is joint work with Sy-David Friedman.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the 16th International Luminy Workshop in Set Theory, CIRM, September 14, 2021 (virtual).Slides</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Indestructibility for Ramsey and Ramsey-like cardinals</title><link href="/publications/2021/09/01/indestructibility-for-ramsey-and-ramsey-like-cardinals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Indestructibility for Ramsey and Ramsey-like cardinals" /><published>2021-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-09-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/publications/2021/09/01/indestructibility-for-ramsey-and-ramsey-like-cardinals</id><content type="html" xml:base="/publications/2021/09/01/indestructibility-for-ramsey-and-ramsey-like-cardinals.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;gitman:ramseyindes&quot;&gt;V. Gitman and T. A. Johnstone, “Indestructibility properties of Ramsey and Ramsey-like
              cardinals,” &lt;i&gt;Ann. Pure Appl. Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 173, no. 6, pp. Paper No. 103106, 30, 2022. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The study of indestructibility properties of large cardinals was initiated by a seminal result of Lévy and Solovay showing that measurable cardinals cannot be destroyed by small forcing &lt;a href=&quot;#levysolovay:ch&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. The Lévy-Solovay phenomenon is now known to extend to most large cardinal notions, which means, in particular, that large cardinals cannot decide ${\rm CH}$ or other independent set theoretic statements that can be manipulated by small forcing. This, taken more generally, is the significance of studying indestructibility properties of large cardinals: it provides a means of verifying which set theoretic properties, among those that can be manipulated by forcing, are compatible with a given large cardinal. There are other applications of indestructibility, such as in separating closely related large cardinal notions by forcing to destroy a part of a large cardinal property, while preserving the rest.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;
Ramsey cardinals were introduced by Erdős and Hajnal in 1962 &lt;a href=&quot;#erdos:ramsey&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;, who defined that a cardinal $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;Ramsey&lt;/em&gt; if every coloring $f:[\kappa]^{\lt\omega}\to 2$ of finite tuples of elements of $\kappa$ into two colors has a homogeneous set of size $\kappa$. Ramsey cardinals can also be characterized by the existence of indiscernibles for certain structures as well as by the existence of iterable ultrafilters for certain families of subsets of $\kappa$ of size $\kappa$. Historically very little was known about the indestructibility properties of Ramsey cardinals. A folklore proof, using their original characterization, shows that Ramsey cardinals are indestructible by small forcing &lt;a href=&quot;#kanamori:higher&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt; (Section 10). Jensen in &lt;a href=&quot;#jensen:indestructibility&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt; hinted at a proof that Ramsey cardinals are indestructible by a product forcing which yields the ${\rm GCH}$ in the forcing extension. Finally, Welch showed in &lt;a href=&quot;#welch:codingpreserveramsey&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;, using a characterization of Ramsey cardinals in terms of the existence of indiscernibles, that they are indestructible by the forcing to code the universe into a real.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Most general techniques for establishing indestructibility properties of a large cardinal require it to have a characterization in terms of the existence of elementary embeddings. The indestructibility arguments then proceed by showing how to lift (extend) the elementary embedding(s) characterizing the large cardinal from the ground model $V$ to the forcing extension $V[G]$, thus verifying that the large cardinal maintains its property there. It is more common to think of the large cardinals including and above measurable cardinals as being characterized by the existence of elementary embeddings. But in fact, even smaller large cardinals that we typically associate with combinatorial definitions, such as weakly compact and indescribable cardinals, have elementary embedding characterizations. These smaller large cardinals $\kappa$ are usually characterized by the existence of elementary embeddings of weak $\kappa$-models (transitive models of ${\rm ZFC}^-$ of size $\kappa$ with height above $\kappa$) or of $\kappa$-models (additionally closed under $\lt\kappa$-sequences).  Mitchell discovered an elementary embeddings characterization of Ramsey cardinals involving the existence of countably complete ultrafilters for weak $\kappa$-models &lt;a href=&quot;#mitchell:ramsey&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;, but it was not extensively studied until the first author started to explore it in her dissertation with the purpose of obtaining indestructibility results for Ramsey cardinals &lt;a href=&quot;#gitman:dissertation&quot;&gt;[7]&lt;/a&gt;. In the process, the first author generalized aspects of the Ramsey embeddings to introduce new Ramsey-like large cardinal notions: $\alpha$-iterable, strongly Ramsey, and super Ramsey cardinals &lt;a href=&quot;#gitman:ramsey&quot;&gt;[8]&lt;/a&gt;. Since then other Ramsey-like large cardinal notions have been introduced in, for example, &lt;a href=&quot;#HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;[9]&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;#HolyLucke:smallModels&quot;&gt;[10]&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The elementary embeddings characterization of Ramsey cardinals does not easily lend itself to standard indestructibility techniques. The first difficulty is that the embeddings are on weak $\kappa$-models, as opposed to $\kappa$-models, and these may not even be closed under countable sequences. The second difficulty is that the embeddings are ultrapowers by countably complete ultrafilters and while the lift of an ultrapower embedding remains an ultrapower embedding by a potentially larger ultrafilter, it is not trivial to verify that the larger ultrafilter is still countably complete. Strongly Ramsey and super Ramsey cardinals, which, as the name suggests, are a strengthening of Ramsey cardinals, were defined to have embedding characterizations remedying the deficiencies of Ramsey embeddings with respect to indestructibility arguments. The $\alpha$-iterable cardinals generalized a different aspect of the Ramsey embeddings. They are defined by the existence of partially iterable ultrafilters for weak $\kappa$-models, a requirement that weakens the Ramsey embeddings characterization because countably complete ultrafilters are fully iterable.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In this article, we prove basic indestructibility results for Ramsey, $\alpha$-iterable, strongly Ramsey, and super Ramsey cardinals using a mix of old and newly introduced techniques. We use standard techniques to establish indestructibility properties of strongly Ramsey and super Ramsey cardinals, as their definition was directly motivated to make them easily amenable to these techniques. We develop techniques for lifting embeddings on models without closure. We show that if the forcing notion is countably closed, then a lift of the ultrapower by a countably complete ultrafilter retains this property in the forcing extension. The combination of these new techniques allows us to prove the same basic indestructibility results for Ramsey cardinals as for strongly and super Ramsey cardinals. For the $\alpha$-iterable cardinals, we develop techniques for simultaneously lifting entire iterations of embeddings, so that we can verify that the potentially larger ultrafilter associated with the lift of the first ultrapower in the iteration continues to have at least the iterability of the original ultrafilter. The new indestructibility techniques we introduce can potentially be used to establish a variety of indestructibility results for these and similar large cardinal notions. Here, we obtain the following indestructibility results.
&lt;/p&gt;



&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;:
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Ramsey, $\alpha$-iterable, strongly Ramsey, and super Ramsey cardinals $\kappa$ are indestructible by:
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
small forcing,
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
the canonical forcing of the ${\rm GCH}$,
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
the forcing to add a fast function on $\kappa$,
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
 If $\kappa$ is one of these large cardinals, then there is a forcing extension in which the large cardinal property of $\kappa$ becomes indestructible by the forcing ${\rm Add}(\kappa,\theta)$ for every cardinal $\theta$.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
These indestructibility properties have the following consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Corollary&lt;/strong&gt;:
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
If $\kappa$ is Ramsey, $\alpha$-iterable, strongly Ramsey, or super Ramsey, then there is a forcing extension preserving this in which the ${\rm GCH}$ fails at $\kappa$.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If $\kappa$ is Ramsey, $\alpha$-iterable, strongly Ramsey, or super Ramsey, then there is a a forcing extension preserving this in which $\kappa$ is not even weakly compact in ${\rm HOD}$.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
If $\kappa$ is Ramsey, then there is a forcing extension destroying this, while preserving that $\kappa$ is virtually Ramsey.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
To establish $(3)$, we use techniques from (missing reference). The &lt;em&gt;virtually Ramsey&lt;/em&gt; cardinals from $(4)$  were introduced in  &lt;a href=&quot;#welch:ramsey&quot;&gt;[11]&lt;/a&gt; as an upper bound on the consistency strength of a variant of Chang's Conjecture studied there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;levysolovay:ch&quot;&gt;A. Lévy and R. M. Solovay, “Measurable cardinals and the continuum hypothesis,” &lt;i&gt;Israel J. Math.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 5, pp. 234–248, 1967. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;erdos:ramsey&quot;&gt;P. Erdős and A. Hajnal, “Some remarks concerning our paper ‘On the structure of set-mappings’. Non-existence of a two-valued $σ$-measure for the first uncountable inaccessible cardinal,” &lt;i&gt;Acta Math. Acad. Sci. Hungar.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 13, pp. 223–226, 1962. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;kanamori:higher&quot;&gt;A. Kanamori, &lt;i&gt;The higher infinite&lt;/i&gt;, Second. Berlin: Springer-Verlag, 2009, p. xxii+536. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;jensen:indestructibility&quot;&gt;R. B. Jensen, “Measurable cardinals and the ${\rm GCH}$,” in &lt;i&gt;Axiomatic set theory (Proc. Sympos. Pure Math., Vol.
              XIII, Part II, Univ. California, Los Angeles,
              Calif., 1967)&lt;/i&gt;, Providence, R.I.: Amer. Math. Soc., 1974, pp. 175–178. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;welch:codingpreserveramsey&quot;&gt;A. Beller, R. Jensen, and P. Welch, &lt;i&gt;Coding the universe&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 47. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1982, p. i+353. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;mitchell:ramsey&quot;&gt;W. Mitchell, “Ramsey cardinals and constructibility,” &lt;i&gt;J. Symbolic Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 44, no. 2, pp. 260–266, 1979. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;gitman:dissertation&quot;&gt;V. Gitman, &lt;i&gt;Applications of the proper forcing axiom to models of Peano
              arithmetic&lt;/i&gt;. ProQuest LLC, Ann Arbor, MI, 2007, p. 149. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;gitman:ramsey&quot;&gt;V. Gitman, “Ramsey-like cardinals,” &lt;i&gt;The Journal of Symbolic Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 76, no. 2, pp. 519–540, 2011. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;P. Holy and P. Schlicht, “A hierarchy of Ramsey-like cardinals,” &lt;i&gt;Fund. Math.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 242, no. 1, pp. 49–74, 2018. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;HolyLucke:smallModels&quot;&gt;P. Holy and P. Lücke, “Small Models, Large Cardinals, and Induced Ideals,” &lt;i&gt;Manuscript&lt;/i&gt;, 2020. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;welch:ramsey&quot;&gt;I. Sharpe and P. Welch, “Greatly Erdős cardinals with some generalizations to
              the Chang and Ramsey properties,” &lt;i&gt;Ann. Pure Appl. Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 162, no. 11, pp. 863–902, 2011. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">{% reference page.ref %} The study of indestructibility properties of large cardinals was initiated by a seminal result of Lévy and Solovay showing that measurable cardinals cannot be destroyed by small forcing {% cite levysolovay:ch %}. The Lévy-Solovay phenomenon is now known to extend to most large cardinal notions, which means, in particular, that large cardinals cannot decide ${\rm CH}$ or other independent set theoretic statements that can be manipulated by small forcing. This, taken more generally, is the significance of studying indestructibility properties of large cardinals: it provides a means of verifying which set theoretic properties, among those that can be manipulated by forcing, are compatible with a given large cardinal. There are other applications of indestructibility, such as in separating closely related large cardinal notions by forcing to destroy a part of a large cardinal property, while preserving the rest. Ramsey cardinals were introduced by Erdős and Hajnal in 1962 {% cite erdos:ramsey %}, who defined that a cardinal $\kappa$ is Ramsey if every coloring $f:[\kappa]^{\lt\omega}\to 2$ of finite tuples of elements of $\kappa$ into two colors has a homogeneous set of size $\kappa$. Ramsey cardinals can also be characterized by the existence of indiscernibles for certain structures as well as by the existence of iterable ultrafilters for certain families of subsets of $\kappa$ of size $\kappa$. Historically very little was known about the indestructibility properties of Ramsey cardinals. A folklore proof, using their original characterization, shows that Ramsey cardinals are indestructible by small forcing {% cite kanamori:higher %} (Section 10). Jensen in {% cite jensen:indestructibility %} hinted at a proof that Ramsey cardinals are indestructible by a product forcing which yields the ${\rm GCH}$ in the forcing extension. Finally, Welch showed in {% cite welch:codingpreserveramsey %}, using a characterization of Ramsey cardinals in terms of the existence of indiscernibles, that they are indestructible by the forcing to code the universe into a real. Most general techniques for establishing indestructibility properties of a large cardinal require it to have a characterization in terms of the existence of elementary embeddings. The indestructibility arguments then proceed by showing how to lift (extend) the elementary embedding(s) characterizing the large cardinal from the ground model $V$ to the forcing extension $V[G]$, thus verifying that the large cardinal maintains its property there. It is more common to think of the large cardinals including and above measurable cardinals as being characterized by the existence of elementary embeddings. But in fact, even smaller large cardinals that we typically associate with combinatorial definitions, such as weakly compact and indescribable cardinals, have elementary embedding characterizations. These smaller large cardinals $\kappa$ are usually characterized by the existence of elementary embeddings of weak $\kappa$-models (transitive models of ${\rm ZFC}^-$ of size $\kappa$ with height above $\kappa$) or of $\kappa$-models (additionally closed under $\lt\kappa$-sequences). Mitchell discovered an elementary embeddings characterization of Ramsey cardinals involving the existence of countably complete ultrafilters for weak $\kappa$-models {% cite mitchell:ramsey %}, but it was not extensively studied until the first author started to explore it in her dissertation with the purpose of obtaining indestructibility results for Ramsey cardinals {% cite gitman:dissertation %}. In the process, the first author generalized aspects of the Ramsey embeddings to introduce new Ramsey-like large cardinal notions: $\alpha$-iterable, strongly Ramsey, and super Ramsey cardinals {% cite gitman:ramsey %}. Since then other Ramsey-like large cardinal notions have been introduced in, for example, {% cite HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals %} and {% cite HolyLucke:smallModels %}. The elementary embeddings characterization of Ramsey cardinals does not easily lend itself to standard indestructibility techniques. The first difficulty is that the embeddings are on weak $\kappa$-models, as opposed to $\kappa$-models, and these may not even be closed under countable sequences. The second difficulty is that the embeddings are ultrapowers by countably complete ultrafilters and while the lift of an ultrapower embedding remains an ultrapower embedding by a potentially larger ultrafilter, it is not trivial to verify that the larger ultrafilter is still countably complete. Strongly Ramsey and super Ramsey cardinals, which, as the name suggests, are a strengthening of Ramsey cardinals, were defined to have embedding characterizations remedying the deficiencies of Ramsey embeddings with respect to indestructibility arguments. The $\alpha$-iterable cardinals generalized a different aspect of the Ramsey embeddings. They are defined by the existence of partially iterable ultrafilters for weak $\kappa$-models, a requirement that weakens the Ramsey embeddings characterization because countably complete ultrafilters are fully iterable. In this article, we prove basic indestructibility results for Ramsey, $\alpha$-iterable, strongly Ramsey, and super Ramsey cardinals using a mix of old and newly introduced techniques. We use standard techniques to establish indestructibility properties of strongly Ramsey and super Ramsey cardinals, as their definition was directly motivated to make them easily amenable to these techniques. We develop techniques for lifting embeddings on models without closure. We show that if the forcing notion is countably closed, then a lift of the ultrapower by a countably complete ultrafilter retains this property in the forcing extension. The combination of these new techniques allows us to prove the same basic indestructibility results for Ramsey cardinals as for strongly and super Ramsey cardinals. For the $\alpha$-iterable cardinals, we develop techniques for simultaneously lifting entire iterations of embeddings, so that we can verify that the potentially larger ultrafilter associated with the lift of the first ultrapower in the iteration continues to have at least the iterability of the original ultrafilter. The new indestructibility techniques we introduce can potentially be used to establish a variety of indestructibility results for these and similar large cardinal notions. Here, we obtain the following indestructibility results. Theorem: Ramsey, $\alpha$-iterable, strongly Ramsey, and super Ramsey cardinals $\kappa$ are indestructible by: small forcing, the canonical forcing of the ${\rm GCH}$, the forcing to add a fast function on $\kappa$, If $\kappa$ is one of these large cardinals, then there is a forcing extension in which the large cardinal property of $\kappa$ becomes indestructible by the forcing ${\rm Add}(\kappa,\theta)$ for every cardinal $\theta$. These indestructibility properties have the following consequences. Corollary: If $\kappa$ is Ramsey, $\alpha$-iterable, strongly Ramsey, or super Ramsey, then there is a forcing extension preserving this in which the ${\rm GCH}$ fails at $\kappa$. If $\kappa$ is Ramsey, $\alpha$-iterable, strongly Ramsey, or super Ramsey, then there is a a forcing extension preserving this in which $\kappa$ is not even weakly compact in ${\rm HOD}$. If $\kappa$ is Ramsey, then there is a forcing extension destroying this, while preserving that $\kappa$ is virtually Ramsey. To establish $(3)$, we use techniques from {% cite ChengFriedmanHamkins2015:LargeCardinalsNeedNotBeLargeInHOD %}. The virtually Ramsey cardinals from $(4)$ were introduced in {% cite welch:ramsey %} as an upper bound on the consistency strength of a variant of Chang's Conjecture studied there. References {% bibliography --cited %}</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Characterizing large cardinals via abstract logics</title><link href="/talks/2021/07/14/characterizing-large-cardinals-via-abstract-logics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Characterizing large cardinals via abstract logics" /><published>2021-07-14T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-07-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/talks/2021/07/14/characterizing-large-cardinals-via-abstract-logics</id><content type="html" xml:base="/talks/2021/07/14/characterizing-large-cardinals-via-abstract-logics.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the Münster Logic Seminar, University of
Münster,  July 14, 2021 (virtual).&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The abstract and slides can be found in this &lt;a href='/talks/2021/06/17/characterizing-large-cardinals-via-abstract-logics/'&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the Münster Logic Seminar, University of Münster, July 14, 2021 (virtual).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Baby measurable cardinals</title><link href="/projects/2021/07/03/baby-measurable-cardinals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Baby measurable cardinals" /><published>2021-07-03T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-07-03T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/projects/2021/07/03/baby-measurable-cardinals</id><content type="html" xml:base="/projects/2021/07/03/baby-measurable-cardinals.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;GitmanSchlicht:babyMeasurableCardinals&quot;&gt;V. Gitman and S. Philipp, “Baby measurable cardinals,” &lt;i&gt;Manuscript&lt;/i&gt;, 2020. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; 
Measurable cardinals and most stronger large cardinals are defined by the existence of elementary embeddings $j:V\to M$ from the universe $V$ into an inner model $M$ with that cardinal as the critical point. Stronger large cardinal axioms impose additional assumptions on the target model $M$ that allow it to capture more and more sets from $V$. Weakly compact and many other smaller large cardinals are defined via combinatorial properties, often involving existence of large homogeneous sets for colorings. But almost all of them also have elementary embedding characterizations that, like the larger large cardinals, follow prescribed patterns as consistency strength grows. These smaller large cardinals $\kappa$ are characterized by elementary embeddings of models $\langle M,\in\rangle\models{\rm ZFC}^-$ of size $\kappa$, most often transitive, with critical point $\kappa$, and usually, but not always, with well-founded targets. ${\rm ZFC}^-$ is the theory ${\rm ZFC}$ with the powerset axiom removed, the collection scheme in place of the replacement scheme, and the version of the axiom of choice which states that every set can be well-ordered.(Without the powerset axiom, collection and replacement schemes are not equivalent and neither are the various forms of the axiom of choice. See &lt;a href=&quot;#zarach:unions_of_zfminus_models&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;#zfcminus:gitmanhamkinsjohnstone&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;.) In many cases, the existence of these embeddings can be equivalently expressed in terms of the existence of certain ultrafilters on the subsets of $\kappa$ contained in $M$.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Suppose $\langle M,\in\rangle \models{\rm ZFC}^-$ is a transitive model of size $\kappa$ with $\kappa\in M$ (we will give precise definitions and drop the transitivity requirement in the next section). We call such structures &lt;em&gt;weak $\kappa$-models&lt;/em&gt;. We will call a filter $U$, on the subsets of $\kappa$ of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$, an &lt;em&gt;$M$-ultrafilter&lt;/em&gt; if the structure $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$, together with a predicate for $U$, satisfies that $U$ is a uniform, normal ultrafilter on $\kappa$. What this says is that $U$ is an ultrafilter on the subsets of $\kappa$ that live in $M$ and if a $\kappa$-length sequence of elements of $U$ is an element of $M$, then its diagonal intersection is in $U$. The Łoś-Theorem holds for ultrapowers by an $M$-ultrafilter, but the ultrapower need not be well-founded. Note that the filter $U$ may not be countably complete for sequences outside of $M$. The $M$-ultrafilter $U$, is in most interesting cases, external to $M$ and even though $\langle M,\in\rangle\models{\rm ZFC}^-$, separation and replacement can fail completely in the structure $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$ once we let $M$ know about $U$. In the same way that making the inner model $M$ closer to $V$ in the characterizations of larger large cardinals increases strength, for the smaller large cardinals, we increase strength by making $M$ be more compatible with $U$, which amounts to $M$ being more correct about the properties of $U$ or to having more of the ${\rm ZFC}^-$ axioms in the structure $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's look at some examples. A cardinal $\kappa$ is weakly compact if and only if it is inaccessible and every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ for which there is a (externally) countably complete $M$-ultrafilter $U$ (in particular the ultrapower is well-founded). A cardinal $\kappa$ is completely ineffable if and only if every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ for which there is an $M$-ultrafilter $U$ such that $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$ satisfies $\Sigma_0$-separation (but with a potentially ill-founded ultrapower) &lt;a href=&quot;#HolyLucke:smallModels&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;. A cardinal $\kappa$ is $1$-iterable if every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ for which there is an $M$-ultrafilter $U$ such that $\langle M,\in, U\rangle$ satisfies $\Sigma_0$-separation and the ultrapower is well-founded &lt;a href=&quot;#gitman:welch&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;. A cardinal $\kappa$ is Ramsey if and only if every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ for which there is an $M$-ultrafilter $U$ such that $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$ satisfies $\Sigma_0$-separation and which is (externally) countably complete &lt;a href=&quot;#mitchell:ramsey&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In this article, motivated by the work of Bovykin and McKenzie &lt;a href=&quot;#BovykinMcKenzie:RamseyLikeNFUM&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;, we consider a hierarchy of large cardinal notions characterized by the existence, for weak $\kappa$-models $M$, of $M$-ultrafilters $U$ such that the structure $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$ satisfies fragments up to full ${\rm ZFC}^-$. Following Bovykin and McKenzie, we call such cardinals &lt;em&gt;baby measurable&lt;/em&gt;. We show that increasing levels of replacement and separation for the structures $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$ increases large cardinal strength even if the ultrapowers are ill-founded. For example, adding even $\Sigma_0$-replacement to the characterization of completely ineffable cardinals pushes consistency strength well beyond a Ramsey cardinal. We apply the concepts derived from baby measurable cardinals to Holy's and the second author's game Ramsey cardinals &lt;a href=&quot;#HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;[7]&lt;/a&gt; to obtain strong small large cardinal notions below a measurable cardinal. We show that these new large cardinals are robust under forcing. Finally, we show that these notions are naturally connected to models of Kelley-Morse set theory in which ${\rm Ord}$ is measurable and help us to understand the structure of these second-order models.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;zarach:unions_of_zfminus_models&quot;&gt;A. Zarach, “Unions of ${\rm ZF}^{-}$-models which are themselves
              ${\rm ZF}^{-}$-models,” in &lt;i&gt;Logic Colloquium ’80 (Prague, 1980)&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 108, Amsterdam: North-Holland, 1982, pp. 315–342. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;zfcminus:gitmanhamkinsjohnstone&quot;&gt;V. Gitman, J. D. Hamkins, and T. A. Johnstone, “What is the theory $\mathsf {ZFC}$ without power set?,” &lt;i&gt;MLQ Math. Log. Q.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 62, no. 4-5, pp. 391–406, 2016. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;HolyLucke:smallModels&quot;&gt;P. Holy and P. Lücke, “Small Models, Large Cardinals, and Induced Ideals,” &lt;i&gt;Manuscript&lt;/i&gt;, 2020. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;gitman:welch&quot;&gt;V. Gitman and P. D. Welch, “Ramsey-like cardinals II,” &lt;i&gt;The Journal of Symbolic Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 76, no. 2, pp. 541–560, 2011. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;mitchell:ramsey&quot;&gt;W. Mitchell, “Ramsey cardinals and constructibility,” &lt;i&gt;J. Symbolic Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 44, no. 2, pp. 260–266, 1979. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;BovykinMcKenzie:RamseyLikeNFUM&quot;&gt;A. Bovykin and Z. McKenzie, “Ramsey-like cardinals that characterize the exact consistency strength of NFUM,” &lt;i&gt;Manuscript&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;P. Holy and P. Schlicht, “A hierarchy of Ramsey-like cardinals,” &lt;i&gt;Fund. Math.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 242, no. 1, pp. 49–74, 2018. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">{% reference page.ref %} Measurable cardinals and most stronger large cardinals are defined by the existence of elementary embeddings $j:V\to M$ from the universe $V$ into an inner model $M$ with that cardinal as the critical point. Stronger large cardinal axioms impose additional assumptions on the target model $M$ that allow it to capture more and more sets from $V$. Weakly compact and many other smaller large cardinals are defined via combinatorial properties, often involving existence of large homogeneous sets for colorings. But almost all of them also have elementary embedding characterizations that, like the larger large cardinals, follow prescribed patterns as consistency strength grows. These smaller large cardinals $\kappa$ are characterized by elementary embeddings of models $\langle M,\in\rangle\models{\rm ZFC}^-$ of size $\kappa$, most often transitive, with critical point $\kappa$, and usually, but not always, with well-founded targets. ${\rm ZFC}^-$ is the theory ${\rm ZFC}$ with the powerset axiom removed, the collection scheme in place of the replacement scheme, and the version of the axiom of choice which states that every set can be well-ordered.(Without the powerset axiom, collection and replacement schemes are not equivalent and neither are the various forms of the axiom of choice. See {% cite zarach:unions_of_zfminus_models %} and {% cite zfcminus:gitmanhamkinsjohnstone %}.) In many cases, the existence of these embeddings can be equivalently expressed in terms of the existence of certain ultrafilters on the subsets of $\kappa$ contained in $M$. Suppose $\langle M,\in\rangle \models{\rm ZFC}^-$ is a transitive model of size $\kappa$ with $\kappa\in M$ (we will give precise definitions and drop the transitivity requirement in the next section). We call such structures weak $\kappa$-models. We will call a filter $U$, on the subsets of $\kappa$ of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$, an $M$-ultrafilter if the structure $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$, together with a predicate for $U$, satisfies that $U$ is a uniform, normal ultrafilter on $\kappa$. What this says is that $U$ is an ultrafilter on the subsets of $\kappa$ that live in $M$ and if a $\kappa$-length sequence of elements of $U$ is an element of $M$, then its diagonal intersection is in $U$. The Łoś-Theorem holds for ultrapowers by an $M$-ultrafilter, but the ultrapower need not be well-founded. Note that the filter $U$ may not be countably complete for sequences outside of $M$. The $M$-ultrafilter $U$, is in most interesting cases, external to $M$ and even though $\langle M,\in\rangle\models{\rm ZFC}^-$, separation and replacement can fail completely in the structure $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$ once we let $M$ know about $U$. In the same way that making the inner model $M$ closer to $V$ in the characterizations of larger large cardinals increases strength, for the smaller large cardinals, we increase strength by making $M$ be more compatible with $U$, which amounts to $M$ being more correct about the properties of $U$ or to having more of the ${\rm ZFC}^-$ axioms in the structure $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$. Let's look at some examples. A cardinal $\kappa$ is weakly compact if and only if it is inaccessible and every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ for which there is a (externally) countably complete $M$-ultrafilter $U$ (in particular the ultrapower is well-founded). A cardinal $\kappa$ is completely ineffable if and only if every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ for which there is an $M$-ultrafilter $U$ such that $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$ satisfies $\Sigma_0$-separation (but with a potentially ill-founded ultrapower) {% cite HolyLucke:smallModels %}. A cardinal $\kappa$ is $1$-iterable if every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ for which there is an $M$-ultrafilter $U$ such that $\langle M,\in, U\rangle$ satisfies $\Sigma_0$-separation and the ultrapower is well-founded {% cite gitman:welch %}. A cardinal $\kappa$ is Ramsey if and only if every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ for which there is an $M$-ultrafilter $U$ such that $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$ satisfies $\Sigma_0$-separation and which is (externally) countably complete {% cite mitchell:ramsey %}. In this article, motivated by the work of Bovykin and McKenzie {% cite BovykinMcKenzie:RamseyLikeNFUM %}, we consider a hierarchy of large cardinal notions characterized by the existence, for weak $\kappa$-models $M$, of $M$-ultrafilters $U$ such that the structure $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$ satisfies fragments up to full ${\rm ZFC}^-$. Following Bovykin and McKenzie, we call such cardinals baby measurable. We show that increasing levels of replacement and separation for the structures $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$ increases large cardinal strength even if the ultrapowers are ill-founded. For example, adding even $\Sigma_0$-replacement to the characterization of completely ineffable cardinals pushes consistency strength well beyond a Ramsey cardinal. We apply the concepts derived from baby measurable cardinals to Holy's and the second author's game Ramsey cardinals {% cite HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals %} to obtain strong small large cardinal notions below a measurable cardinal. We show that these new large cardinals are robust under forcing. Finally, we show that these notions are naturally connected to models of Kelley-Morse set theory in which ${\rm Ord}$ is measurable and help us to understand the structure of these second-order models. References {% bibliography --cited %}</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The many universes of modern set theory</title><link href="/talks/2021/06/25/the-many-universes-of-modern-set-theory.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The many universes of modern set theory" /><published>2021-06-25T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2021-06-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>/talks/2021/06/25/the-many-universes-of-modern-set-theory</id><content type="html" xml:base="/talks/2021/06/25/the-many-universes-of-modern-set-theory.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the Mathematics Colloquium, University of
Warwick, June 25, 2021 (virtual).&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/ModernSetTheoryWarwick.pdf&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
All mathematical objects can be reduced down to sets and properties of sets underlie their fundamental behavior. A universe of set theory is a mathematical structure consisting of sets together with a membership relation telling us when a set is an element of another set. We think of  mathematics as taking place within some such set-theoretic universe. Mathematicians of the early 20th century had over-optimistically hoped that a cleverly chosen collection of axioms would determine the unique set-theoretic universe to serve as the foundation of mathematics. This naive foundational view was crushed by Gödel's incompleteness theorems. In the decades that followed set theorists worked to construct a myriad of extremely different universes of set theory all satisfying the Zermelo-Fraenkel axioms (with the Axiom of Choice) ZF(C). Godel discovered the constructible universe $L$, a minimal universe sitting inside any other universe. Cohen developed the technique of forcing for expanding a given universe of set theory to a larger universe - called a forcing extension- satisfying some desired property such as the failure of the continuum hypothesis. Set theorists began strengthening ZFC by adding large cardinal axioms asserting the existence of large infinite objects beyond those provable in ZF(C). Remarkably the existence of these extreme infinities was shown to affect the properties 'small' mathematical objects such as the reals. Interestingly, large cardinals are also intimately connected with the existence of elementary embeddings of a universe of set theory into a sub-universe of itself. Set theory, having been around for a little longer than a century, is a relatively young field.  In this talk, I will try to give an overview of its history proceeding into the modern times.  If I have time, I will mention some very recent research connecting large cardinals with forcing, where we introduce fruitful axioms asserting that elementary embeddings following from a given large cardinal exist in a forcing extension, but not necessarily in the universe itself.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the Mathematics Colloquium, University of Warwick, June 25, 2021 (virtual).Slides</summary></entry></feed>