<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-05-12T19:45:28-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Victoria Gitman</title><subtitle>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Virtual large cardinal principles at KGRC</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/talks/2018/03/21/virtual-large-cardinals-at-kgrc.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Virtual large cardinal principles at KGRC" /><published>2018-03-21T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-03-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/talks/2018/03/21/virtual-large-cardinals-at-kgrc</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/talks/2018/03/21/virtual-large-cardinals-at-kgrc.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the &lt;a \href=&quot;http://www.logic.univie.ac.at/Home.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Kurt Gödel Research Center&lt;/a&gt; Research Seminar in Vienna, Austria, April 14, 2018.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Josephinum.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:left; padding: 10px;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: Given a set-theoretic property $\mathcal P$ characterized by the existence of elementary embeddings between some first-order structures, we say that $\mathcal P$ holds &lt;em&gt;virtually&lt;/em&gt; if the embeddings between structures from $V$ characterizing $\mathcal P$ exist somewhere in the generic multiverse. We showed with Schindler that virtual versions of supercompact, $C^{(n)}$-extendible, $n$-huge and rank-into-rank cardinals form a large cardinal hierarchy consistent with $V=L$. Sitting atop the hierarchy are virtual versions of inconsistent large cardinal principles such as the existence of an elementary embedding $j:V_\lambda\to V_\lambda$ for $\lambda$ much larger than the supremum of the critical sequence. The Silver indiscernibles, under $0^\sharp$, which have a number of large cardinal properties in $L$, are also natural examples of virtual large cardinals. With Bagaria, Hamkins and Schindler, we investigated  properties of the virtual version of Vopěnka's Principle, which is consistent with $V=L$, and established some surprising differences from Vopenka's Principle, stemming from the failure of Kunen's Inconsistency in the virtual setting. A recent new direction in the study of virtual large cardinal principles involves asking that the required embeddings exist in forcing extensions preserving a large segment of the cardinals. In the talk, I will discuss a mixture of results about the virtual large cardinal hierarchy and virtual Vopěnka's  Principle. Time permitting, I will give an overview of Woodin's new results on virtual large cardinals in cardinal preserving extensions. 

&lt;div class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/vienna.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the Kurt Gödel Research Center Research Seminar in Vienna, Austria, April 14, 2018.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A model of second-order arithmetic satisfying AC but not DC</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publications/2018/03/21/a-model-of-second-order-arithmetic-satisfying-AC-but-not-DC.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A model of second-order arithmetic satisfying AC but not DC" /><published>2018-03-21T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-03-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publications/2018/03/21/a-model-of-second-order-arithmetic-satisfying-AC-but-not-DC</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publications/2018/03/21/a-model-of-second-order-arithmetic-satisfying-AC-but-not-DC.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;FriedmanGitman:ModelOfACNotDC&quot;&gt;S.-D. Friedman and V. Gitman, “A model of second-order arithmetic satisfying AC but not DC,” &lt;i&gt;manuscript under review&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Models of arithmetic are two-sorted structures, having two types of objects, which we think of as numbers and sets of numbers. Their properties are formalized using a two-sorted logic with separate variables and quantifiers for numbers and sets. By convention, we will denote number variables by lower-case letters and sets variables by upper-case letters. The language of second-order arithmetic is the language of first-order arithmetic $\mathcal L_A=\{+,\cdot,&lt;,0,1\}$ together with a membership relation $\in$ between numbers and sets. A multitude of second-order arithmetic theories, as well as the relationships between them, have been extensively studied (see &lt;a href=&quot;#simpson:second-orderArithmetic&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of a weak second-order arithmetic theory is ${\rm ACA_0}$, whose axioms consist of the modified Peano axioms, where instead of the induction scheme we have the single second-order induction axiom $$\forall X [(0\in X\wedge \forall n(n\in X\rightarrow n+1\in X))\rightarrow \forall n (n\in X)],$$ and the &lt;em&gt;comprehension scheme&lt;/em&gt; for first-order formulas. The latter is a scheme of assertions stating for every first-order formula, possibly with class parameters, that there is a set whose elements are exactly the numbers satisfying the formula. One of the strongest second-order arithmetic theories is ${\rm Z}_2$, often referred to as &lt;em&gt;full second-order arithmetic&lt;/em&gt;, which strengthens comprehension for first-order formulas in ${\rm ACA}_0$ to full comprehension for all second-order assertions. This means that for a formula with any number of second-order quantifiers, there is a set whose elements are exactly the numbers satisfying the formula. The reals of any model of ${\rm ZF}$ is a model of ${\rm Z}_2$. We can further strengthen the theory ${\rm Z}_2$ by adding choice principles for sets: the choice scheme and the dependent choice scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;choice scheme&lt;/em&gt; is a scheme of assertions, which states for every second-order formula $\varphi(n,X,A)$ with a set parameter $A$ that if for every number $n$, there is a set $X$ witnessing $\varphi(n,X,A)$, then there is a single set $Y$ collecting witnesses for every $n$, in the sense that $\varphi(n,Y_n,A)$ holds, where $Y_n=\{m\mid \langle n,m\rangle\in Y\}$ and $\langle n,m\rangle$ is any standard coding of pairs. More precisely, an instance of the choice scheme for the formula $\varphi(n,X,A)$ is $$\forall n\exists X\varphi(n,X,A)\rightarrow \exists Y\forall n\varphi(n,Y_n,A).$$ We will denote by $\Sigma^1_n$-${\rm AC}$ the fragment of the choice scheme for $\Sigma^1_n$-assertions, making an analogous definition for $\Pi^1_n$, and we will denote the full choice scheme by $\Sigma^1_\infty$-${\rm AC}$. The reals of any model of ${\rm ZF}+{\rm AC}_\omega$ (countable choice) satisfy ${\rm Z}_2+\Sigma^1_\infty$-${\rm AC}$. It is a folklore result, going back possibly to Mostowski, that the theory ${\rm Z}_2+\Sigma^1_\infty$-${\rm AC}$ is bi-interpretable with the theory ${\rm ZFC}^-$ (${\rm ZFC}$ without the powerset axiom, with Collection instead of Replacement) together with the statement that every set is countable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;dependent choice scheme&lt;/em&gt; is a scheme of assertions, which states for every second-order formula $\varphi(X,Y,A)$ with set parameter $A$ that if for every set $X$, there is a set $Y$ witnessing $\varphi(X,Y,A)$, then there is a single set $Z$ making infinitely many dependent choices according to $\varphi$. More precisely, an instance of the dependent choice scheme for the formula $\varphi(X,Y,A)$ is $$\forall X\exists Y\varphi(X,Y,A)\rightarrow \exists Z\forall n\varphi(Z_n,Z_{n+1},A).$$ We will denote by $\Sigma^1_n$-${\rm DC}$ the dependent choice scheme for $\Sigma^1_n$-assertions, with an analogous definition for $\Pi^1_n$, and we will denote the full dependent choice scheme by $\Sigma^1_\infty$-${\rm DC}$. The reals of a model of ${\rm ZF}+{\rm DC}$ (dependent choice) satisfy ${\rm Z}_2+\Sigma^1_\infty$-${\rm DC}$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not difficult to see that the theory ${\rm Z}_2$ implies $\Sigma^1_2$-${\rm AC}$, the choice scheme for $\Sigma^1_2$-assertions. Models of ${\rm Z}_2$ can build their own version of Gödel's constructible universe $L$. If a model of ${\rm Z}_2$ believes that a set $\Gamma$ is a well-order, then it has a set coding a set-theoretic structure constructed like $L$ along the well-order $\Gamma$.  It turns out that models of ${\rm Z}_2$ satisfy a version of Shoenfield's absoluteness with respect to their constructible universes. For every $\Sigma^1_2$-assertion $\varphi$, a model of ${\rm Z}_2$ satisfies $\varphi$ if and only its constructible universe satisfies $\varphi$ with set quantifiers naturally interpreted as ranging over the reals. All of the above generalizes to constructible universes $L[A]$ relativized to a set parameter $A$. Thus, given a $\Sigma^1_2$-assertion $\varphi(n,X,A)$ for which the model satisfies $\forall n\exists X\varphi(n,X,A)$, the model can go to its constructible universe $L[A]$ to pick the least witness $X$ for $\varphi(n,X,A)$ for every $n$, because $L[A]$ agrees when $\varphi$ is satisfied, and then put the witnesses together into a single set using comprehension. So long as the unique witnessing set can be obtained for each $n$, comprehension suffices to obtain a single set of witnesses. How much more of the choice scheme follows from ${\rm Z}_2$? The reals of the classical Feferman-Lévy model of ${\rm ZF}$ (see &lt;a href=&quot;#levy:choicescheme&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;, Theorem 8), in which $\aleph_1$ is a countable union of countable sets, is a $\beta$-model of ${\rm Z}_2$ in which $\Pi^1_2$-${\rm AC}$ fails. This is a particulary strong failure of the choice scheme because, as we explain below, $\beta$-models are meant to strongly resemble the full standard model $P(\omega)$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two ways in which a model of second-order arithmetic can resemble the full standard model $P(\omega)$. A model of second-order arithmetic is called an $\omega$-&lt;em&gt;model&lt;/em&gt; if its first-order part is $\omega$, and it follows that its second-order part is some subset of $P(\omega)$. But even an $\omega$-model can poorly resemble $P(\omega)$ because it may be wrong about well-foundedness by missing $\omega$-sequences. An $\omega$-model of second-order arithmetic which is correct about well-foundedness is called a $\beta$-&lt;em&gt;model&lt;/em&gt;. The reals of any transitive ${\rm ZF}$-model is a $\beta$-model of ${\rm Z}_2$. One advantage to having a $\beta$-model of ${\rm Z}_2$ is that the constructible universe it builds internally is isomorphic to an initial segment $L_\alpha$ of the actual constructible universe $L$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theory ${\rm Z}_2$ also implies $\Sigma^1_2$-${\rm DC}$ (see &lt;a href=&quot;#simpson:second-orderArithmetic&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, Theorem VII.9.2), the dependent choice scheme for $\Sigma^1_2$-assertions.  In this article, we construct a symmetric submodel of a forcing extension of $L$ whose reals form a model of second-order arithmetic in which ${\rm Z}_2$ together with $\Sigma^1_\infty$-${\rm AC}$ holds, but $\Pi^1_2$-${\rm DC}$ fails. The forcing notion we use is a tree iteration of a forcing for adding a real due to Jensen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jensen's forcing, which we will call here $\mathbb P^J$, introduced by Jensen in &lt;a href=&quot;#jensen:real&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;, is a subposet of Sacks forcing constructed in $L$ using the $\diamondsuit$ principle. The poset $\mathbb P^J$ has the ccc and adds a unique generic real over $L$. The collection of all $L$-generic reals for $\mathbb P^J$ in any model is $\Pi^1_2$-definable. Jensen used his forcing to show that it is consistent with ${\rm ZFC}$ that there is a $\Sigma^1_3$-definable non-constructible real &lt;a href=&quot;#jensen:real&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;. Recently Lyubetsky and Kanovei extended the &quot;uniqueness of generic filters&quot; property of Jensen's forcing to finite-support products of $\mathbb P^J$ &lt;a href=&quot;#kanovei:productOfJensenReals&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;. They showed that in a forcing extension $L[G]$ by the $\omega$-length finite support-product of $\mathbb P^J$, the only $L$-generic reals for $\mathbb P^J$ are the slices of the generic filter $G$. The result easily extends to $\omega_1$-length finite support-products as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We in turn extend the ``uniqueness of generic filters&quot; property to tree iterations of Jensen's forcing. We first define finite iterations $\mathbb P^J_n$ of Jensen's forcing $\mathbb P^J$, and then define an iteration of $\mathbb P^J$ along a tree $\mathcal T$ to be a forcing whose conditions are functions from a finite subtree of $\mathcal T$ into $\bigcup_{n&lt;\omega}\mathbb P_n^J$ such that nodes on level $n$ get mapped to elements of the $n$-length iteration $\mathbb P_n^J$ and conditions on higher nodes extend conditions on lower nodes. The functions are ordered by extension of domain and strengthening on each coordinate. We show that in a forcing extension $L[G]$ by the tree iteration of $\mathbb P^J$ along the tree ${}^{\lt\omega}\omega_1$ (or the tree ${}^{\lt\omega}\omega$) the only $L$-generic filters for $\mathbb P_n^J$ are the restrictions of $G$ to level $n$ nodes of tree. We proceed to construct a symmetric submodel of $L[G]$ which has the tree of $\mathbb P_n^J$-generic filters added by $G$ but no branch through it. The symmetric model we construct satisfies ${\rm AC}_\omega$ and the tree of $\mathbb P_n^J$-generic filters is $\Pi^1_2$-definable in it. The reals of this model thus provide the desired $\beta$-model of ${\rm Z}_2$ in which $\Sigma^1_\infty$-${\rm AC}$ holds, but $\Pi^1_2$-${\rm DC}$ fails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our results also answer a long-standing open question of Zarach from &lt;a href=&quot;#Zarach1996:ReplacmentDoesNotImplyCollection&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt; about whether the Reflection Principle holds in models of ${\rm ZFC}^-$. The &lt;em&gt;Reflection Principle&lt;/em&gt; states that every formula can be reflected to a transitive set, and holds in ${\rm ZFC}$ by the Lévy-Montague reflection because every formula is reflected by some $V_\alpha$. In the absence of the von Neumann hierarchy, it is not clear how to realize reflection, and indeed we show that it fails in $H_{\omega_1}\models{\rm ZFC}^-$ of the symmetric model we construct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;simpson:second-orderArithmetic&quot;&gt;S. G. Simpson, &lt;i&gt;Subsystems of second order arithmetic&lt;/i&gt;, Second. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge; Association for
              Symbolic Logic, Poughkeepsie, NY, 2009, p. xvi+444. Available at: http://dx.doi.org/10.1017/CBO9780511581007&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;levy:choicescheme&quot;&gt;A. Lévy, “Definability in axiomatic set theory. II,” in &lt;i&gt;Mathematical Logic and Foundations of Set Theory
              (Proc. Internat. Colloq., Jerusalem, 1968)&lt;/i&gt;, North-Holland, Amsterdam, 1970, pp. 129–145. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;jensen:real&quot;&gt;R. Jensen, “Definable sets of minimal degree,” in &lt;i&gt;Mathematical logic and foundations of set theory (Proc.
              Internat. Colloq., Jerusalem, 1968)&lt;/i&gt;, North-Holland, Amsterdam, 1970, pp. 122–128. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;kanovei:productOfJensenReals&quot;&gt;V. Kanovei and V. Lyubetsky, “A countable definable set of reals containing no definable elements.” &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Zarach1996:ReplacmentDoesNotImplyCollection&quot;&gt;A. M. Zarach, “Replacement $\nrightarrow$ collection,” in &lt;i&gt;Gödel ’96 (Brno, 1996)&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 6, Berlin: Springer, 1996, pp. 307–322. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">{% reference page.ref %} Models of arithmetic are two-sorted structures, having two types of objects, which we think of as numbers and sets of numbers. Their properties are formalized using a two-sorted logic with separate variables and quantifiers for numbers and sets. By convention, we will denote number variables by lower-case letters and sets variables by upper-case letters. The language of second-order arithmetic is the language of first-order arithmetic $\mathcal L_A=\{+,\cdot, An example of a weak second-order arithmetic theory is ${\rm ACA_0}$, whose axioms consist of the modified Peano axioms, where instead of the induction scheme we have the single second-order induction axiom $$\forall X [(0\in X\wedge \forall n(n\in X\rightarrow n+1\in X))\rightarrow \forall n (n\in X)],$$ and the comprehension scheme for first-order formulas. The latter is a scheme of assertions stating for every first-order formula, possibly with class parameters, that there is a set whose elements are exactly the numbers satisfying the formula. One of the strongest second-order arithmetic theories is ${\rm Z}_2$, often referred to as full second-order arithmetic, which strengthens comprehension for first-order formulas in ${\rm ACA}_0$ to full comprehension for all second-order assertions. This means that for a formula with any number of second-order quantifiers, there is a set whose elements are exactly the numbers satisfying the formula. The reals of any model of ${\rm ZF}$ is a model of ${\rm Z}_2$. We can further strengthen the theory ${\rm Z}_2$ by adding choice principles for sets: the choice scheme and the dependent choice scheme. The choice scheme is a scheme of assertions, which states for every second-order formula $\varphi(n,X,A)$ with a set parameter $A$ that if for every number $n$, there is a set $X$ witnessing $\varphi(n,X,A)$, then there is a single set $Y$ collecting witnesses for every $n$, in the sense that $\varphi(n,Y_n,A)$ holds, where $Y_n=\{m\mid \langle n,m\rangle\in Y\}$ and $\langle n,m\rangle$ is any standard coding of pairs. More precisely, an instance of the choice scheme for the formula $\varphi(n,X,A)$ is $$\forall n\exists X\varphi(n,X,A)\rightarrow \exists Y\forall n\varphi(n,Y_n,A).$$ We will denote by $\Sigma^1_n$-${\rm AC}$ the fragment of the choice scheme for $\Sigma^1_n$-assertions, making an analogous definition for $\Pi^1_n$, and we will denote the full choice scheme by $\Sigma^1_\infty$-${\rm AC}$. The reals of any model of ${\rm ZF}+{\rm AC}_\omega$ (countable choice) satisfy ${\rm Z}_2+\Sigma^1_\infty$-${\rm AC}$. It is a folklore result, going back possibly to Mostowski, that the theory ${\rm Z}_2+\Sigma^1_\infty$-${\rm AC}$ is bi-interpretable with the theory ${\rm ZFC}^-$ (${\rm ZFC}$ without the powerset axiom, with Collection instead of Replacement) together with the statement that every set is countable. The dependent choice scheme is a scheme of assertions, which states for every second-order formula $\varphi(X,Y,A)$ with set parameter $A$ that if for every set $X$, there is a set $Y$ witnessing $\varphi(X,Y,A)$, then there is a single set $Z$ making infinitely many dependent choices according to $\varphi$. More precisely, an instance of the dependent choice scheme for the formula $\varphi(X,Y,A)$ is $$\forall X\exists Y\varphi(X,Y,A)\rightarrow \exists Z\forall n\varphi(Z_n,Z_{n+1},A).$$ We will denote by $\Sigma^1_n$-${\rm DC}$ the dependent choice scheme for $\Sigma^1_n$-assertions, with an analogous definition for $\Pi^1_n$, and we will denote the full dependent choice scheme by $\Sigma^1_\infty$-${\rm DC}$. The reals of a model of ${\rm ZF}+{\rm DC}$ (dependent choice) satisfy ${\rm Z}_2+\Sigma^1_\infty$-${\rm DC}$. It is not difficult to see that the theory ${\rm Z}_2$ implies $\Sigma^1_2$-${\rm AC}$, the choice scheme for $\Sigma^1_2$-assertions. Models of ${\rm Z}_2$ can build their own version of Gödel's constructible universe $L$. If a model of ${\rm Z}_2$ believes that a set $\Gamma$ is a well-order, then it has a set coding a set-theoretic structure constructed like $L$ along the well-order $\Gamma$. It turns out that models of ${\rm Z}_2$ satisfy a version of Shoenfield's absoluteness with respect to their constructible universes. For every $\Sigma^1_2$-assertion $\varphi$, a model of ${\rm Z}_2$ satisfies $\varphi$ if and only its constructible universe satisfies $\varphi$ with set quantifiers naturally interpreted as ranging over the reals. All of the above generalizes to constructible universes $L[A]$ relativized to a set parameter $A$. Thus, given a $\Sigma^1_2$-assertion $\varphi(n,X,A)$ for which the model satisfies $\forall n\exists X\varphi(n,X,A)$, the model can go to its constructible universe $L[A]$ to pick the least witness $X$ for $\varphi(n,X,A)$ for every $n$, because $L[A]$ agrees when $\varphi$ is satisfied, and then put the witnesses together into a single set using comprehension. So long as the unique witnessing set can be obtained for each $n$, comprehension suffices to obtain a single set of witnesses. How much more of the choice scheme follows from ${\rm Z}_2$? The reals of the classical Feferman-Lévy model of ${\rm ZF}$ (see {% cite levy:choicescheme %}, Theorem 8), in which $\aleph_1$ is a countable union of countable sets, is a $\beta$-model of ${\rm Z}_2$ in which $\Pi^1_2$-${\rm AC}$ fails. This is a particulary strong failure of the choice scheme because, as we explain below, $\beta$-models are meant to strongly resemble the full standard model $P(\omega)$. There are two ways in which a model of second-order arithmetic can resemble the full standard model $P(\omega)$. A model of second-order arithmetic is called an $\omega$-model if its first-order part is $\omega$, and it follows that its second-order part is some subset of $P(\omega)$. But even an $\omega$-model can poorly resemble $P(\omega)$ because it may be wrong about well-foundedness by missing $\omega$-sequences. An $\omega$-model of second-order arithmetic which is correct about well-foundedness is called a $\beta$-model. The reals of any transitive ${\rm ZF}$-model is a $\beta$-model of ${\rm Z}_2$. One advantage to having a $\beta$-model of ${\rm Z}_2$ is that the constructible universe it builds internally is isomorphic to an initial segment $L_\alpha$ of the actual constructible universe $L$. The theory ${\rm Z}_2$ also implies $\Sigma^1_2$-${\rm DC}$ (see {% cite simpson:second-orderArithmetic%}, Theorem VII.9.2), the dependent choice scheme for $\Sigma^1_2$-assertions. In this article, we construct a symmetric submodel of a forcing extension of $L$ whose reals form a model of second-order arithmetic in which ${\rm Z}_2$ together with $\Sigma^1_\infty$-${\rm AC}$ holds, but $\Pi^1_2$-${\rm DC}$ fails. The forcing notion we use is a tree iteration of a forcing for adding a real due to Jensen. Jensen's forcing, which we will call here $\mathbb P^J$, introduced by Jensen in {% cite jensen:real %}, is a subposet of Sacks forcing constructed in $L$ using the $\diamondsuit$ principle. The poset $\mathbb P^J$ has the ccc and adds a unique generic real over $L$. The collection of all $L$-generic reals for $\mathbb P^J$ in any model is $\Pi^1_2$-definable. Jensen used his forcing to show that it is consistent with ${\rm ZFC}$ that there is a $\Sigma^1_3$-definable non-constructible real {% cite jensen:real%}. Recently Lyubetsky and Kanovei extended the &quot;uniqueness of generic filters&quot; property of Jensen's forcing to finite-support products of $\mathbb P^J$ {% cite kanovei:productOfJensenReals %}. They showed that in a forcing extension $L[G]$ by the $\omega$-length finite support-product of $\mathbb P^J$, the only $L$-generic reals for $\mathbb P^J$ are the slices of the generic filter $G$. The result easily extends to $\omega_1$-length finite support-products as well. We in turn extend the ``uniqueness of generic filters&quot; property to tree iterations of Jensen's forcing. We first define finite iterations $\mathbb P^J_n$ of Jensen's forcing $\mathbb P^J$, and then define an iteration of $\mathbb P^J$ along a tree $\mathcal T$ to be a forcing whose conditions are functions from a finite subtree of $\mathcal T$ into $\bigcup_{n Our results also answer a long-standing open question of Zarach from {% cite Zarach1996:ReplacmentDoesNotImplyCollection %} about whether the Reflection Principle holds in models of ${\rm ZFC}^-$. The Reflection Principle states that every formula can be reflected to a transitive set, and holds in ${\rm ZFC}$ by the Lévy-Montague reflection because every formula is reflected by some $V_\alpha$. In the absence of the von Neumann hierarchy, it is not clear how to realize reflection, and indeed we show that it fails in $H_{\omega_1}\models{\rm ZFC}^-$ of the symmetric model we construct. References {% bibliography --cited %}</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The emerging zoo of second-order set theories</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/talks/2018/01/03/the-emerging-zoo-of-second-order-set-theories.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The emerging zoo of second-order set theories" /><published>2018-01-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/talks/2018/01/03/the-emerging-zoo-of-second-order-set-theories</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/talks/2018/01/03/the-emerging-zoo-of-second-order-set-theories.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the Young Researchers' Workshop: Forcing and Philosophy, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uni-konstanz.de/en/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;University of Konstanz&lt;/a&gt;, January 18, 2018.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/konstanz.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:left; padding: 10px;&quot; /&gt;
In set theory, classes are collections of sets which are ``too large&quot; to be sets themselves. More formally, a &lt;em&gt;class&lt;/em&gt;, in a model of first-order set theory, is a definable (with parameters) collection of sets. Classes play an important role in modern set theory. Class forcing can make global changes to a universe of set theory, such as making the ${\rm GCH}$ fail at all regular cardinals. Large cardinals imply the existence of class elementary embeddings $j:V\to M$ from the universe into a transitive class submodel. Inner model theory studies canonical &lt;em&gt;inner models&lt;/em&gt; (transitive class submodels containing all the ordinals).

&lt;p&gt;The restriction to the study of only the definable large collections of sets is a limitation of first-order set theory which prevents us from exploring some natural properties of set-theoretic universes. For instance, consider the long standing open question whether Reinhardt cardinals are consistent with ${\rm ZF}$, which has been revisited only a few days ago in &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1712.09678&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;em&gt;Reinhardt cardinal&lt;/em&gt; is the critical point of an elementary embedding $j:V\to V$. It is not difficult to show that there cannot be a definable elementary $j:V\to V$ in a model of ${\rm ZF}$, so the open question is about the existence of an undefinable such embedding. Other recent examples of the use of general classes comes from the study of inner model reflection principles. Motivated by a question of Neil Barton, Barton, Caicedo, Fuchs, Hamkins, and Reitz recently introduced and studied the &lt;em&gt;Inner Model Reflection Principle&lt;/em&gt; stating that every first-order formula reflects to a proper inner model &lt;a href=&quot;#BartonCaicedoFuchsHamkinsReitz:Inner-model-reflection-principles&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. The statement of the principle cannot be expressed in first-order set theory because it requires quantifying over classes. Along similar lines, Friedman had previously introduced the &lt;em&gt;Inner Model Hypothesis&lt;/em&gt; which states that if a first-order sentence holds in an outer model (extension universe) of an inner model, then it already holds in some inner model &lt;a href=&quot;#Friedman2006:InternalConsistencyAndIMH&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. For a long time it was not clear in what framework this principle could be formalized because it requires not only quantifying over classes but also referring to classes that are potentially outside the universe itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do we undertake a general study of classes? What is the framework in which we can have undefinable classes and where we can study the properties of classes in the same way we study sets? This framework is second-order set theory, formalized in a two-sorted logic with separate objects and quantifiers for sets and classes. Models of second-order set theory are triples $\mathscr V=\langle V,\in,\mathcal C\rangle$ where $\mathcal C$ is the collection of classes of $\mathscr V$. One of the weakest reasonable axiomatizations of second-order theory is the Gödel-Bernays set theory ${\rm GBC}$ whose axioms consist of the ${\rm ZFC}$ axioms for sets, extensionality, replacement, and existence of global well-order axioms for classes, together with a weak comprehension scheme stating that every first-order formula defines a class. If a universe of set theory has a definable global well-order, then it together with its definable classes is a model of ${\rm GBC}$. Indeed, ${\rm GBC}$ is equiconsistent with ${\rm ZFC}$ and has the same first-order consequences as ${\rm ZFC}$. If we just add to ${\rm GBC}$ comprehension for $\Sigma^1_1$-formulas (formulas with a single class existential quantifier), we get a much stronger theory with many desirable properties. The theory ${\rm GBC}$ + $\Sigma^1_1$-Comprehension implies that that any two &lt;em&gt;meta-ordinals&lt;/em&gt; (class well-orders) are comparable, that we can iterate the $L$ construction along any meta-ordinal, that there is an iterated truth predicate along any meta-ordinal, that determinacy holds for open class games, and that the class forcing theorem holds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;truth predicate&lt;/em&gt; is a class of Gödel codes of first-order formulas obeying Tarskian truth conditions. Tarski's Theorem on the undefinablity of truth implies that a truth predicate cannot be definable and therefore ${\rm GBC}$, because it can have models with only the definable classes, cannot imply the existence of such a class. Indeed, the existence of a truth predicate class implies $\text{Con}({\rm ZFC})$, $\text{Con}(\text{Con}({\rm ZFC}))$ and much more. ${\rm GBC}$ + $\Sigma^1_1$-Comprehension implies that there is a truth predicate for every structure $\langle V,\in, A\rangle$ for a class $A$. In particular, if $T_0$ is the truth predicate (for $\langle V,\in,A\rangle$), then we have a truth predicate $T_1$ for the structure $\langle V,\in, T_0,A\rangle$, that is we have truth for truth. How far can we iterate the truth operation? ${\rm GBC}$ + $\Sigma^1_1$-Comprehension implies that we get an iterated truth predicate along any meta-ordinal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By analogy with games on $X^\omega$, for a set $X$, where the players take turns playing elements from $X$ for $\omega$-many steps, in the second-order context we can consider games on ${\rm ORD}^\omega$. It turns out ${\rm GBC}$ + $\Sigma^1_1$-Comprehension implies determinacy for all such open class games &lt;a href=&quot;#GitmanHamkins:OpenDeterminacyForClassGames&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strength of the forcing construction comes from the &lt;em&gt;Forcing Theorem&lt;/em&gt; which states that the forcing relation (for a fixed first-order formula) is definable. The analogue of the Forcing Theorem for class partial orders says that the forcing relation (for a fixed first-order formula) is a class. The &lt;em&gt;Class Forcing Theorem&lt;/em&gt; can fail in a model of ${\rm GBC}$ because there are class forcing notions from whose forcing relation for atomic formulas we can define a truth predicate. But ${\rm GBC}$ + $\Sigma^1_1$-Comprehension implies the Class Forcing Theorem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, in ${\rm GBC}$ + $\Sigma^1_1$-Comprehension, we can even formalize Friedman's Inner Model Hypothesis because the properties of outer models can be expressed via a strong logic, called $V$-logic, whose proof system is expressible in this theory &lt;a href=&quot;#AntosBartonFriedman:VLogic&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, it turns out that most of these principles are implied by a weaker natural theory ${\rm GBC}$ + ${\rm ETR}$ elementary transfinite recursion. The principle ${\rm ETR}$, which is an analogue of the Recursion Theorem in first-order set theory, states that every first-order definable recursion along a meta-ordinal has a solution. The principle ${\rm ETR}$ implies over ${\rm GBC}$ that we can iterate the $L$ construction along any meta-ordinal. Over ${\rm GBC}$, the principle ${\rm ETR}$ is equivalent to determinacy for clopen class games and to the existence of an iterated truth predicate along any meta-ordinal &lt;a href=&quot;#GitmanHamkins:OpenDeterminacyForClassGames&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;. The Class Forcing Theorem is equivalent over ${\rm GBC}$, to the principle $\rm {ETR}_{\rm {ORD}}$, stating that we can perform recursions along ${\rm ORD}$ &lt;a href=&quot;#GitmanHamkinsHolySchlichtWilliams:ForcingTheorem&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;. The amount of available ${\rm ETR}$ gives a natural hierarchy of second-order set theories above ${\rm GBC}$ with ${\rm ETR}_\omega$ already implying the existence of a truth predicate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only principle we have considered so far which is known to be stronger than ${\rm ETR}$ is open determinacy, a result due to Sato &lt;a href=&quot;#Sato:determinacy&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;. Hamkins and Woodin showed recently that open determinacy implies that forcing does not add meta-ordinals, a natural analogue to the statement that forcing does not add ordinals (personal communication).

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the amount of available comprehension itself gives a hierarchy of second-order set theories culminating with the Kelley-Morse set theory ${\rm KM}$, which consists of ${\rm GBC}$ together with the full comprehension scheme for all second-order formulas. Beyond ${\rm KM}$ are theories which include choice principles for classes, such as the &lt;em&gt;choice scheme&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;dependent choice scheme&lt;/em&gt;. These theories have the advantage of bi-interpretability with extensions of the well-understood first-order set theory ${\rm ZFC}^-_I$ (${\rm ZFC}$ without powerset and with the existence of the largest cardinal which is inaccessible). An even stronger principle, which endows classes with more set-like properties, is the existence of a canonically definable well-order of the classes. The existence of a definable well-ordering on classes makes it possible, for instance, to carry out the Boolean valued model forcing construction for class forcing notions (work in progress with Carolin Antos and Sy-David Friedman).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are there natural second-order set-theoretic principles between ${\rm GBC}$ + $\Sigma^1_1$-comprehension and ${\rm KM}?$ What natural principles lie beyond ${\rm KM}$ together with the choice scheme and the dependent choice scheme? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;BartonCaicedoFuchsHamkinsReitz:Inner-model-reflection-principles&quot;&gt;N. Barton, A. E. Caicedo, G. Fuchs, J. D. Hamkins, and J. Reitz, “Inner-model reflection principles,” &lt;i&gt;ArXiv e-prints&lt;/i&gt;, 2017. Available at: http://jdh.hamkins.org/inner-model-reflection-principles&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Friedman2006:InternalConsistencyAndIMH&quot;&gt;S.-D. Friedman, “Internal consistency and the inner model hypothesis,” &lt;i&gt;Bull. Symbolic Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 12, no. 4, pp. 591–600, 2006. Available at: http://projecteuclid.org/getRecord?id=euclid.bsl/1164056808&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;GitmanHamkins:OpenDeterminacyForClassGames&quot;&gt;V. Gitman and J. D. Hamkins, “Open determinacy for class games,” in &lt;i&gt;Foundations of Mathematics, Logic at Harvard, Essays in Honor of Hugh Woodin’s 60th Birthday&lt;/i&gt;, A. E. Caicedo, J. Cummings, P. Koellner, and P. Larson, Eds. American Mathematical Society, (expected) 2016. Available at: http://jdh.hamkins.org/open-determinacy-for-class-games&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;AntosBartonFriedman:VLogic&quot;&gt;N. Barton, C. Antos, and S.-D. Friedman, “Universism and extensions of V,” &lt;i&gt;ArXiv e-prints&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;GitmanHamkinsHolySchlichtWilliams:ForcingTheorem&quot;&gt;V. Gitman, J. D. Hamkins, P. Holy, P. Schlicht, and K. Williams, “The exact strength of the class forcing theorem.” &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Sato:determinacy&quot;&gt;K. Sato, “Inductive dichotomy: separation of open and clopen class determinacies.” &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/vika_konstanz4.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/vika_konstanz1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the Young Researchers' Workshop: Forcing and Philosophy, University of Konstanz, January 18, 2018.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Virtual large cardinal principles</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/talks/2017/10/12/virtual-large-cardinal-principles.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Virtual large cardinal principles" /><published>2017-10-12T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-10-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/talks/2017/10/12/virtual-large-cardinal-principles</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/talks/2017/10/12/virtual-large-cardinal-principles.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://logic.harvard.edu/colloquium.php&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Harvard Logic Colloquium&lt;/a&gt;, Cambridge, November 8, 2017.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/images/harvard.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:left; padding: 10px;&quot; /&gt;

&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: 
Given a set-theoretic property $\mathcal P$ characterized by the existence of elementary embeddings between some first-order structures, let's say that $\mathcal P$ holds &lt;em&gt;virtually&lt;/em&gt; if the embeddings between structures from $V$ characterizing $\mathcal P$ exist somewhere in the generic multiverse. We showed with Schindler that virtual versions of supercompact, $C^{(n)}$-extendible, $n$-huge and rank-into-rank cardinals form a large cardinal hierarchy consistent with $V=L$. Included in the hierarchy are virtual versions of inconsistent large cardinal notions such as the existence of an elementary embedding $j:V_\lambda\to V_\lambda$ for $\lambda$ much larger than the supremum of the critical sequence. The Silver indiscernibles, under $0^\sharp$, which have a number of large cardinal properties in $L$, are also natural examples of virtual large cardinals.   Virtual versions of forcing axioms, including ${\rm PFA}$, ${\rm SCFA}$, and resurrection axioms, have been studied by Schindler and Fuchs, who showed that they are equiconsistent with virtual large cardinals. We showed with Bagaria and Schindler that the virtual version of Vopěnka's  Principle is consistent with $V=L$. Bagaria had showed that Vopěnka's  Principle holds if and only if the universe has a proper class of $C^{(n)}$-extendible cardinals for every $n\in\omega$. We almost generalized his result by showing that the virtual version is equiconsistent with the existence, for every $n\in\omega$, of a proper class of virtually $C^{(n)}$-extendible cardinals. With Hamkins we showed that Bagaria's result cannot generalize by constructing a model of virtual Vopěnka's  Principle in which there are no virtually extendible cardinals. The difference arises from the failure of Kunen's Inconsistency in the virtual setting. In the talk, I will discuss a mixture of results about the virtual large cardinal hierarchy and virtual Vopěnka's  Principle.</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the Harvard Logic Colloquium, Cambridge, November 8, 2017.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Filter games and Ramsey-like cardinals</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/talks/2017/09/27/filter-games-and-ramsey-like-cardinals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Filter games and Ramsey-like cardinals" /><published>2017-09-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/talks/2017/09/27/filter-games-and-ramsey-like-cardinals</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/talks/2017/09/27/filter-games-and-ramsey-like-cardinals.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://boolesrings.org/victoriagitman/cuny-logic-seminars/cuny-set-theory-seminar/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CUNY Set Theory Seminar&lt;/a&gt;, October 20, 2017.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter Holy and Philipp Schlicht recently introduced a robust hierarchy of Ramsey-like cardinals $\kappa$ using games in which player I plays an increasing sequence of $\kappa$-models and player II responds by playing an increasing sequence of $M$-ultrafilters for some cardinal $\alpha\leq\kappa$ many steps, with player II winning if she is able to continue finding the required filters &lt;a href=&quot;#HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. The entire hierarchy sits below a measurable cardinal and intertwines with Ramsey cardinals, as well as the Ramsey-like cardinals I introduced in &lt;a href=&quot;#gitman:ramsey&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. The cardinals in the hierarchy can also be defined by the existence of the kinds of elementary embeddings characterizing Ramsey cardinals and other cardinals in that neighborhood. Before getting to their hierarchy and the filter games, we need some background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Large cardinals $\kappa$ below a measurable cardinal tend to be characterized by the existence of certain elementary embeddings of weak $\kappa$-models or $\kappa$-models. A &lt;em&gt;weak $\kappa$-model&lt;/em&gt; is a transitive model of ${\rm ZFC}^-$ of size $\kappa$ and height above $\kappa$, which we should think of as a mini-universe of set theory; a $\kappa$-model is additionally closed under $\lt\kappa$-sequences. Given a weak $\kappa$-model $M$, we call $U\subseteq P(\kappa)\cap M$ an $M$-&lt;em&gt;ultrafilter&lt;/em&gt; if the structure $\langle M,\in, U\rangle$ satisfies that $U$ is a normal ultrafilter. (Note that since an $M$-ultrafilter is only $\lt\kappa$-complete for sequences from $M$, the ultrapower by it need not be well-founded.) Obviously, if the ultrapower of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ by an $M$-ultrafilter on $\kappa$ is well-founded, then we get an elementary embedding of $M$ into a transitive model $N$, and conversely if there is an elementary embedding $j:M\to N$ with $N$ transitive and critical point $\kappa$, then $U=\{A\in M\mid A\subseteq\kappa\text{ and }\kappa\in j(A)\}$ is an $M$-ultrafilter with a well-founded ultrapower. These types of elementary embeddings characterize, for instance, weakly compact cardinals. If $\kappa^{\lt\kappa}=\kappa$, then $\kappa$ is weakly compact whenever every $\kappa$-model has an $M$-ultrafilter on $\kappa$ (and hence a well-founded ultrapower).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An $M$-ultrafilter $U$, for a weak $\kappa$-model $M$, is called &lt;em&gt;weakly amenable&lt;/em&gt; if for every $X\in M$, which $M$ thinks has size $\kappa$, $X\cap U\in M$. Because a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter is partially internal to $M$, we are able to define its iterates and iterate the ultrapower construction as we would do with a measure on $\kappa$. If $j:M\to N$ is the ultrapower by a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter on $\kappa$, then $M$ and $N$ have the same subsets of $\kappa$, and conversely if $M$ and $N$ have the same subsets of $\kappa$ and $j:M\to N$ is an elementary embedding with critical point $\kappa$, then the induced $M$-ultrafilter is weakly amenable. In a striking contrast with the characterization of weakly compact cardinals, it is inconsistent to assume that &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; $\kappa$-model $M$ has a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter! Looking at this from the perspective of the corresponding elementary embeddings $j:M\to N$, this happens because there is too much reflection between $M$ and $N$ for objects of size $\kappa$. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The existence of weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilters for some weak $\kappa$-models characterizes Ramsey cardinals. A cardinal $\kappa$ is Ramsey whenever every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ which has a weakly amenable countably complete $M$-ultrafilter. If we assume that every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a $\kappa$-model $M$ which has such an $M$-ultrafilter, then we get a stronger large cardinal notion, the &lt;em&gt;strongly Ramsey&lt;/em&gt; cardinal. If we further assume that every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a $\kappa$-model $M\prec H_{\kappa^+}$ for which there is such an $M$-ultrafilter, then we get an even stronger notion, the &lt;em&gt;super Ramsey&lt;/em&gt; cardinal. Both notions are still weaker than a measurable cardinal. If we instead weaken our requirements and assume that every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model for which there is a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter with a well-founded ultrapower, we get a &lt;em&gt;weakly Ramsey&lt;/em&gt; cardinal, which sits between ineffable and Ramsey cardinals. I introduced these notions and showed that a super Ramsey cardinal is a limit of strongly Ramsey cardinals, which is in turn a limit of Ramsey cardinals, which is in turn a limit of weakly Ramsey cardinals, which is in turn a limit of completely ineffable cardinals [bibcite key=gitman:ramsey]. I also called weakly Ramsey cardinals &lt;em&gt;$1$-iterable&lt;/em&gt; because they are the first step in a hierarchy of &lt;em&gt;$\alpha$-iterable&lt;/em&gt; cardinals for $\alpha\leq\omega_1$, which all sit below a Ramsey cardinal (see [bibcite key=gitman:welch] for definitions and properties). What happens if we consider intermediate versions between Ramsey and strongly Ramsey cardinals where we stratify the closure on the model $M$, considering models with $M^\alpha\subseteq M$ for cardinals $\alpha&lt;\kappa$? What happens if we consider models $M\prec H_\theta$ for large $\theta$ and not just models $M\prec H_{\kappa^+}$?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Obviously we cannot have a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ elementary in $H_\theta$ for $\theta&gt;\kappa^+$. So let's drop the requirement of transitivity from the definition of a weak $\kappa$-model, but only require that $\kappa+1\subseteq M$. Now it makes sense to ask for a weak $\kappa$-model $M\prec H_\theta$ for arbitrarily large $\theta$. Suppose $\alpha\leq\kappa$ is a regular cardinal. Holy and Schlicht defined that $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;$\alpha$-Ramsey&lt;/em&gt; if for every $A\subseteq\kappa$ and arbitrarily large regular $\theta&gt;\kappa$, there is a weak $\kappa$-model $M\prec H_\theta$, closed under $\lt\alpha$-sequences, with $A\in M$ for which there is a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter on $\kappa$ (in the lone case $\alpha=\omega$, add that the ultrapower must be well-founded) &lt;a href=&quot;#HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. It is not difficult to see that it is equivalent to require that the models exist for &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; regular $\theta&gt;\kappa$. Also, for a fixed $\theta$, it suffices to have a single such weak $\kappa$-model $M\prec H_\theta$, meaning that the requirement that every $A$ is an element of such a model is superfluous. An $\omega$-Ramsey cardinal is a limit of weakly Ramsey cardinals, and I showed that it is weaker than a 2-iterable cardinal, and hence much weaker than a Ramsey cardinal. An $\omega_1$-Ramsey cardinal is a limit of Ramsey cardinals. A $\kappa$-Ramsey cardinal is a limit of super Ramsey cardinals. I will say where the strongly Ramsey cardinals fit in below. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that the $\alpha$-Ramsey cardinals have a game theoretic characterization! To motivate it, let's consider the following natural strengthening of the characterization of weakly compact cardinals. Suppose that whenever $M$ is a weak $\kappa$-model, $F$ is an $M$-ultrafilter and $N$ is another weak $\kappa$-model extending $M$, then we can find an $N$-ultrafilter $\bar F\supseteq F$. What is the strength of this property? I showed that it is inconsistent. Roughly, it implies the existence of too many weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilters, which we already saw leads to inconsistency (see &lt;a href=&quot;#HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; for proof). So here is instead a game version of extending models and filters formulated by Holy and Schlicht.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us say that a &lt;em&gt;filter&lt;/em&gt; is any subset of $P(\kappa)$ with the property that the intersection of any finite number of its elements has size $\kappa$. We will say that a filter $F$ &lt;em&gt;measures&lt;/em&gt; $A\subseteq \kappa$ if $A\in F$ or $\kappa\setminus A\in F$ and we will say that $F$ &lt;em&gt;measures&lt;/em&gt; $X\subseteq P(\kappa)$ if $F$ measures all $A\in X$. If $M$ is a weak $\kappa$-model, we will say that a filter $F$ is &lt;em&gt;$M$-normal&lt;/em&gt; if $F\cap M$ is an $M$-ultrafilter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose $\kappa$ is weakly compact. Given an ordinal $\alpha\leq\kappa^+$ and a regular $\theta&gt;\kappa$, consider the following two-player game of perfect information $G^\theta_\alpha(\kappa)$. Two players, the &lt;em&gt;challenger&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;judge&lt;/em&gt;, take turns to play $\subseteq$-increasing sequences $\langle M_\gamma\mid \gamma&lt;\alpha\rangle$ of $\kappa$-models, and $\langle F_\gamma\mid\gamma&lt;\alpha\rangle$ of filters on $\kappa$, such that the following hold for every $\gamma&lt;\alpha$.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; The challenger plays $M_\gamma\prec H_\theta$, and then the judge plays a filter $F_\gamma$ on $\kappa$ that measures $P(\kappa)\cap M_\gamma$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; $\langle M_{\bar\gamma}\mid \bar\gamma&lt;\gamma\rangle,\,\langle F_{\bar \gamma}\cap M_{\bar\gamma}\mid\bar\gamma&lt;\gamma\rangle\in M_\gamma$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
Let $M_\alpha=\bigcup_{\gamma&lt;\alpha}M_\gamma$ and $F_\alpha=\bigcup_{\gamma&lt;\alpha}F_\gamma$. If $F_\alpha$ is a $M_\alpha$-normal filter, then the judge wins, and otherwise the challenger wins. Note that in order to have any hope of winning the judge must play a filter $F_\gamma$ at each stage such that $F_\gamma\cap M_\gamma$ is an $M_\gamma$-ultrafilter.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Holy and Schlicht showed that if the challenger has a winning strategy in $G^\theta_\alpha(\kappa)$ for a single $\theta$, then the challenger has a winning strategy for all $\theta$, and similarly for the judge. Thus, we will say that $\kappa$ has the &lt;em&gt;$\alpha$-filter property&lt;/em&gt; if the challenger has no winning strategy in the game $G^\theta_\alpha(\kappa)$ for some (all) regular $\theta&gt;\kappa$. &lt;a href=&quot;#HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Holy and Schlicht showed that for regular $\alpha&gt;\omega$, $\kappa$ has the $\alpha$-filter property if and only if $\kappa$ is $\alpha$-Ramsey! Using the game characterization, they showed that $\kappa$ is $\alpha$-Ramsey ($\alpha&gt;\omega$) if and only if every $A\in H_{2^{\kappa^+}}$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M\prec H_{2^{\kappa^+}}$, closed under $\lt\alpha$-sequences, for which there is an $M$-ultrafilter. [bibcite key=HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals] Thus, we actually only need a single $\theta=2^{\kappa^+}$! So instead of $H_{\kappa^+}$ as in the definition of super Ramsey cardinals, the natural stopping point is $H_{2^{\kappa^+}}$. With the new characterization, we can also show that a strongly Ramsey cardinal is a limit of $\alpha$-Ramsey cardinals for every $\alpha&lt;\kappa$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So now we have in order of increasing strength: weakly Ramsey, $\omega$-Ramsey, $\alpha$-iterable for $2\leq\alpha\leq\omega_1$, Ramsey, $\alpha$-Ramsey for $\omega_1\leq\alpha&lt;\kappa$, strongly Ramsey, super Ramsey, $\kappa$-Ramsey, measurable.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why the restriction $\gamma&gt;\omega$? I showed that an $\omega$-Ramsey cardinal is a limit of cardinals with the $\omega$-filter property (see [bibcite key=HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals] for proof). The problem arises because even if the judge wins the game $G^\theta_\omega(\kappa)$, the ultrapower of $M_\omega$ by $F_\omega$ need not be well-founded. The same problem arises for any singular cardinal of cofinality $\omega$. The solution seems to be to consider a stronger version of the game for cardinals $\alpha$ of cofinality $\omega$, where it is required that the final filter $F_\alpha$ produces a well-founded ultrapower. Let's call this game $wfG^\theta_\alpha(\kappa)$. The well-founded games don't seem to behave as nicely as $G^\theta_\alpha(\kappa)$. For instance, it is not known whether having a winning strategy for a single $\theta$ is equivalent to having a winning strategy for all $\theta$. I conjecture that it is not the case. Still with the well-founded games, the arguments now generalize to show that $\kappa$ is $\omega$-Ramsey if and only if $\kappa$ has the well-founded $\omega$-filter property for every $\theta$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, what about $\alpha$-Ramsey cardinals for singular $\alpha$? Well, since a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ that is closed under $\lt\alpha$-sequences for a singular $\alpha$ is also closed under $\lt\alpha^+$-sequences, $\alpha$-Ramsey for a singular $\alpha$ implies $\alpha^+$-Ramsey. So instead Holy and Schlicht defined that $\kappa$ is $\alpha$-Ramsey for a singular $\alpha$ if $\kappa$ has the well-founded $\alpha$-filter property (the well-founded part is only needed for $\alpha$ of cofinality $\omega$) &lt;a href=&quot;#HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. Now we have the $\alpha$-Ramsey hierarchy for all cardinals $\alpha\leq\kappa$. Holy and Schlicht showed that this is a strict hierarchy of large cardinal notions: if $\kappa$ is $\alpha$-Ramsey and $\beta&lt;\alpha$, then $V_\kappa$ is a model of proper class many $\beta$-Ramsey cardinals, and moreover if $\beta$ is regular, then $\kappa$ is indeed a limit of $\beta$-Ramsey cardinals &lt;a href=&quot;#HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;P. Holy and P. Schlicht, “A hierarchy of Ramsey-like cardinals.” &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;gitman:ramsey&quot;&gt;V. Gitman, “Ramsey-like cardinals,” &lt;i&gt;The Journal of Symbolic Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 76, no. 2, pp. 519–540, 2011. Available at: http://dx.doi.org/10.2178/jsl/1305810762&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the CUNY Set Theory Seminar, October 20, 2017.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The exact strength of the class forcing theorem</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publications/2017/07/13/the-exact-strength-of-the-class-forcing-theorem.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The exact strength of the class forcing theorem" /><published>2017-07-13T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-07-13T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publications/2017/07/13/the-exact-strength-of-the-class-forcing-theorem</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publications/2017/07/13/the-exact-strength-of-the-class-forcing-theorem.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;GitmanHamkinsHolySchlichtWilliams:ForcingTheorem&quot;&gt;V. Gitman, J. D. Hamkins, P. Holy, P. Schlicht, and K. Williams, “The exact strength of the class forcing theorem.” &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We shall characterize the exact strength of the class forcing theorem, which asserts that every class forcing notion $\mathbb P$ has a corresponding forcing relation $\Vdash_{\mathbb P}$ satisfying the relevant recursive definition. When there is such a forcing relation, then statements true in any corresponding forcing extension are forced and forced statements are true in those extensions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike the case of set-sized forcing, where one may prove in ${\rm ZFC}$ that every set forcing notion $\mathbb P$ has its corresponding forcing relations, in the case of class forcing it is consistent with Gödel-Bernays set theory ${\rm GBC}$ that there is a proper class forcing notion $\mathbb P$ lacking a corresponding forcing relation, even merely for the atomic formulas. For certain forcing notions, the existence of an atomic forcing relation implies ${\rm Con}({\rm ZFC})$ and much more (see &lt;a href=&quot;#PeterHolyRegulaKrapfPhilippLuckeAnaNjegomirPhilippSchlicht:classforcing1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;), and so the consistency strength of the class forcing theorem goes strictly beyond ${\rm GBC}$, if this theory is consistent. Nevertheless, the class forcing theorem is provable in stronger theories, such as Kelley-Morse set theory. What is the exact strength of the class forcing theorem?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/images/ClassForcing.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; width=&quot;796&quot; height=&quot;782&quot; /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our project here is to identify the exact strength of the class forcing theorem by situating it in the rich hierarchy of theories between ${\rm GBC}$ and ${\rm KM}$, displayed in part in the above diagram, with the class forcing theorem highlighted in blue. It turns out that the class forcing theorem is equivalent over ${\rm GBC}$ to an attractive collection of several other natural set-theoretic assertions. So it is a robust axiomatic principle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main theorem is naturally part of the emerging subject we call the reverse mathematics of second-order set theory, a higher analogue of the perhaps more familiar reverse mathematics of second-order arithmetic. In this new research area, we are concerned with the hierarchy of second-order set theories between ${\rm GBC}$ and ${\rm KM}$ and beyond, analyzing the strength of various assertions in second-order set theory, such as the principle ${\rm ETR}$ of elementary transfinite recursion, the principle of $\Pi^1_1$-comprehension or the principle of determinacy for clopen class games, and so on. We fit these set-theoretic principles into the hierarchy of theories over the base theory ${\rm GBC}$. The main theorem of this article does exactly this with the class forcing theorem, by finding its exact strength in relation to nearby related theories in this hierarchy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Specifically, extending the analysis of &lt;a href=&quot;#PeterHolyRegulaKrapfPhilippLuckeAnaNjegomirPhilippSchlicht:classforcing1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; and (missing reference), we show in our main theorem that the class forcing theorem is equivalent over ${\rm GBC}$ to the principle of elementary transfinite recursion ${\rm ETR}_{\rm Ord}$ for transfinite class recursions of length ${\rm Ord}$; it is equivalent to the existence of a truth predicate for the infinitary language of set theory $\mathcal{L}_{\rm {Ord},\omega}(\in,A)$, with any fixed class parameter $A$; to the existence of a truth predicate in the more generous infinitary language $\mathcal{L}_{\rm {Ord},{\rm Ord}}(\in,A)$; to the existence of ${\rm Ord}$-iterated truth predicates for the first-order language $\mathcal{L}_{\omega,\omega}(\in,A)$; to the existence of set-complete Boolean class completions of any separative class partial order; and to the principle of determinacy for clopen class games of rank at most ${\rm Ord}+1$. We shall prove several of the separations indicated in figure above, such as the fact that the class forcing theorem is strictly stronger in consistency strength than having ${\rm ETR}_\alpha$ simultaneously for all ordinals $\alpha$ and strictly weaker than ${\rm ETR}_{\rm {Ord}\cdot\omega}$. The principle ${\rm ETR}_\omega$ is already sufficient to produce truth predicates for first-order truth, relative to any class parameter. Thus, our results locate the class forcing theorem somewhat finely in the hierarchy of second-order set theories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;strong&gt;Main Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;: The following are equivalent over Gödel-Bernays set theory ${\rm GBC}$.
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
The atomic class forcing theorem: every class forcing notion admits forcing relations for atomic formulas $$p\Vdash\sigma=\tau\qquad\qquad p\Vdash\sigma\in\tau.$$
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
The class forcing theorem scheme: every class forcing notion admits a scheme of forcing relations for first-order formulas. That is, for any particular first-order formula in the forcing language (finite in the meta-theory), with finitely many class names $\dot \Gamma_i$, there is a forcing relation
       $$p\Vdash\varphi(\vec\tau,\dot\Gamma_0,\ldots,\dot\Gamma_m)$$ applicable to this formula and its subformulas.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
The uniform first-order class forcing theorem: every class forcing notion $\mathbb P$ admits a uniform forcing relation $$p\Vdash\varphi(\vec \tau),$$ applicable uniformly with all first-order assertions in the forcing language $\varphi\in\mathcal{L}_{\omega,\omega}(\in,V^{\mathbb P},\dot\Gamma_0,\ldots,\dot\Gamma_m)$, allowing finitely many class names $\dot\Gamma_i$.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
Names for truth predicates: every class forcing notion $\mathbb P$ has a class name $\dot{\mathord{\rm T}}$ and a forcing relation for which ${\rm 1}\Vdash\dot{\mathord{\rm T}}$ is a truth-predicate for the first-order forcing language with finitely many class name parameters $\mathcal{L}_{\omega,\omega}(\in,V^{\mathbb P},\dot\Gamma_0,\ldots,\dot\Gamma_m)$.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
The uniform infinitary class forcing theorem: every class forcing notion $\mathbb P$ admits a uniform forcing relation $$p\Vdash\varphi(\vec \tau),$$ applicable to all assertions $\varphi(\vec{\tau})$ in the infinitary forcing language $\mathcal{L}_{\rm {Ord},\rm {Ord}}(\in,V^{\mathbb P},\dot\Gamma_0,\ldots,\dot\Gamma_m)$, allowing finitely many class names $\dot\Gamma_i$.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
 Every class forcing notion $\mathbb P$ admits a Boolean completion $\mathbb B$, a set-complete class Boolean algebra into which $\mathbb P$ densely embeds.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
The class-join separation principle plus ${\rm ETR}_{\rm Ord}$-foundation.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
For every class $A$, there is a truth predicate for $\mathcal{L}_{\rm {Ord},\omega}(\in,A)$.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
For every class $A$, there is a truth predicate for $\mathcal{L}_{\rm {Ord},\rm {Ord}}(\in,A)$.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
For every class $A$, there is an ${\rm Ord}$-iterated truth predicate for $\mathcal{L}_{\omega,\omega}(\in,A)$.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
The principle ${\rm ETR}_{\rm Ord}$ of elementary transfinite recursion for ${\rm Ord}$-length recursions of first-order properties, using any class parameter.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
The principle of determinacy for clopen class games of rank at most ${\rm Ord}+1$.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;PeterHolyRegulaKrapfPhilippLuckeAnaNjegomirPhilippSchlicht:classforcing1&quot;&gt;P. Holy, R. Krapf, P. Lücke, A. Njegomir, and P. Schlicht, “Class Forcing, the Forcing Theorem and Boolean Completions.” &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">{% reference page.ref %} We shall characterize the exact strength of the class forcing theorem, which asserts that every class forcing notion $\mathbb P$ has a corresponding forcing relation $\Vdash_{\mathbb P}$ satisfying the relevant recursive definition. When there is such a forcing relation, then statements true in any corresponding forcing extension are forced and forced statements are true in those extensions. Unlike the case of set-sized forcing, where one may prove in ${\rm ZFC}$ that every set forcing notion $\mathbb P$ has its corresponding forcing relations, in the case of class forcing it is consistent with Gödel-Bernays set theory ${\rm GBC}$ that there is a proper class forcing notion $\mathbb P$ lacking a corresponding forcing relation, even merely for the atomic formulas. For certain forcing notions, the existence of an atomic forcing relation implies ${\rm Con}({\rm ZFC})$ and much more (see {% cite PeterHolyRegulaKrapfPhilippLuckeAnaNjegomirPhilippSchlicht:classforcing1 %}), and so the consistency strength of the class forcing theorem goes strictly beyond ${\rm GBC}$, if this theory is consistent. Nevertheless, the class forcing theorem is provable in stronger theories, such as Kelley-Morse set theory. What is the exact strength of the class forcing theorem? Our project here is to identify the exact strength of the class forcing theorem by situating it in the rich hierarchy of theories between ${\rm GBC}$ and ${\rm KM}$, displayed in part in the above diagram, with the class forcing theorem highlighted in blue. It turns out that the class forcing theorem is equivalent over ${\rm GBC}$ to an attractive collection of several other natural set-theoretic assertions. So it is a robust axiomatic principle. The main theorem is naturally part of the emerging subject we call the reverse mathematics of second-order set theory, a higher analogue of the perhaps more familiar reverse mathematics of second-order arithmetic. In this new research area, we are concerned with the hierarchy of second-order set theories between ${\rm GBC}$ and ${\rm KM}$ and beyond, analyzing the strength of various assertions in second-order set theory, such as the principle ${\rm ETR}$ of elementary transfinite recursion, the principle of $\Pi^1_1$-comprehension or the principle of determinacy for clopen class games, and so on. We fit these set-theoretic principles into the hierarchy of theories over the base theory ${\rm GBC}$. The main theorem of this article does exactly this with the class forcing theorem, by finding its exact strength in relation to nearby related theories in this hierarchy. Specifically, extending the analysis of {% cite PeterHolyRegulaKrapfPhilippLuckeAnaNjegomirPhilippSchlicht:classforcing1 %} and {% cite key=PeterHolyRegulaKrapfPhilippSchlicht:classforcing2 %}, we show in our main theorem that the class forcing theorem is equivalent over ${\rm GBC}$ to the principle of elementary transfinite recursion ${\rm ETR}_{\rm Ord}$ for transfinite class recursions of length ${\rm Ord}$; it is equivalent to the existence of a truth predicate for the infinitary language of set theory $\mathcal{L}_{\rm {Ord},\omega}(\in,A)$, with any fixed class parameter $A$; to the existence of a truth predicate in the more generous infinitary language $\mathcal{L}_{\rm {Ord},{\rm Ord}}(\in,A)$; to the existence of ${\rm Ord}$-iterated truth predicates for the first-order language $\mathcal{L}_{\omega,\omega}(\in,A)$; to the existence of set-complete Boolean class completions of any separative class partial order; and to the principle of determinacy for clopen class games of rank at most ${\rm Ord}+1$. We shall prove several of the separations indicated in figure above, such as the fact that the class forcing theorem is strictly stronger in consistency strength than having ${\rm ETR}_\alpha$ simultaneously for all ordinals $\alpha$ and strictly weaker than ${\rm ETR}_{\rm {Ord}\cdot\omega}$. The principle ${\rm ETR}_\omega$ is already sufficient to produce truth predicates for first-order truth, relative to any class parameter. Thus, our results locate the class forcing theorem somewhat finely in the hierarchy of second-order set theories. Main Theorem: The following are equivalent over Gödel-Bernays set theory ${\rm GBC}$. The atomic class forcing theorem: every class forcing notion admits forcing relations for atomic formulas $$p\Vdash\sigma=\tau\qquad\qquad p\Vdash\sigma\in\tau.$$ The class forcing theorem scheme: every class forcing notion admits a scheme of forcing relations for first-order formulas. That is, for any particular first-order formula in the forcing language (finite in the meta-theory), with finitely many class names $\dot \Gamma_i$, there is a forcing relation $$p\Vdash\varphi(\vec\tau,\dot\Gamma_0,\ldots,\dot\Gamma_m)$$ applicable to this formula and its subformulas. The uniform first-order class forcing theorem: every class forcing notion $\mathbb P$ admits a uniform forcing relation $$p\Vdash\varphi(\vec \tau),$$ applicable uniformly with all first-order assertions in the forcing language $\varphi\in\mathcal{L}_{\omega,\omega}(\in,V^{\mathbb P},\dot\Gamma_0,\ldots,\dot\Gamma_m)$, allowing finitely many class names $\dot\Gamma_i$. Names for truth predicates: every class forcing notion $\mathbb P$ has a class name $\dot{\mathord{\rm T}}$ and a forcing relation for which ${\rm 1}\Vdash\dot{\mathord{\rm T}}$ is a truth-predicate for the first-order forcing language with finitely many class name parameters $\mathcal{L}_{\omega,\omega}(\in,V^{\mathbb P},\dot\Gamma_0,\ldots,\dot\Gamma_m)$. The uniform infinitary class forcing theorem: every class forcing notion $\mathbb P$ admits a uniform forcing relation $$p\Vdash\varphi(\vec \tau),$$ applicable to all assertions $\varphi(\vec{\tau})$ in the infinitary forcing language $\mathcal{L}_{\rm {Ord},\rm {Ord}}(\in,V^{\mathbb P},\dot\Gamma_0,\ldots,\dot\Gamma_m)$, allowing finitely many class names $\dot\Gamma_i$. Every class forcing notion $\mathbb P$ admits a Boolean completion $\mathbb B$, a set-complete class Boolean algebra into which $\mathbb P$ densely embeds. The class-join separation principle plus ${\rm ETR}_{\rm Ord}$-foundation. For every class $A$, there is a truth predicate for $\mathcal{L}_{\rm {Ord},\omega}(\in,A)$. For every class $A$, there is a truth predicate for $\mathcal{L}_{\rm {Ord},\rm {Ord}}(\in,A)$. For every class $A$, there is an ${\rm Ord}$-iterated truth predicate for $\mathcal{L}_{\omega,\omega}(\in,A)$. The principle ${\rm ETR}_{\rm Ord}$ of elementary transfinite recursion for ${\rm Ord}$-length recursions of first-order properties, using any class parameter. The principle of determinacy for clopen class games of rank at most ${\rm Ord}+1$. References {% bibliography --cited %}</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A model of the generic Vopěnka principle in which the ordinals are not Mahlo</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publications/2017/07/13/a-model-of-the-generic-vopenka-principle-in-which-the-ordinals-are-not-mahlo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A model of the generic Vopěnka principle in which the ordinals are not Mahlo" /><published>2017-07-13T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-07-13T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publications/2017/07/13/a-model-of-the-generic-vopenka-principle-in-which-the-ordinals-are-not-mahlo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publications/2017/07/13/a-model-of-the-generic-vopenka-principle-in-which-the-ordinals-are-not-mahlo.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;GitmanHamkins:GVP&quot;&gt;V. Gitman and J. D. Hamkins, “A model of the generic Vopěnka principle in which the ordinals are not Mahlo,” &lt;i&gt;To appear in the Archive for Mathematical Logic&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Vopěnka principle&lt;/em&gt; is the assertion that for every proper class of first-order structures in a fixed language, one of the structures embeds elementarily into another. This principle can be formalized as a single second-order statement in Gödel-Bernays set-theory ${\rm GBC}$, and it has a variety of useful equivalent characterizations. For example, the Vopěnka principle holds precisely when for every class $A$, the universe has an $A$-extendible cardinal, and it is also equivalent to the assertion that for every class $A$, there is a stationary proper class of $A$-extendible cardinals &lt;a href=&quot;#Hamkins:VopenkaPrinciple&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. In particular, the Vopěnka principle implies that ${\rm ORD}$ is Mahlo: every class club contains a regular cardinal and indeed, an extendible cardinal and more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To define these terms, recall that a cardinal $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;extendible&lt;/em&gt;, if for every $\lambda&gt;\kappa$, there is an ordinal $\theta$ and an elementary embedding $j:V_\lambda\to V_\theta$ with critical point $\kappa$. It turns out that, in light of the Kunen inconsistency, this weak form of extendibility is equivalent to a stronger form, where one insists also that $\lambda&amp;gt;j(\kappa)$; but there is a subtle issue about this that will come up later in our treatment of the virtual forms of these axioms, where the virtual weak and virtual strong forms are no longer equivalent. Relativizing to a class parameter, a cardinal $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;$A$-extendible&lt;/em&gt; for a class $A$, if for every $\lambda&amp;gt;\kappa$, there is an elementary embedding
 $$j:\langle V_\lambda, \in, A\cap V_\lambda\rangle\to \langle V_\theta,\in,A\cap V_\theta\rangle$$
with critical point $\kappa$, and again one may equivalently insist also that $\lambda&amp;lt;j(\kappa)$. Every such $A$-extendible cardinal is therefore extendible and hence inaccessible, measurable, supercompact and more. These are amongst the largest large cardinals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first-order ${\rm ZFC}$ context, set theorists commonly consider a first-order version of the Vopěnka principle, which we call the &lt;em&gt;Vopěnka scheme&lt;/em&gt;, the scheme making the Vopěnka assertion of each definable class separately, allowing parameters. That is, the Vopěnka scheme asserts, of every formula $\varphi$, that for any parameter $p$, if $\{\,x\mid \varphi(x,p)\,\}$ is a proper class of first-order structures in a common language, then one of those structures elementarily embeds into another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Vopěnka scheme is naturally stratified by the assertions ${\rm VP}(\Sigma_n)$, for the particular natural numbers $n$ in the meta-theory, where ${\rm VP}(\Sigma_n)$ makes the Vopěnka assertion for all $\Sigma_n$-definable classes. Using the definable $\Sigma_n$-truth predicate, each assertion ${\rm VP}(\Sigma_n)$ can be expressed as a single first-order statement in the language of set theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hamkins &lt;a href=&quot;#Hamkins:VopenkaPrinciple&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; proved that the Vopěnka principle is not provably equivalent to the Vopěnka scheme, if consistent, although they are equiconsistent over ${\rm GBC}$ and furthermore, the Vopěnka principle is conservative over the Vopěnka scheme for first-order assertions. That is, over ${\rm GBC}$ the two versions of the Vopěnka principle have exactly the same consequences in the first-order language of set theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, we are concerned with the virtual forms of the Vopěnka principles. The main idea of virtualization, due to Schindler, is to weaken elementary-embedding existence assertions to the assertion that such embeddings can be found in a forcing extension of the universe. Gitman and Schindler &lt;a href=&quot;#GitmanSchindler:virtualCardinals&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt; emphasized that the remarkable cardinals, for example, instantiate the virtualized form of supercompactness via the Magidor characterization of supercompactness. This virtualization program has now been undertaken with various large cardinals, leading to fruitful new insights (see &lt;a href=&quot;#GitmanSchindler:virtualCardinals&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;#BagariaGitmanSchindler:VopenkaPrinciple&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carrying out the virtualization idea with the Vopěnka principles, we define the &lt;em&gt;generic Vopěnka principle&lt;/em&gt; to be the second-order assertion in ${\rm GBC}$ that for every proper class of first-order structures in a common first-order language, one of the structures admits, in some forcing extension of the universe, an elementary embedding into another. That is, the structures themselves are in the class in the ground model, but you may have to go to the forcing extension in order to find the elementary embedding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, the &lt;em&gt;generic Vopěnka scheme&lt;/em&gt;, introduced in &lt;a href=&quot;#BagariaGitmanSchindler:VopenkaPrinciple&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;, is the assertion (in ${\rm ZFC}$  or ${\rm GBC}$) that for every first-order definable proper class of first-order structures in a common first-order language, one of the structures admits, in some forcing extension, an elementary embedding into another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the basis of their work in &lt;a href=&quot;#BagariaGitmanSchindler:VopenkaPrinciple&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;, Bagaria, Gitman and Schindler had asked the following question:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Question&lt;/strong&gt;: If the generic Vopěnka scheme holds, then must there be a proper class of remarkable cardinals?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There seemed good reason to expect an affirmative answer, even assuming only ${\rm gVP}(\Sigma_2)$, based on strong analogies with the non-generic case. Specifically, in the non-generic context Bagaria had proved that ${\rm VP}(\Sigma_2)$ was equivalent to the existence of a proper class of supercompact cardinals, while in the virtual context, Bagaria, Gitman and Schindler proved that the generic form ${\rm gVP}(\Sigma_2)$ was equiconsistent with a proper class of remarkable cardinals, the virtual form of supercompactness. Similarly, higher up, in the non-generic context Bagaria had proved that ${\rm VP}(\Sigma_{n+2})$ is equivalent to the existence of a proper class of $C^{(n)}$-extendible cardinals, while in the virtual context, Bagaria, Gitman and Schindler proved that the generic form ${\rm gVP}(\Sigma_{n+2})$ is equiconsistent with a proper class of virtually $C^{(n)}$-extendible cardinals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But further, they achieved direct implications, with an interesting bifurcation feature that specifically suggested an affirmative answer to the above question. Namely, what they showed at the $\Sigma_2$-level is that if there is a proper class of remarkable cardinals, then ${\rm gVP}(\Sigma_2)$ holds, and conversely if ${\rm gVP}(\Sigma_2)$ holds, then there is either a proper class of remarkable cardinals or a proper class of virtually rank-into-rank cardinals. And similarly, higher up, if there is a proper class of virtually $C^{(n)}$-extendible cardinals, then ${\rm gVP}(\Sigma_{n+2})$ holds, and conversely, if ${\rm gVP}(\Sigma_{n+2})$ holds, then either there is a proper class of virtually $C^{(n)}$-extendible cardinals or there is a proper class of virtually rank-into-rank cardinals. So in each case, the converse direction achieves a disjunction with the target cardinal and the virtually rank-into-rank cardinals. But since the consistency strength of the virtually rank-into-rank cardinals is strictly stronger than the generic Vopěnka principle itself, one can conclude on consistency-strength grounds that it isn't always relevant, and for this reason, it seemed natural to inquire whether this second possibility in the bifurcation could simply be removed. That is, it seemed natural to expect an affirmative answer to their question, even assuming only ${\rm gVP}(\Sigma_2)$, since such an answer would resolve the bifurcation issue and make a tighter analogy with the corresponding results in the non-generic/non-virtual case.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, however, we shall answer the question negatively. The details of our argument seem to suggest that a robust analogy with the non-generic/non-virtual principles is achieved not with the virtual $C^{(n)}$-cardinals, but with a weakening of that property that drops the requirement that $\lambda&amp;lt;j(\kappa)$. This seems to offer an illuminating resolution of the bifurcation aspect of the results we mentioned from &lt;a href=&quot;#BagariaGitmanSchindler:VopenkaPrinciple&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;, because it provides outright virtual large-cardinal equivalents of the stratified generic Vopěnka principles. Because the resulting virtual large cardinals are not necessarily remarkable, however, our main theorem shows that it is relatively consistent with even the full generic Vopěnka principle that there are no $\Sigma_2$-reflecting cardinals and therefore no remarkable cardinals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Main Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;ol style=&quot;margin-top: -20px;&quot;;&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; It is relatively consistent that ${\rm GBC}$ and the generic Vopěnka principle holds, yet ${\rm ORD}$ is not Mahlo.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt; It is relatively consistent that ${\rm ZFC}$ and the generic Vopěnka scheme holds, yet ${\rm ORD}$ is not definably Mahlo, and not even $\Delta_2$-Mahlo. In such a model, there can be no $\Sigma_2$-reflecting cardinals and therefore also no remarkable cardinals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Hamkins:VopenkaPrinciple&quot;&gt;J. D. Hamkins, “The Vopěnka principle is inequivalent to but conservative over the Vopěnka scheme.” Available at: http://jdh.hamkins.org/vopenka-principle-vopenka-scheme&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;GitmanSchindler:virtualCardinals&quot;&gt;V. Gitman and R. Schindler, “Virtual large cardinals,” &lt;i&gt;To appear in the Proceedings of the Logic Colloquium 2015&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;BagariaGitmanSchindler:VopenkaPrinciple&quot;&gt;J. Bagaria, V. Gitman, and R. Schindler, “Generic Vopěnka’s Principle, remarkable cardinals, and the
              weak Proper Forcing Axiom,” &lt;i&gt;Arch. Math. Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 56, no. 1-2, pp. 1–20, 2017. Available at: http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00153-016-0511-x&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">{% reference page.ref %} The Vopěnka principle is the assertion that for every proper class of first-order structures in a fixed language, one of the structures embeds elementarily into another. This principle can be formalized as a single second-order statement in Gödel-Bernays set-theory ${\rm GBC}$, and it has a variety of useful equivalent characterizations. For example, the Vopěnka principle holds precisely when for every class $A$, the universe has an $A$-extendible cardinal, and it is also equivalent to the assertion that for every class $A$, there is a stationary proper class of $A$-extendible cardinals {% cite Hamkins:VopenkaPrinciple %}. In particular, the Vopěnka principle implies that ${\rm ORD}$ is Mahlo: every class club contains a regular cardinal and indeed, an extendible cardinal and more. To define these terms, recall that a cardinal $\kappa$ is extendible, if for every $\lambda&gt;\kappa$, there is an ordinal $\theta$ and an elementary embedding $j:V_\lambda\to V_\theta$ with critical point $\kappa$. It turns out that, in light of the Kunen inconsistency, this weak form of extendibility is equivalent to a stronger form, where one insists also that $\lambda&amp;gt;j(\kappa)$; but there is a subtle issue about this that will come up later in our treatment of the virtual forms of these axioms, where the virtual weak and virtual strong forms are no longer equivalent. Relativizing to a class parameter, a cardinal $\kappa$ is $A$-extendible for a class $A$, if for every $\lambda&amp;gt;\kappa$, there is an elementary embedding $$j:\langle V_\lambda, \in, A\cap V_\lambda\rangle\to \langle V_\theta,\in,A\cap V_\theta\rangle$$ with critical point $\kappa$, and again one may equivalently insist also that $\lambda&amp;lt;j(\kappa)$. Every such $A$-extendible cardinal is therefore extendible and hence inaccessible, measurable, supercompact and more. These are amongst the largest large cardinals. In the first-order ${\rm ZFC}$ context, set theorists commonly consider a first-order version of the Vopěnka principle, which we call the Vopěnka scheme, the scheme making the Vopěnka assertion of each definable class separately, allowing parameters. That is, the Vopěnka scheme asserts, of every formula $\varphi$, that for any parameter $p$, if $\{\,x\mid \varphi(x,p)\,\}$ is a proper class of first-order structures in a common language, then one of those structures elementarily embeds into another. The Vopěnka scheme is naturally stratified by the assertions ${\rm VP}(\Sigma_n)$, for the particular natural numbers $n$ in the meta-theory, where ${\rm VP}(\Sigma_n)$ makes the Vopěnka assertion for all $\Sigma_n$-definable classes. Using the definable $\Sigma_n$-truth predicate, each assertion ${\rm VP}(\Sigma_n)$ can be expressed as a single first-order statement in the language of set theory. Hamkins {% cite Hamkins:VopenkaPrinciple%} proved that the Vopěnka principle is not provably equivalent to the Vopěnka scheme, if consistent, although they are equiconsistent over ${\rm GBC}$ and furthermore, the Vopěnka principle is conservative over the Vopěnka scheme for first-order assertions. That is, over ${\rm GBC}$ the two versions of the Vopěnka principle have exactly the same consequences in the first-order language of set theory. In this article, we are concerned with the virtual forms of the Vopěnka principles. The main idea of virtualization, due to Schindler, is to weaken elementary-embedding existence assertions to the assertion that such embeddings can be found in a forcing extension of the universe. Gitman and Schindler {% cite GitmanSchindler:virtualCardinals %} emphasized that the remarkable cardinals, for example, instantiate the virtualized form of supercompactness via the Magidor characterization of supercompactness. This virtualization program has now been undertaken with various large cardinals, leading to fruitful new insights (see {% cite GitmanSchindler:virtualCardinals %}, {% cite BagariaGitmanSchindler:VopenkaPrinciple %}). Carrying out the virtualization idea with the Vopěnka principles, we define the generic Vopěnka principle to be the second-order assertion in ${\rm GBC}$ that for every proper class of first-order structures in a common first-order language, one of the structures admits, in some forcing extension of the universe, an elementary embedding into another. That is, the structures themselves are in the class in the ground model, but you may have to go to the forcing extension in order to find the elementary embedding. Similarly, the generic Vopěnka scheme, introduced in {% cite BagariaGitmanSchindler:VopenkaPrinciple %}, is the assertion (in ${\rm ZFC}$ or ${\rm GBC}$) that for every first-order definable proper class of first-order structures in a common first-order language, one of the structures admits, in some forcing extension, an elementary embedding into another. On the basis of their work in {% cite BagariaGitmanSchindler:VopenkaPrinciple %}, Bagaria, Gitman and Schindler had asked the following question: Question: If the generic Vopěnka scheme holds, then must there be a proper class of remarkable cardinals? There seemed good reason to expect an affirmative answer, even assuming only ${\rm gVP}(\Sigma_2)$, based on strong analogies with the non-generic case. Specifically, in the non-generic context Bagaria had proved that ${\rm VP}(\Sigma_2)$ was equivalent to the existence of a proper class of supercompact cardinals, while in the virtual context, Bagaria, Gitman and Schindler proved that the generic form ${\rm gVP}(\Sigma_2)$ was equiconsistent with a proper class of remarkable cardinals, the virtual form of supercompactness. Similarly, higher up, in the non-generic context Bagaria had proved that ${\rm VP}(\Sigma_{n+2})$ is equivalent to the existence of a proper class of $C^{(n)}$-extendible cardinals, while in the virtual context, Bagaria, Gitman and Schindler proved that the generic form ${\rm gVP}(\Sigma_{n+2})$ is equiconsistent with a proper class of virtually $C^{(n)}$-extendible cardinals. But further, they achieved direct implications, with an interesting bifurcation feature that specifically suggested an affirmative answer to the above question. Namely, what they showed at the $\Sigma_2$-level is that if there is a proper class of remarkable cardinals, then ${\rm gVP}(\Sigma_2)$ holds, and conversely if ${\rm gVP}(\Sigma_2)$ holds, then there is either a proper class of remarkable cardinals or a proper class of virtually rank-into-rank cardinals. And similarly, higher up, if there is a proper class of virtually $C^{(n)}$-extendible cardinals, then ${\rm gVP}(\Sigma_{n+2})$ holds, and conversely, if ${\rm gVP}(\Sigma_{n+2})$ holds, then either there is a proper class of virtually $C^{(n)}$-extendible cardinals or there is a proper class of virtually rank-into-rank cardinals. So in each case, the converse direction achieves a disjunction with the target cardinal and the virtually rank-into-rank cardinals. But since the consistency strength of the virtually rank-into-rank cardinals is strictly stronger than the generic Vopěnka principle itself, one can conclude on consistency-strength grounds that it isn't always relevant, and for this reason, it seemed natural to inquire whether this second possibility in the bifurcation could simply be removed. That is, it seemed natural to expect an affirmative answer to their question, even assuming only ${\rm gVP}(\Sigma_2)$, since such an answer would resolve the bifurcation issue and make a tighter analogy with the corresponding results in the non-generic/non-virtual case. In this article, however, we shall answer the question negatively. The details of our argument seem to suggest that a robust analogy with the non-generic/non-virtual principles is achieved not with the virtual $C^{(n)}$-cardinals, but with a weakening of that property that drops the requirement that $\lambda&amp;lt;j(\kappa)$. This seems to offer an illuminating resolution of the bifurcation aspect of the results we mentioned from {% cite BagariaGitmanSchindler:VopenkaPrinciple %}, because it provides outright virtual large-cardinal equivalents of the stratified generic Vopěnka principles. Because the resulting virtual large cardinals are not necessarily remarkable, however, our main theorem shows that it is relatively consistent with even the full generic Vopěnka principle that there are no $\Sigma_2$-reflecting cardinals and therefore no remarkable cardinals. Main Theorem It is relatively consistent that ${\rm GBC}$ and the generic Vopěnka principle holds, yet ${\rm ORD}$ is not Mahlo. It is relatively consistent that ${\rm ZFC}$ and the generic Vopěnka scheme holds, yet ${\rm ORD}$ is not definably Mahlo, and not even $\Delta_2$-Mahlo. In such a model, there can be no $\Sigma_2$-reflecting cardinals and therefore also no remarkable cardinals. References {% bibliography --cited %}</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A model of second-order arithmetic with the choice scheme in which $\Pi^1_2$-dependent choice fails</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/talks/2017/05/09/a-model-of-second-order-arithmetic.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A model of second-order arithmetic with the choice scheme in which $\Pi^1_2$-dependent choice fails" /><published>2017-05-09T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-05-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/talks/2017/05/09/a-model-of-second-order-arithmetic</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/talks/2017/05/09/a-model-of-second-order-arithmetic.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the &lt;a \href=&quot;http://www.logic.univie.ac.at/Home.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Kurt Gödel Research Center&lt;/a&gt; Research Seminar in Vienna, Austria, May 18, 2017.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Josephinum.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:left; padding: 10px;&quot;/&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few years ago myself, Joel Hamkins, and Thomas Johnstone &lt;a href=&quot;#GitmanHamkinsJohnstone:KMplus&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;
(see this &lt;a href=&quot;/talks/2014/07/30/choice-schemes-for-kelley-morse-set-theory/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;) showed that the class choice scheme is independent of Kelley-Morse (${\rm KM}$) set theory in the strongest possible sense. The &lt;em&gt;class choice scheme&lt;/em&gt; is the scheme asserting, for every second-order formula $\varphi(x,X,A)$, that if for every set $x$, there is a class $X$ such that $\varphi(x,X,A)$ holds, then there is a collecting class $Y$ such that the $x$-th slice $Y_x$ is some witness for $x$, namely $\varphi(x,Y_x,A)$ holds. We can also consider a weaker version of the choice scheme allowing only set many choices. We showed that it is relatively consistent to have a model of ${\rm KM}$ in which the choice scheme fails for a first-order assertion and only $\omega$-many choices. We also showed that ${\rm KM}$ together with the choice scheme for set many choices cannot prove the choice scheme even for first-order assertions. The choice scheme can be viewed either as a collection principle or as an analogue of the axiom of choice for classes. With the later perspective, we can also consider the &lt;em&gt;dependent choice scheme&lt;/em&gt;, which asserts, for every second-order formula $\varphi(X,Y,A)$, that if for every $\alpha$-sequence of classes (coded by a class) $X$, there is a class $Y$ such that $\varphi(X,Y,A)$ holds, then there is a single class $Z$ coding ${\rm ORD}$-many dependent choices, namely for all ordinals $\alpha$, $\varphi(Z\upharpoonright\alpha,Z_\alpha,A)$ holds. Again, we can consider a weaker version of the dependent choice scheme where we only allow ordinal many choices. We conjectured that that the dependent choice scheme is independent of ${\rm KM}$ together with the choice scheme, but were not able to make further progress on the question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Usually when trying to prove a result about models of second-order set theory, it helps, as the first step, to understand analogous results for models of second-order arithmetic. There are many affinities, but also some notable differences between the kinds of results you can obtain in the two fields. Both the choice scheme and the dependent choice scheme were first considered and extensively studied in the context of models of second-order arithmetic (see &lt;a href=&quot;#simpson:second-orderArithmetic&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;, Chapter VII.6). The analogue of ${\rm KM}$ in second-order arithmetic is the theory ${\rm Z}_2$, which consists of ${\rm PA}$ together with full second-order comprehension. The theory ${\rm Z}_2$ implies the choice scheme for $\Sigma^1_2$-formulas. This is true roughly because a model of ${\rm Z}_2$ can uniformly construct (a code for) $L_\alpha$ for every coded ordinal $\alpha$ and so it can pass to an $L_\alpha$ to select a unique witness for a $\Sigma^1_2$-assertion, which are absolute by Shoenfield's Absoluteness. The classic Feferman-Lévy model was used to show that the very next level $\Pi^1_2$-choice scheme can fail in a model of ${\rm Z}_2$. Consider a model $\mathcal M$ of ${\rm Z}_2$ whose sets are the reals of the Feferman-Lévy model of ${\rm ZF}$. The model $\mathcal M$ can construct (a code for) $L_{\aleph_n}$ for every natural number $n$, but it cannot collect the codes because $\aleph_\omega$ is uncountable. The dependent choice scheme for $\Sigma^1_2$-formulas also follows from ${\rm Z}_2$ (indeed from the choice scheme for $\Sigma^1_2$-formulas together with induction for $\Sigma^1_2$-formulas, see &lt;a href=&quot;#simpson:second-orderArithmetic&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;, Theorem VII.6.9.2). Simpson claimed in 1972 that he had a proof of the independence of the $\Pi^1_2$-dependent choice scheme from ${\rm Z}_2$ together with the choice scheme but the proof was never published and has since been lost (I corresponded with Steve Simpson about it). So a few years ago Sy Friedman and myself set out to find a proof of this result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The standard strategy for obtaining a model of ${\rm Z}_2$ together with the choice scheme but with a $\Pi^1_2$-failure of the dependent choice scheme would be to construct a model of ${\rm ZF}$ in which ${\rm AC}_\omega$ holds, but ${\rm DC}$ fails for a $\Pi^1_2$-definable relation on the reals. We then take our model of ${\rm Z}_2$ whose sets are the reals of the ${\rm ZF}$-model, so that ${\rm AC}_\omega$ translates directly into the choice scheme holding. Such models of ${\rm ZF}$ are obtained as symmetric submodels of carefully chosen forcing extensions. The classical model of ${\rm AC}_\omega+\neg{\rm DC}$ (due to Jensen &lt;a href=&quot;#jensen:ACplusNotDC&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;) is a symmetric submodel of the forcing extension adding a collection of Cohen subsets of $\omega_1$ indexed by nodes of the tree ${}^{\lt\omega}\omega_1$ with countable conditions. By choosing the right collections of automorphisms to consider, we obtain a symmetric submodel, call it $N$, which has the tree of the Cohen subsets, but no branch through the tree, witnessing a violation of ${\rm DC}$. The countable closure of the poset allows us to prove that the model $N$ satisfies ${\rm AC}_\omega$. The obvious obstacle in using the classical model for our purposes was that the relation witnessing failure of ${\rm DC}$ is not on the reals. We were able to obtain a variation on the classical model where we forced to add a collection of Cohen reals indexed by nodes of the tree ${}^{\lt\omega}\omega_1$ with finite conditions. We use that the poset is ccc to again argue that ${\rm AC}_\omega$ holds in the desired symmetric submodel. The new model has a relation on the reals witnessing a failure of ${\rm DC}$, but it is not at all clear why even the domain of the relation, namely the Cohen reals making up the nodes of the generic tree, would be definable over the reals. The collection of all Cohen reals is of course $\Pi^1_2$-definable, but there does not appear to be a good way of picking out those coming from the nodes of our tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our construction we force with a tree iteration of Jensen's forcing along the tree ${}^{\lt\omega}\omega_1$. Conditions in the forcing are finite subtrees of ${}^{\lt\omega}\omega_1$ whose $n$-level nodes are conditions in the $n$-length iteration of Jensen's forcing, so that nodes on the higher levels extend those from the lower levels. The tree iteration adds, for every node on level $n$ of ${}^{\lt\omega}\omega_1$, an $n$-length sequence of reals generic for the $n$-length iteration of Jensen's forcing with the sequences ordered by extension. Jensen's forcing is a subposet of Sacks forcing in $L$ which has the ccc and the property that it adds a unique generic real over $L$ (see this &lt;a href=&quot;/talks/2017/01/20/a-countable-ordinal-definable-set-of-reals-without-ordinal-definable-elements/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;). The poset is constructed using $\diamondsuit$ to seal maximal antichains. Kanovei and Lyubetsky recently showed that Jensen's forcing has an even stronger uniqueness of generic filters property &lt;a href=&quot;#kanovei:productOfJensenReals&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;. They showed that a forcing extension of $L$ by the finite-support $\omega$-length product of Jensen's forcing has precisely the $L$-generic reals for Jensen's forcing which appear on the coordinates of the generic filter for the product. We were able to show that a forcing extension of $L$ by the tree iteration of Jensen's forcing has for a fixed $n$, precisely the generic $n$-length sequences of reals for the $n$-length iteration of Jensen's forcing which make up the nodes of the generic tree. Since the collection of the generic $n$-length sequences of reals for iterations of Jensen's forcing is $\Pi^1_2$ and the ordering of the sequences is by extension, we succeed in producing a symmetric submodel whose associated model of second-order arithmetic witnesses a $\Pi^1_2$-failure of the dependent choice scheme. That our symmetric model satisfied ${\rm AC}_\omega$ followed because the tree iteration forcing has the ccc.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are now working with Sy Friedman on transferring the arguments from second-order arithmetic to the context of second-order set theory. In particular, we hope to produce a subposet of $\kappa$-Sacks forcing for an inaccessible $\kappa$ in $L$ mimicking the properties of Jensen's forcing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;GitmanHamkinsJohnstone:KMplus&quot;&gt;V. Gitman, J. D. Hamkins, and T. Johnstone, “Kelley-Morse set theory and choice principles for classes.” &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;simpson:second-orderArithmetic&quot;&gt;S. G. Simpson, &lt;i&gt;Subsystems of second order arithmetic&lt;/i&gt;, Second. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge; Association for
              Symbolic Logic, Poughkeepsie, NY, 2009, p. xvi+444. Available at: http://dx.doi.org/10.1017/CBO9780511581007&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;jensen:ACplusNotDC&quot;&gt;R. B. Jensen, “Consistency results for models of ZF,” &lt;i&gt;Notices Am. Math. Soc.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 14, p. 137, 1967. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;kanovei:productOfJensenReals&quot;&gt;V. Kanovei and V. Lyubetsky, “A countable definable set of reals containing no definable elements.” &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the Kurt Gödel Research Center Research Seminar in Vienna, Austria, May 18, 2017.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Computable processes which produce any desired output in the right nonstandard model</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/talks/2017/03/15/computable-processes-which-produce-any-desired-output.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Computable processes which produce any desired output in the right nonstandard model" /><published>2017-03-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-03-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/talks/2017/03/15/computable-processes-which-produce-any-desired-output</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/talks/2017/03/15/computable-processes-which-produce-any-desired-output.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the special session &quot;Computability Theory: Pushing the Boundaries&quot; of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ams.org/meetings/sectional/2234_program.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;2​017 AMS Eastern Sectional Meeting&lt;/a&gt; in New York, May 6-7.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/images/huntercollege.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:left; padding: 10px;&quot; /&gt;
This talk will be a very condensed version of the &lt;a href=&quot;/talks/2016/03/29/computable-processes-can-produce-arbitrary-outputs-in-nonstandard-models/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;talk&lt;/a&gt; with a similar title I gave last spring at MOPA Seminar in CUNY.
&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/br&gt;&lt;/br&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt;
A total computable function will produce the same output on the standard natural numbers regardless of which model of arithmetic it is evaluated in. But a (partial) computable function can be the empty function in the standard model $\mathbb N$, while turning into a total function in some nonstandard model. I will discuss some extreme instances of this phenomena investigated recently by Woodin and Hamkins showing that there are computable processes which can produce any desired output by going to the right nonstandard model. Hamkins showed that there is a single ${\rm TM}$ program $p$ (computing the empty function in $\mathbb N$) with the property that given any function $f:\mathbb N\to \mathbb N$, there is a nonstandard model $M_f\models{\rm PA}$ so that in $M_f$ $p$ computes $f$ on the standard part. Even more drastically, Woodin has shown that there is a single index $e$ (for the empty function in $\mathbb N$), for which ${\rm PA}$ proves that $W_e$ is finite, with the property that for any finite set $s$ of natural numbers, there is a model $M_s\models{\rm PA}$ in which $W_e=s$. It follows for instance, by the MRDP theorem, that there is a single Diophantine equation $p(n,\bar x)=0$ having no solutions in $\mathbb N$, for which ${\rm PA}$ proves that there are finitely many $n$ with a solution, and given any finite set $s$, we can pass to a nonstandard model in which $p(n,\bar x)=0$ has a solution if and only if $n\in s$.

&lt;p&gt;Here are links to blog posts by myself and others on this topic:
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;/talks/2016/03/29/computable-processes-can-produce-arbitrary-outputs.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Computable processes can produce arbitrary outputs in nonstandard models&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;/talks/2016/03/29/computable-processes-can-produce-arbitrary-outputs-continued/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Computable processes can produce arbitrary outputs in nonstandard models (continued)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; (J. Hamkins) &lt;a href=&quot;http://jdh.hamkins.org/every-function-can-be-computable/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Every function can be computable!&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; (J. Baez) &lt;a href=&quot;https://johncarlosbaez.wordpress.com/2016/04/02/computing-the-uncomputable/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Computing the Uncomputable&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the special session &quot;Computability Theory: Pushing the Boundaries&quot; of 2​017 AMS Eastern Sectional Meeting in New York, May 6-7.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Virtual large cardinals</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publications/2017/03/14/virtual-large-cardinals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Virtual large cardinals" /><published>2017-03-14T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-03-14T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publications/2017/03/14/virtual-large-cardinals</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publications/2017/03/14/virtual-large-cardinals.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;GitmanSchindler:virtualCardinals&quot;&gt;V. Gitman and R. Schindler, “Virtual large cardinals,” &lt;i&gt;To appear in the Proceedings of the Logic Colloquium 2015&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose $\mathcal A$ is a large cardinal notion that can be characterized by the existence of one or many elementary embeddings $j:V_\alpha\to V_\beta$ satisfying some list of properties. For instance, both extendible cardinals and ${\rm I3}$ cardinals meet these requirements. Recall that $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;extendible&lt;/em&gt; if for every $\alpha&gt;\kappa$, there is an elementary embedding $j:V_\alpha\to V_\beta$ with critical point $\kappa$ and $j(\kappa)&gt;\alpha$, and recall also that $\kappa$ is ${\rm I3}$ if there is an elementary embedding $j:V_\lambda\to V_\lambda$ with critical point $\kappa&lt;\lambda$. Let us say that a cardinal $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;virtually&lt;/em&gt; $\mathcal A$ if the embeddings $j:V_\alpha\to V_\beta$ needed to witness $\mathcal A$ can be found in set-generic extensions of the universe $V$; equivalently we can say that the embeddings exist in the generic multiverse of $V$. Indeed, it is  not difficult to see that it suffices to only consider the collapse extensions.  So we now have that $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;virtually extendible&lt;/em&gt; if for every $\alpha&gt;\kappa$, some set-forcing extension has an elementary embedding $j:V^V_\alpha\to V^V_\beta$ with critical point $\kappa$ and $j(\kappa)&gt;\alpha$, and we have that $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;virtually&lt;/em&gt; ${\rm I3}$ if some set-forcing extension has an elementary embedding $j:V_\lambda^V\to V_\lambda^V$ with critical point $\kappa$. The template of virtual large cardinals can be applied to several large cardinals notions in the neighborhood of a supercompact cardinal. We can even apply it to inconsistent large cardinal principles to obtain virtual large cardinals that are compatible with $V=L$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of virtual large cardinals is close in spirit to generic large cardinals, but is technically very different. Suppose $\mathcal A$ is a large cardinal notion characterized by the existence of elementary embeddings $j:V\to M$ satisfying some list of properties. Then we say that a cardinal $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;generically&lt;/em&gt; $\mathcal A$ if the embeddings needed to witness $\mathcal A$ exist in set-forcing extensions of $V$. More precisely, if the existence of $j:V\to M$ satisfying some properties witnesses $\mathcal A$, then we want a forcing extension $V[G]$ to have a definable $j:V\to M$ with these properties, where $M$ is an inner model of $V[G]$. So for example, $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;generically supercompact&lt;/em&gt; if for every $\lambda&gt;\kappa$, some set-forcing extension $V[G]$ has an elementary embedding $j:V\to M$ with critical point $\kappa$ and $j''\lambda\in M$. If $\kappa$ is not actually $\lambda$-supercompact, the model $M$ will not be contained in $V$. Generic large cardinals are either known to have the same consistency strength as their actual counterparts or are conjectured to have the same consistency strength based on currently available evidence. Most importantly, generic large cardinals need not be actually &quot;large&quot; since, for instance, $\omega_1$ can be generically supercompact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of virtual large cardinals, because we consider only set-sized embeddings, the source and target of the embedding are both from $V$, and because the embedding exists in a forcing extension, there is no a priori reason why the target model would have any closure at all. The combination of these gives that virtual large cardinals are actual large cardinals that fit into the large cardinal hierarchy between ineffable cardinals and $0^\#$. If $0^\#$ exists, the Silver indiscernibles have (nearly) all the virtual large cardinal properties we consider in this article, and all these notions will be downward absolute to $L$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first virtual large cardinal notion, the remarkable cardinal, was introduced by Schindler in &lt;a href=&quot;#schindler:remarkable1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. A cardinal $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;remarkable&lt;/em&gt; if for every $\lambda&gt;\kappa$, there is $\bar\lambda&lt;\kappa$ such that in some set-forcing extension there is an elementary embedding $j:V_{\bar\lambda}^V \to V_\lambda^V$ with $j(\text{crit}(j))=\kappa$. It turns out that remarkable cardinals are virtually supercompact because, as shown by Magidor &lt;a href=&quot;#magidor:supercompact&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;, $\kappa$ is supercompact precisely when for every $\lambda&gt;\kappa$, there is $\bar\lambda&lt;\kappa$ and an elementary embedding $j:V_{\bar\lambda}\to V_\lambda$ with $j(\text{crit}(j))=\kappa$. Schindler showed that the existence of a remarkable cardinal is equiconsistent with the assertion that the theory of $L(\mathbb R)$ cannot be changed by proper forcing &lt;a href=&quot;#schindler:remarkable1&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, and since then it has turned out that remarkable cardinals are equiconsistent to other natural assertions such as the third-order Harrington's principle (missing reference), together with Bagaria, we studied a virtual version of Vopěnka's Principle (Generic Vopěnka's Principle) and a virtual version of the Proper Forcing Axiom ${\rm PFA}$. Fuchs has generalized this approach to obtain virtual versions of other forcing axioms such as the forcing axiom for subcomplete forcing ${\rm SCFA}$  &lt;a href=&quot;#Fuchs:HierarchiesForcingAxiomsContinuumHypothesisSquarePrinciples&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt; and resurrection axioms &lt;a href=&quot;#Fuchs:HierarchiesVirtualResurrectionAxioms&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;. Each of these virtual properties has turned out to be equiconsistent with some virtual large cardinal, which has so far been the main application of these ideas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our template for the definition of virtual large cardinals requires the large cardinal notion to be characterized by the existence of elementary embeddings $j:V_\alpha\to V_\beta$. This template is quite restrictive. Its main advantage is that it gives a hierarchy of large cardinal notions that mirrors the hierarchy of its actual counterparts, and the large cardinals have other desirable properties such as being downward absolute to $L$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;schindler:remarkable1&quot;&gt;R.-D. Schindler, “Proper forcing and remarkable cardinals,” &lt;i&gt;Bull. Symbolic Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 6, no. 2, pp. 176–184, 2000. Available at: http://dx.doi.org.ezproxy.gc.cuny.edu/10.2307/421205&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;magidor:supercompact&quot;&gt;M. Magidor, “On the role of supercompact and extendible cardinals in logic,” &lt;i&gt;Israel J. Math.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 10, pp. 147–157, 1971. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Fuchs:HierarchiesForcingAxiomsContinuumHypothesisSquarePrinciples&quot;&gt;G. Fuchs, “Hierarchies of forcing axioms, the continuum hypothesis and square principles.” &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Fuchs:HierarchiesVirtualResurrectionAxioms&quot;&gt;G. Fuchs, “Hierarchies of (virtual) resurrection axioms.” &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">{% reference page.ref %} Suppose $\mathcal A$ is a large cardinal notion that can be characterized by the existence of one or many elementary embeddings $j:V_\alpha\to V_\beta$ satisfying some list of properties. For instance, both extendible cardinals and ${\rm I3}$ cardinals meet these requirements. Recall that $\kappa$ is extendible if for every $\alpha&gt;\kappa$, there is an elementary embedding $j:V_\alpha\to V_\beta$ with critical point $\kappa$ and $j(\kappa)&gt;\alpha$, and recall also that $\kappa$ is ${\rm I3}$ if there is an elementary embedding $j:V_\lambda\to V_\lambda$ with critical point $\kappavirtually $\mathcal A$ if the embeddings $j:V_\alpha\to V_\beta$ needed to witness $\mathcal A$ can be found in set-generic extensions of the universe $V$; equivalently we can say that the embeddings exist in the generic multiverse of $V$. Indeed, it is not difficult to see that it suffices to only consider the collapse extensions. So we now have that $\kappa$ is virtually extendible if for every $\alpha&gt;\kappa$, some set-forcing extension has an elementary embedding $j:V^V_\alpha\to V^V_\beta$ with critical point $\kappa$ and $j(\kappa)&gt;\alpha$, and we have that $\kappa$ is virtually ${\rm I3}$ if some set-forcing extension has an elementary embedding $j:V_\lambda^V\to V_\lambda^V$ with critical point $\kappa$. The template of virtual large cardinals can be applied to several large cardinals notions in the neighborhood of a supercompact cardinal. We can even apply it to inconsistent large cardinal principles to obtain virtual large cardinals that are compatible with $V=L$. The concept of virtual large cardinals is close in spirit to generic large cardinals, but is technically very different. Suppose $\mathcal A$ is a large cardinal notion characterized by the existence of elementary embeddings $j:V\to M$ satisfying some list of properties. Then we say that a cardinal $\kappa$ is generically $\mathcal A$ if the embeddings needed to witness $\mathcal A$ exist in set-forcing extensions of $V$. More precisely, if the existence of $j:V\to M$ satisfying some properties witnesses $\mathcal A$, then we want a forcing extension $V[G]$ to have a definable $j:V\to M$ with these properties, where $M$ is an inner model of $V[G]$. So for example, $\kappa$ is generically supercompact if for every $\lambda&gt;\kappa$, some set-forcing extension $V[G]$ has an elementary embedding $j:V\to M$ with critical point $\kappa$ and $j''\lambda\in M$. If $\kappa$ is not actually $\lambda$-supercompact, the model $M$ will not be contained in $V$. Generic large cardinals are either known to have the same consistency strength as their actual counterparts or are conjectured to have the same consistency strength based on currently available evidence. Most importantly, generic large cardinals need not be actually &quot;large&quot; since, for instance, $\omega_1$ can be generically supercompact. In the case of virtual large cardinals, because we consider only set-sized embeddings, the source and target of the embedding are both from $V$, and because the embedding exists in a forcing extension, there is no a priori reason why the target model would have any closure at all. The combination of these gives that virtual large cardinals are actual large cardinals that fit into the large cardinal hierarchy between ineffable cardinals and $0^\#$. If $0^\#$ exists, the Silver indiscernibles have (nearly) all the virtual large cardinal properties we consider in this article, and all these notions will be downward absolute to $L$. The first virtual large cardinal notion, the remarkable cardinal, was introduced by Schindler in {% cite schindler:remarkable1 %}. A cardinal $\kappa$ is remarkable if for every $\lambda&gt;\kappa$, there is $\bar\lambda\kappa$, there is $\bar\lambda The idea behind the concept of virtual large cardinals of taking a property characterized by the existence of elementary embeddings of sets and defining a virtual version of the property by positing that the embeddings exist in the generic multiverse can be extended beyond large cardinals. In {% cite BagariaGitmanSchindler:VopenkaPrinciple %}, together with Bagaria, we studied a virtual version of Vopěnka's Principle (Generic Vopěnka's Principle) and a virtual version of the Proper Forcing Axiom ${\rm PFA}$. Fuchs has generalized this approach to obtain virtual versions of other forcing axioms such as the forcing axiom for subcomplete forcing ${\rm SCFA}$ {% cite Fuchs:HierarchiesForcingAxiomsContinuumHypothesisSquarePrinciples %} and resurrection axioms {% cite Fuchs:HierarchiesVirtualResurrectionAxioms %}. Each of these virtual properties has turned out to be equiconsistent with some virtual large cardinal, which has so far been the main application of these ideas. Our template for the definition of virtual large cardinals requires the large cardinal notion to be characterized by the existence of elementary embeddings $j:V_\alpha\to V_\beta$. This template is quite restrictive. Its main advantage is that it gives a hierarchy of large cardinal notions that mirrors the hierarchy of its actual counterparts, and the large cardinals have other desirable properties such as being downward absolute to $L$. References {% bibliography --cited %}</summary></entry></feed>