<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://victoriagitman.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://victoriagitman.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-06-15T14:53:04-04:00</updated><id>https://victoriagitman.github.io/</id><title type="html">Victoria Gitman</title><entry><title type="html">Class forcing in its rightful setting</title><link href="https://victoriagitman.github.io/talks/2020/06/25/class-forcing-in-its-rightful-setting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Class forcing in its rightful setting" /><published>2020-06-25T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-06-25T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://victoriagitman.github.io/talks/2020/06/25/class-forcing-in-its-rightful-setting</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://victoriagitman.github.io/talks/2020/06/25/class-forcing-in-its-rightful-setting.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the Kurt Godel Research Seminar, University of Vienna, June 25, 2020 (virtual).&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/classForcingTalk.pdf&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The use of class forcing in set theoretic constructions goes back to the proof Easton's Theorem that ${\rm GCH}$ can fail at all regular cardinals. Class forcing extensions are ubiquitous in modern set theory, particularly in the emerging field of set-theoretic geology. Yet, besides the pioneering work by Friedman and Stanley concerning pretame and tame class forcing, the general theory of class forcing has not really been developed until recently. A revival of interest in second-order set theory has set the stage for understanding the properties of class forcing in its natural setting. Class forcing makes a fundamental use of class objects, which in the first-order setting can only be studied in the meta-theory. Not surprisingly it has turned out that properties of class forcing notions are fundamentally determined by which other classes exist around them. In this talk, I will survey recent results (of myself, Antos, Friedman, Hamkins, Holy, Krapf, Schlicht, Williams and others) regarding the general theory of class forcing, the effects of the second-order set theoretic background on the behavior of class forcing notions and the numerous ways in which familiar properties of set forcing can fail for class forcing even in strong second-order set theories.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the Kurt Godel Research Seminar, University of Vienna, June 25, 2020 (virtual).Slides</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Elementary embeddings and smaller large cardinals</title><link href="https://victoriagitman.github.io/talks/2020/05/06/elementary-embeddings-and-smaller-large-cardinals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Elementary embeddings and smaller large cardinals" /><published>2020-05-06T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2020-05-06T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://victoriagitman.github.io/talks/2020/05/06/elementary-embeddings-and-smaller-large-cardinals</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://victoriagitman.github.io/talks/2020/05/06/elementary-embeddings-and-smaller-large-cardinals.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the Oxford Logic Seminar, Oxford University, May 6, 2020 (virtual).&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/smallembeddings.pdf&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href='https://www.youtube.com/watch?time_continue=113&amp;v=8h_OJcrNl2o&amp;feature=emb_logo'&gt;Video&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A common theme in the definitions of larger large cardinals is the existence of elementary embeddings from the universe into an inner model. In contrast, smaller large cardinals, such as weakly compact and Ramsey cardinals, are usually characterized by their combinatorial properties such as existence of large homogeneous sets for colorings. It turns out that many familiar smaller large cardinals have elegant elementary embedding characterizations. The embeddings here are correspondingly ‘small’; they are between transitive set models of set theory, usually the size of the large cardinal in question. The study of these elementary embeddings has led us to isolate certain important properties via which we have defined robust hierarchies of large cardinals below a measurable cardinal. In this talk, I will introduce these types of elementary embeddings and discuss the large cardinal hierarchies that have come out of the analysis of their properties. The more recent results in this area are a joint work with Philipp Schlicht.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the Oxford Logic Seminar, Oxford University, May 6, 2020 (virtual).Slides Video</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Toy multiverses of set theory</title><link href="https://victoriagitman.github.io/talks/2020/01/10/toy-multiverses-of-set-theory.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Toy multiverses of set theory" /><published>2020-01-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-01-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://victoriagitman.github.io/talks/2020/01/10/toy-multiverses-of-set-theory</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://victoriagitman.github.io/talks/2020/01/10/toy-multiverses-of-set-theory.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the &lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;Winter ASL Meeting&lt;/a&gt;, Denver, January 17-18, 2020.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Modern set theoretic research has produced a myriad of set-theoretic universes with fundamentally different properties and structures. Multiversists hold the philosophical position that none of these universes is the true universe of set theory - they all have equal ontological status and populate the set-theoretic multiverse. Hamkins, one of the main proponents of this view, formulated his position via the heuristic Hamkins Multiverse Axioms, which include such radical relativity assertions as that any universe is ill-founded from the perspective of another universe in the multiverse. With Hamkins, we showed that the collection of all countable computably saturated models of ${\rm ZFC}$ satisfies his axioms. Countable computably saturated models form a unique natural class with a number of desirable model theoretic properties such as existence of truth predicates and automorphisms. Indeed, any collection of models satisfying the Hamkins Multiverse Axioms must be contained within this class. In a joint work with Toby Meadows, Michał Godziszewski, and Kameryn Williams, we explore which weaker versions of the multiverse axioms have 'toy multiverses' that are not made up entirely of computably saturated models.
&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the Winter ASL Meeting, Denver, January 17-18, 2020.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ramsey-like cardinals</title><link href="https://victoriagitman.github.io/talks/2020/01/10/ramsey-like-cardinals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ramsey-like cardinals" /><published>2020-01-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-01-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://victoriagitman.github.io/talks/2020/01/10/ramsey-like-cardinals</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://victoriagitman.github.io/talks/2020/01/10/ramsey-like-cardinals.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the Algebra and Logic Seminar, University of Denver, January 14, 2020.&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/ramseyLikeCardinalsTalk.pdf&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ramsey-like cardinals originated with the study of elementary embedding properties of smaller large cardinals. Measurable cardinals and stronger large cardinals $\kappa$ are defined by the existence of elementary embeddings $j:V\to M$ with critical point $\kappa$ from the universe into an inner model. Elementary embeddings provide a unifying framework in the study of these large cardinals and set theorists have developed a toolbox of techniques for working with elementary embeddings, particularly for showing indestructibility under forcing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smaller large cardinals such as weakly compact cardinals and Ramsey cardinals were originally defined in terms of combinatorial Ramsey-type properties, but it turns out that they also have elementary embedding characterizations involving elementary embeddings of set-sized models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elementary embeddings $j:V\to M$ are connected with the existence of certain ultrafilters. The ultrapower of $V$ by a non-principal &lt;em&gt;countably complete&lt;/em&gt; ultrafilter is well-founded, and therefore produces a non-trivial elementary embedding $j:V\to M$, and such an embedding, if its critical point is $\kappa$, can be used to obtain a non-principal $\kappa$-complete ultrafilter $$U=\{A\subseteq\kappa\mid \kappa\in j(A)\}.$$  We will say that $U$ is &lt;em&gt;generated by $\kappa$ via $j$&lt;/em&gt;. Thus, in particular, there is a non-trivial elementary embedding $j:V\to M$ if and only if there is a non-principal countably complete ultrafilter on some cardinal $\kappa$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ultrapower construction with a countably complete ultrafilter can be iterated through all the ordinals to produce ${\rm Ord}$-many well-founded iterated ultrapowers. Given such an ultrafilter $U$, the first step is the original ultrapower $j:V\to M$, the second step is the ultrapower by $j(U)$, and we proceed in this manner, using the image of the original ultrafilter at successor stages and direct limits at limit stages. The successor stages are well-founded because all ultrafilters are countably complete (by elementarity) from the perspective of the model in which the ultrapower is constructed, and the direct limits are well-founded by a theorem of Gaifman &lt;a href=&quot;#gaifman:ultrapowers&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. Thus, we say that countably complete ultrafilters are &lt;em&gt;iterable&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Elementary embeddings of set-sized models of set theory are also connected with the existence of certain ultrafilters. So let's talk about these  models and ultrafilters. We say that a &lt;em&gt;weak $\kappa$-model&lt;/em&gt; is a transitive set model $M\models{\rm ZFC}^-$ of size $\kappa$ and height above $\kappa$. A weak $\kappa$-model $M$ is a &lt;em&gt;$\kappa$-model&lt;/em&gt; if it is additionally closed under sequences of length less than $\kappa$, the maximum possible closure for a model of size $\kappa$. Natural weak $\kappa$-models arise as elementary substructures of $H_{\kappa^+}$. Smaller large cardinals $\kappa$ are characterized by the existence of elementary embeddings of weak $\kappa$-models or $\kappa$-models with critical point $\kappa$. Given a weak $\kappa$-model $M$, we say that $U\subseteq P^M(\kappa)$ is an &lt;em&gt;$M$-ultrafilter&lt;/em&gt; if the structure $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$, that is $M$ together with a predicate for $U$, satisfies that $U$ is a normal ultrafilter on $\kappa$. What this means is that $U$ is an ultrafilter measuring $P^M(\kappa)$ that is closed under diagonal intersections of sequences from $M$. The set $U$ is allowed to be completely external to $M$, and while normality for sequences from $M$ implies $\kappa$-completeness for sequences from $M$, an $M$-ultrafilter $U$ may not even be countably complete because $M$, having no closure, can be missing many countable sequences. Note that, while the weak $\kappa$-model $M$ is required to satisfy ${\rm ZFC}^-$, replacement almost certainly fails in the structure $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$ once we add the $M$-ultrafilter. How do we know this? Read on. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the context of $M$-ultrafilters, we will weaken the notion of &lt;em&gt;countable completeness&lt;/em&gt; to say only that the intersection of countably many sets from the $M$-ultrafilter is non-empty. The two notions are equivalent for ultrafilters on $\kappa$, but for $M$-ultrafilters it is too strong to require that the intersection of countably many sets in the ultrafilter is itself in the ultrafilter because the intersection may not even be an element of $M$ and therefore not measured by the $M$-ultrafilter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can build the ultrapower of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ by an $M$-ultrafilter using functions $f$  on $\kappa$ from $M$. While we have a complete characterization of when an ultrafilter on $\kappa$ has a well-founded ultrapower, namely countable completeness, the situation with $M$-ultrafilters is much messier. Countable completeness of the $M$-ultrafilter suffices for well-foundedness, but this condition, as we will see, is too strong. Let's call an $M$-ultrafilter &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; if it has a well-founded ultrapower. There is no known elegant characterization of good $M$-ultrafilters. The existence of good $M$-ultrafilters is equivalent to the existence of elementary embeddings $j:M\to N$ because the set $U$ generated by $\kappa$ via $j$ as above is a good $M$-ultrafilter.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Next, let's talk about iterability of $M$-ultrafilters. After a moment's thought one realizes that given a good $M$-ultrafilter $U$ we cannot even perform the second step of the iterated ultrapower construction because, since $U$ is not an element of $M$, we cannot take the image of it under the ultrapower embedding. To have any hope of being iterable, an $M$-ultrafilter first needs to be internal enough to $M$ to make it possible to define successor stage ultrafilters. An $M$-ultrafilter is said to be &lt;em&gt;weakly amenable&lt;/em&gt; if for every set $S\in M$ with $|S|^M=\kappa$, $S\cap U\in M$. The condition of weak amenability suffices to define successor stage ultrafilters. It also has another nice characterization. We will say that an elementary embedding $j:M\to N$ with critical point $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;$\kappa$-powerset preserving&lt;/em&gt; if $M$ and $N$ have the same subsets of $\kappa$. It is always the case that $P^M(\kappa)\subseteq P^N(\kappa)$, but the other inclusion need not hold. Indeed, if a good $M$-ultrafilter $U$ is weakly amenable, then the ultrapower embedding $j:M\to N$ is $\kappa$-powerset preserving and conversely an $M$-ultrafilter generated by $\kappa$ via a $\kappa$-powerset preserving embedding $j:M\to N$ is weakly amenable. We will see below that while weak amenability makes it possible to define the stages of the iterated ultrapower construction, it does not guarantee the well-foundeness even of the second step ultrapower.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are finally ready to see some elementary embedding characterizations of smaller large cardinals. The simplest such characterization belongs to weakly compact cardinals. An inaccessible cardinal $\kappa$ is weakly compact if and only if every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ which has a good $M$-ultrafilter $U$. It turns out that this characterization can be strengthened in a number of ways. We can replace weak $\kappa$-model by $\kappa$-model, even by $\kappa$-model that is elementary in $H_{\kappa^+}$. Indeed, if $\kappa$ is weakly compact, then &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; weak $\kappa$-model has a good $M$-ultrafilter! Can we further strengthen the characterization by asking that all or at least some weak $\kappa$-models have weakly amenable good $M$-ultrafilters? The answer turns out to be no.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's make another definition. We will say that a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter is &lt;em&gt;$\alpha$-good&lt;/em&gt; if it has $\alpha$-many well-founded iterated ultrapowers. Note that $1$-good equals weakly amenable plus good. Some observations are in order. By a theorem of Gaifman &lt;a href=&quot;#gaifman:ultrapowers&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, only countable stages of the iteration matter. If an $M$-ultrafilter is $\omega_1$-good, then it is $\alpha$-good for every $\alpha$. By a theorem of Kunen (missing reference), a countably complete $M$-ultrafilter is $\omega_1$-good. We will say that a cardinal $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;$\alpha$-iterable&lt;/em&gt; if every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ which has an $\alpha$-good $M$-ultrafilter. Thus, we can rephrase the question about weakly compacts above as asking whether a weakly compact cardinal is 1-iterable. In fact, 1-iterable cardinals are limits of weakly compact cardinals, even limits of ineffable cardinals &lt;a href=&quot;#gitman:ramsey&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. The $\alpha$-iterable cardinals for $\alpha\leq\omega_1$ form a hierarchy of strength where a $\beta$-iterable cardinal is a limit of $\alpha$-iterable cardinals for every $\alpha\lt\beta$. The $\alpha$-iterable cardinals for $\alpha$ countable are downward absolute to $L$, but $\omega_1$-iterable cardinals already imply $0^{\#}$ &lt;a href=&quot;#gitman:welch&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, up are Ramsey cardinals, which also have an unexpectedly nice elementary embedding characterization. A cardinal $\kappa$ is Ramsey if and only if every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ which has a weakly amenable countably complete $M$-ultrafilter &lt;a href=&quot;#mitchell:ramsey&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;. Can we strengthen the Ramsey elementary embedding characterization by replacing weak $\kappa$-model with $\kappa$-model or even $\kappa$-model elementary in $H_{\kappa^+}$, or even ask that it holds for all weak $\kappa$-models? The answer is no.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We say that a cardinal $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;strongly Ramsey&lt;/em&gt; if every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a $\kappa$-model $M$ which has a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter and a cardinal $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;super Ramsey&lt;/em&gt; if we replace $\kappa$-model with $\kappa$-model elementary in $H_{\kappa^+}$. Strongly Ramsey cardinals are limits of Ramsey cardinals and super Ramsey cardinals are limits of strongly Ramsey cardinals. The assertion that every weak $\kappa$-model has a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter is inconsistent! &lt;a href=&quot;#gitman:ramsey&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt; Broadly speaking, the reason for this contrast in relationships with the introduction of weak amenability is that having the same subsets of $\kappa$ creates a great deal of reflection between $M$ and its ultrapower $N$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are there other natural large cardinal notions between super Ramsey and measurable cardinals? Super Ramsey cardinals require embeddings on $\kappa$-model elementary in $H_{\kappa^+}$ because such models look like an initial segment of the universe. A natural extension of the idea of having embeddings on models reflecting an initial segment of the universe is to require that the weak $\kappa$-model is elementary in some larger $H_\theta$. But this is impossible because large $H_\theta$ cannot have transitive elementary submodels of size $\kappa$. So let's define that an &lt;em&gt;imperfect weak $\kappa$-model&lt;/em&gt; is a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ where we replace transitivity with the weaker requirement that $\kappa+1\subseteq M$, and similarly define &lt;em&gt;imperfect $\kappa$-models&lt;/em&gt;. Now we can consider the large cardinal notion &lt;em&gt;$\kappa$-Ramsey&lt;/em&gt;, introduced by Holy and Schlicht, where for every set $A$ and arbitrarily large cardinals $\theta$, $A$ is an element of an imperfect $\kappa$-model $M\prec H_\theta$ which has a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter. $\kappa$-Ramsey cardinals have a natural game characterization. The game is played by the challenger and the judge, with the challenger playing an increasing sequence of imperfect $\kappa$-models $M\prec H_\theta$ and the judge responding with nested $M$-ultrafilters. For the judge to win a game of length $\alpha$ she has to be able to play for $\alpha$-many steps, with the challenger winning otherwise. The reason the large cardinal is called $\kappa$-Ramsey is that it is characterized by the challenger failing to have a winning strategy in this game of length $\kappa$. $\kappa$-Ramsey cardinals are limits of super Ramsey cardinals. &lt;a href=&quot;#HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are there natural large cardinal notions between $\kappa$-Ramsey cardinals and measurable cardinals? Yes! Remember I remarked earlier that the structure $\langle M,\in,U\rangle$, where $M$ is a weak $\kappa$-model and $U$ is an $M$-ultrafilter almost certainly fails to satisfy replacement? Well, let's define that a cardinal $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;weakly baby measurable&lt;/em&gt; if every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ which has a good $M$-ultrafilter such that $\langle M,\in, U\rangle\models{\rm ZFC}^-$. Similar large cardinal notions were introduced and investigated recently by McKenzie and Bovykin &lt;a href=&quot;#BovykinMcKenzie:RamseyLikeNFUM&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;. We recently realized with Philipp Schlicht that if $\kappa$ is weakly baby measurable, then $V_\kappa$ is a model of proper class many cardinals $\alpha$ that are $\alpha$-Ramsey. Baby measurable cardinals (McKenzie and Bovykin call them &lt;em&gt;simultaneously baby measurable&lt;/em&gt;) would be cardinals where we replace weak $\kappa$-model with $\kappa$-model. These are even stronger, but still some ways below a measurable!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;gaifman:ultrapowers&quot;&gt;H. Gaifman, “Elementary embeddings of models of set-theory and certain
              subtheories,” in &lt;i&gt;Axiomatic set theory (Proc. Sympos. Pure Math., Vol.
              XIII, Part II, Univ. California, Los Angeles,
              Calif., 1967)&lt;/i&gt;, Providence R.I.: Amer. Math. Soc., 1974, pp. 33–101. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;gitman:ramsey&quot;&gt;V. Gitman, “Ramsey-like cardinals,” &lt;i&gt;The Journal of Symbolic Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 76, no. 2, pp. 519–540, 2011. Available at: http://dx.doi.org/10.2178/jsl/1305810762&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;gitman:welch&quot;&gt;V. Gitman and P. D. Welch, “Ramsey-like cardinals II,” &lt;i&gt;The Journal of Symbolic Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 76, no. 2, pp. 541–560, 2011. Available at: http://dx.doi.org/10.2178/jsl/1305810763&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;mitchell:ramsey&quot;&gt;W. Mitchell, “Ramsey cardinals and constructibility,” &lt;i&gt;J. Symbolic Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 44, no. 2, pp. 260–266, 1979. Available at: http://dx.doi.org.ezproxy.gc.cuny.edu/10.2307/2273732&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;P. Holy and P. Schlicht, “A hierarchy of Ramsey-like cardinals.” &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;BovykinMcKenzie:RamseyLikeNFUM&quot;&gt;A. Bovykin and Z. McKenzie, “Ramsey-like cardinals that characterize the exact consistency strength of NFUM.” &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the Algebra and Logic Seminar, University of Denver, January 14, 2020.Slides</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Modern class forcing</title><link href="https://victoriagitman.github.io/publications/2019/11/13/modern-class-forcing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Modern class forcing" /><published>2019-11-13T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2019-11-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://victoriagitman.github.io/publications/2019/11/13/modern-class-forcing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://victoriagitman.github.io/publications/2019/11/13/modern-class-forcing.html">&lt;p&gt;(missing reference)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Set theorists started forcing with class partial orders to modify global properties of the universe very soon after general forcing techniques were developed. Once Cohen showed that ${\rm CH}$ could fail, and that indeed the continuum could assume any reasonable value, it was natural to ask whether, for instance, the ${\rm GCH}$ can fail unboundedly often, or more generally what global patterns were possible for the continuum function. Since a set partial order can only affect a set-sized chunk of the continuum function, a class partial order was required to modify the ${\rm GCH}$ pattern unboundedly. Easton used a class product of set-forcing notions, with what became known as Easton support, to show that the ${\rm GCH}$ can fail at every regular cardinal, and that, in fact, any reasonable pattern on the continuum function was consistent with ${\rm ZFC}$ &lt;a href=&quot;#easton:gch&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. Since then class products and iterations, usually with Easton support, have been used, for example, to globally kill large cardinals, to make all supercompact cardinals indestructible, or to code the universe into the continuum function.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two approaches to handling class forcing in first-order set theory. We can use a generic filter $G$ for a class forcing notion $\mathbb P$ to interpret the $\mathbb P$-names and obtain the forcing extension $V[G]$, and then throw $G$ away. We can also work in the structure $(V[G],\in,G)$ with a predicate for $G$. While both approaches were used by set theorists to handle specific instances of class forcing, neither approach could provide a robust framework for the study of general properties of class forcing because it relegated properties of classes to the meta-theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Important early results on class forcing, due to Friedman and Stanley, showed that class partial orders satisfying `niceness' conditions, such as pretameness, behave like set partial orders. But despite the pervasive use of class forcing in set theoretic constructions, a general theory of class forcing was not fully developed until recently. These recent results demonstrated that properties of class forcing depend on what other classes exist around them, establishing that the theory of class forcing can only be properly investigated in a second-order set theoretic setting. The mathematical framework of second-order set theory has objects for both sets and classes, and allows us to move the study of classes out of the meta-theory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Class forcing becomes even more important in the context of second-order set theory, where it can be used to modify the structure of classes. With class forcing, we can, for instances, add a global well-order or shoot class clubs with desirable properties. Both these forcing notions leave the first-order part of the model intact because they do not add sets. Such forcing constructions over models of second-order set theory can actually be used to prove theorems about models of ${\rm ZFC}$. One of the most important results in the model theory of set theory is the Keisler-Morley extension theorem asserting that every countable model of ${\rm ZFC}$ has an elementary top-extension (adding only sets of rank above the ordinals of the model) &lt;a href=&quot;#keislermorley:topextensions&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. Given a countable model $M$ of ${\rm ZFC}$, the top-extension is built as an ultrapower of $M$ by a special ultrafilter, which we can construct provided that $M$ can be expanded to a model of ${\rm GBC}$. If $M$ doesn't already have a definable global well-order, we use class forcing to add it without altering $M$ itself.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many ways class forcing does not behave as nicely as set forcing. Class forcing can destroy ${\rm ZFC}$; even the atomic forcing relation may fail to be definable for a class forcing notion; densely embedded class forcing notions need not be forcing equivalent; most class forcing notions don't have Boolean completions; the intermediate model theorem fails badly for class forcing, etc. At the same time, conditions on class forcing, such as pretameness, guarantee that these pathologies are avoided, and these conditions hold for most familiar class forcing notions used by set theorists, such as progressively closed Easton support products and iterations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article, we survey most of the recent results developing a general theory of class forcing in the second-order setting and establishing surprising connections between properties of class forcing and the structure of second-order set theories.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;easton:gch&quot;&gt;W. B. Easton, “Powers of regular cardinals,” &lt;i&gt;Ann. Math. Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 1, pp. 139–178, 1970. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;keislermorley:topextensions&quot;&gt;H. J. Keisler and M. Morley, “Elementary extensions of models of set theory,” &lt;i&gt;Israel J. Math.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 6, pp. 49–65, 1968. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">{% reference page.ref %} Set theorists started forcing with class partial orders to modify global properties of the universe very soon after general forcing techniques were developed. Once Cohen showed that ${\rm CH}$ could fail, and that indeed the continuum could assume any reasonable value, it was natural to ask whether, for instance, the ${\rm GCH}$ can fail unboundedly often, or more generally what global patterns were possible for the continuum function. Since a set partial order can only affect a set-sized chunk of the continuum function, a class partial order was required to modify the ${\rm GCH}$ pattern unboundedly. Easton used a class product of set-forcing notions, with what became known as Easton support, to show that the ${\rm GCH}$ can fail at every regular cardinal, and that, in fact, any reasonable pattern on the continuum function was consistent with ${\rm ZFC}$ {% cite easton:gch %}. Since then class products and iterations, usually with Easton support, have been used, for example, to globally kill large cardinals, to make all supercompact cardinals indestructible, or to code the universe into the continuum function. There are two approaches to handling class forcing in first-order set theory. We can use a generic filter $G$ for a class forcing notion $\mathbb P$ to interpret the $\mathbb P$-names and obtain the forcing extension $V[G]$, and then throw $G$ away. We can also work in the structure $(V[G],\in,G)$ with a predicate for $G$. While both approaches were used by set theorists to handle specific instances of class forcing, neither approach could provide a robust framework for the study of general properties of class forcing because it relegated properties of classes to the meta-theory. Important early results on class forcing, due to Friedman and Stanley, showed that class partial orders satisfying `niceness' conditions, such as pretameness, behave like set partial orders. But despite the pervasive use of class forcing in set theoretic constructions, a general theory of class forcing was not fully developed until recently. These recent results demonstrated that properties of class forcing depend on what other classes exist around them, establishing that the theory of class forcing can only be properly investigated in a second-order set theoretic setting. The mathematical framework of second-order set theory has objects for both sets and classes, and allows us to move the study of classes out of the meta-theory. Class forcing becomes even more important in the context of second-order set theory, where it can be used to modify the structure of classes. With class forcing, we can, for instances, add a global well-order or shoot class clubs with desirable properties. Both these forcing notions leave the first-order part of the model intact because they do not add sets. Such forcing constructions over models of second-order set theory can actually be used to prove theorems about models of ${\rm ZFC}$. One of the most important results in the model theory of set theory is the Keisler-Morley extension theorem asserting that every countable model of ${\rm ZFC}$ has an elementary top-extension (adding only sets of rank above the ordinals of the model) {% cite keislermorley:topextensions %}. Given a countable model $M$ of ${\rm ZFC}$, the top-extension is built as an ultrapower of $M$ by a special ultrafilter, which we can construct provided that $M$ can be expanded to a model of ${\rm GBC}$. If $M$ doesn't already have a definable global well-order, we use class forcing to add it without altering $M$ itself. In many ways class forcing does not behave as nicely as set forcing. Class forcing can destroy ${\rm ZFC}$; even the atomic forcing relation may fail to be definable for a class forcing notion; densely embedded class forcing notions need not be forcing equivalent; most class forcing notions don't have Boolean completions; the intermediate model theorem fails badly for class forcing, etc. At the same time, conditions on class forcing, such as pretameness, guarantee that these pathologies are avoided, and these conditions hold for most familiar class forcing notions used by set theorists, such as progressively closed Easton support products and iterations. In this article, we survey most of the recent results developing a general theory of class forcing in the second-order setting and establishing surprising connections between properties of class forcing and the structure of second-order set theories. References {% bibliography --cited %}</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Structural properties of the stable core</title><link href="https://victoriagitman.github.io/publications/2019/10/10/structural-properties-of-the-stable-core.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Structural properties of the stable core" /><published>2019-10-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-10-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://victoriagitman.github.io/publications/2019/10/10/structural-properties-of-the-stable-core</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://victoriagitman.github.io/publications/2019/10/10/structural-properties-of-the-stable-core.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;FriedmanGitmanMuller:StableCore&quot;&gt;S.-D. Friedman, V. Gitman, and S. Müller, “Some properties of the Stable Core,” &lt;i&gt;Manuscript&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first author introduced the inner model &lt;em&gt;stable core&lt;/em&gt; while investigating under what
circumstances the universe $V$ is a class forcing extension of the
inner model ${\rm HOD}$, the collection of all hereditarily ordinal
definable sets (missing reference). He showed in (missing reference) that there is a robust $\Delta_2$-definable
class $S$ contained in ${\rm HOD}$ such that $V$ is a class-forcing extension of the structure $\langle L[S],\in, S\rangle$, which he called the stable core, by an ${\rm Ord}$-cc class partial order $\mathbb P$ definable from $S$. Indeed, for any inner model $M$, $V$ is a $\mathbb P$-forcing extension of $\langle M[S],\in,S\rangle$, so that in particular, since ${\rm HOD}[S]={\rm HOD}$, $V$ is a $\mathbb P$-forcing extension of $\langle {\rm HOD},\in,S\rangle$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let's explain the result in more detail for the stable core $L[S]$, noting that exactly the same analysis applies to ${\rm HOD}$. The partial order $\mathbb P$ is definable in $\langle L[S],\in,S\rangle$ and there is a generic filter $G$, meeting all dense sub-classes of $\mathbb P$ definable in $\langle L[S],\in,S\rangle$,
such that $V=L[S][G]$. All standard forcing theorems hold for $\mathbb P$ since it has the ${\rm Ord}$-cc. Thus, we get that the forcing relation for $\mathbb P$ is definable in $\langle L[S],\in,S\rangle$ and the forcing extension $\langle V,\in,G\rangle\models{\rm ZFC}$. However, this particular generic filter $G$ is not definable in $V$. To obtain $G$, we first force with an auxiliary forcing $\mathbb Q$ to add a particular class $F$, without adding sets, such that $V=L[F]$. We then show that $G$ is definable from $F$ and $F$ is in turn definable in the structure $\langle L[S][G], \in, S,G\rangle$, so that $L[S][G]=V$. This gives a formulation of the result as a ${\rm ZFC}$-theorem because we can say (using the definitions of $\mathbb P$ and $\mathbb Q$) that it is forced by $\mathbb Q$ that $V=L[F]$, where $F$ is $V$-generic for $\mathbb Q$, and (the definition of) $G$ is $\langle L[S],\in,S\rangle$-generic, and finally that $F$ is definable in $\langle L[S][G],\in,S,G\rangle$. Of course, a careful formulation would say that the result holds for all sufficiently large natural numbers $n$, where $n$ bounds the complexity of the formulas used.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Without the niceness requirement on $\mathbb P$ that it has the ${\rm Ord}$-cc, there is a much easier construction of a class forcing notion $\mathbb P$, suggested by Woodin, such that $V$ is a class forcing extension of $\langle {\rm HOD},\in, \mathbb P\rangle$. At the same time, some additional predicate must be added to ${\rm HOD}$ in
order to realize all of $V$ as a class-forcing extension because, as
Hamkins and Reitz observed in
&lt;a href=&quot;#HamkinsReitz:The-set-theoretic-universe-is-not-necessarily-a-forcing-extension-of-HOD&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;,
it is consistent that $V$ is not a class-forcing extension of ${\rm HOD}$. To construct such a counterexample, we suppose that $\kappa$ is inaccessible in $L$ and force over the Kelley-Morse model $\mathcal L=\langle L_\kappa,\in, L_{\kappa+1}\rangle$ to code the truth predicate of $L_\kappa$ (which is an element of $L_{\kappa+1}$) into the continuum pattern below $\kappa$. The first-order part $L_\kappa[G]$ of this extension cannot be a forcing extension of ${\rm HOD}^{L_\kappa[G]}=L_\kappa$ (by the weak homogeneity of the coding forcing), because the truth predicate of $L_\kappa$ is definable there and this can be recovered via the forcing relation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
While the definition of the partial order $\mathbb P$ is fairly involved, the
&lt;em&gt;stability predicate&lt;/em&gt; $S$ simply codes the elementarity relations
between sufficiently nice initial segments $H_\alpha$ (the collection of all sets with transitive closure of size less than $\alpha$) of $V$. Given a
natural number $n\geq 1$, call a cardinal $\alpha$ $n$-&lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; if
it is a strong limit cardinal and $H_\alpha$ satisfies
$\Sigma_n$-collection. The predicate $S$ consists of
triples $(n,\alpha,\beta)$ such that $n\geq 1$, $\alpha$ and $\beta$
are $n$-good cardinals and $H_\alpha\prec_{\Sigma_n}H_\beta$. We will denote by $S_n$ the $n$-th slice of the stability predicate $S$, namely $S_n=\{(\alpha,\beta)\mid (n,\alpha,\beta)\in S\}$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Clearly the stable core $L[S]\subseteq{\rm HOD}$, and the first author showed in (missing reference) that
it is consistent that $L[S]$ is smaller than ${\rm HOD}$. The stable core has several nice properties which fail for ${\rm HOD}$ such as that it is partially forcing absolute and, assuming ${\rm GCH}$, is preserved by forcing to code the universe into a real (missing reference)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In order to
motivate the many questions which arise about the stable core let us
briefly discuss the set-theoretic goals of studying inner models.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study of canonical inner models has proved to be one of the most
fruitful directions of modern set-theoretic research. The canonical
inner models, of which Gödel's constructible universe $L$ was the first
example, are built bottom-up by a canonical procedure. The resulting
fine structure of the models leads to regularity properties, such as
the ${\rm GCH}$ and $\square$, and sometimes even absoluteness
properties. But all known canonical inner models are incompatible with
sufficiently large large cardinals, and indeed each such inner model
is very far from the universe in the presence of sufficiently large
large cardinals in the sense, for example, that covering fails and the
large cardinals are not downward absolute.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The inner model ${\rm HOD}$ was introduced by Gödel, who showed that in a
universe of ${\rm ZF}$ it is always a model of ${\rm ZFC}$. But unlike the
constructible universe which also shares this property, ${\rm HOD}$ has
turned out to be highly non-canonical. While $L$ cannot be modified by
forcing, ${\rm HOD}$ can be easily changed by forcing because we can use
forcing to code information into ${\rm HOD}$. For instance, any subset of
the ordinals from $V$ can be made ordinal definable in a set-forcing extension
by coding its characteristic function into the continuum pattern, so
that it becomes an element of the ${\rm HOD}$ of the extension. Indeed, by
coding all of $V$ into the continuum pattern of a class-forcing
extension, Roguski showed that every universe $V$ is the ${\rm HOD}$ of one
of its class-forcing extensions &lt;a href=&quot;#Roguski:HOD&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. Thus, any
consistent set-theoretic property, including all known large cardinals, consistently holds in ${\rm HOD}$. At the same time, the
${\rm HOD}$ of a given universe can be very far from it. It is consistent
that every measurable cardinal is not even weakly compact in ${\rm HOD}$
and that a universe can have a supercompact cardinal which is not even
weakly compact in ${\rm HOD}$
&lt;a href=&quot;#ChengFriedmanHamkins:LargeCardinalsNeedNotBeLargeInHOD&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;. It is
also consistent that ${\rm HOD}$ is wrong about all successor cardinals
&lt;a href=&quot;#CummingsFriedmanGolshani:CollapsingCardinalsHOD&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Does the stable core behave more like the canonical inner models or
more like ${\rm HOD}$? Is there a fine structural version of the stable
core, does it satisfy regularity properties such as the ${\rm GCH}$? Is
there a bound on the large cardinals that are compatible with the stable core? Or, on the other hand, are the large cardinals
downward absolute to the stable core? Can we code information into the
stable core using forcing?&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

In this article, we show the following results about the structure of
the stable core, which answer some of the aforementioned questions as
well as motivate further questions about the structure of the stable
core in the presence of sufficiently large large cardinals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Measurable cardinals are consistent with the stable core.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;:
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt; The stable core of $L[\mu]$, the canonical model for one measurable
  cardinal, is $L[\mu]$. In particular, the stable core can have a measurable cardinal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; If $\vec U=\langle U_\alpha\mid\alpha\in{\rm Ord}\rangle$ is a discrete collection of normal measures, then the stable core of $L[\vec U]$ is $L[\vec U]$. In particular, the stable core can have a discrete proper class of measurable cardinals.
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We can code information into the stable core over $L$ or $L[\mu]$
using forcing.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;:
  Suppose $\mathbb P\in L$ is a forcing notion and $G\subseteq \mathbb P$ is
  $L$-generic. Then there is a further forcing extension $L[G][H]$
  such that $G\in L[S^{L[G][H]}]$ (the universe of the stable core). An analogous result holds for
  $L[\mu]$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
An extension of the coding results shows that the ${\rm GCH}$ can fail
badly in the stable core.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;:
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There is a class-forcing extension of $L$ such that in its stable core the ${\rm GCH}$
  fails at every regular cardinal.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; There is a class-forcing extension of $L[\mu]$ such that in its stable core there is
  a measurable cardinal and the ${\rm GCH}$ fails on a tail of regular
  cardinals.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Measurable cardinals need not be downward absolute to the stable core.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;:
  There is a forcing extension of $L[\mu]$ in which the measurable
  cardinal $\kappa$ of $L[\mu]$ remains measurable, but it is not even
  weakly compact in the stable core.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;

Although we don't know whether the stable core can have a measurable limit of measurables, the stable core has inner models with measurable limits of measurables, and much more. Say that a cardinal $\kappa$ is $1$-&lt;em&gt;measurable&lt;/em&gt;
if it is measurable, and, for $n &lt; \omega$, $(n+1)$-&lt;em&gt;measurable&lt;/em&gt; if it
is measurable and a limit of $n$-measurable cardinals. Write $m_0^\#$ for $0^\#$ and $m_n^\#$ for the minimal mouse which is a sharp for a proper class of $n$-measurable cardinals, namely, an active mouse $\mathcal M$ such that the critical point of the top extender is a limit of $n$-measurable cardinals in $\mathcal M$. Here we mean &lt;em&gt;mouse&lt;/em&gt; in the sense of &lt;a href=&quot;#Mitchell:BeginningInnerModelTheory&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt; (Sections 1 and 2), i.e., a mouse has only total measures on its sequence. The mouse $m_n^{\#}$ can also be construed as a fine structural
mouse with both total and partial extenders (see &lt;a href=&quot;#Zeman:InnerModelsLargeCardinals&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;, Section 4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;:
  For all $n&lt;\omega$, if $m_{n+1}^\#$ exists, then $m_n^\#$ is in the
  stable core.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Moreover, we obtain the following characterization of natural inner
models of the stable core.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;:
  Let $n &lt; \omega$ and suppose that $m_n^\#$ exists. Then whenever
  $$C_1\supseteq C_2\supseteq\ldots\supseteq C_n$$ are class clubs of
  uncountable cardinals such that for every $1 &lt; i\leq n$ and every
  $\gamma \in C_i$,
\[\langle H_\gamma,\in, C_1,\ldots,C_{i-1}\rangle\prec_{\Sigma_1} \langle V,\in,
  C_1,\ldots,C_{i-1}\rangle,\] then $L[C_1,\ldots,C_n]$ is a hyperclass-forcing extension of a (truncated) iterate of $m_n^\#$.
&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;HamkinsReitz:The-set-theoretic-universe-is-not-necessarily-a-forcing-extension-of-HOD&quot;&gt;J. D. Hamkins and J. Reitz, “The set-theoretic universe $V$ is not necessarily a class-forcing extension of HOD,” &lt;i&gt;ArXiv e-prints&lt;/i&gt;, Sep. 2017. Available at: http://jdh.hamkins.org/the-universe-need-not-be-a-class-forcing-extension-of-hod&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Roguski:HOD&quot;&gt;S. Roguski, “Cardinals and iterations of ${\rm HOD}$,” &lt;i&gt;Colloq. Math.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 58, no. 2, pp. 159–161, 1990. Available at: https://doi.org/10.4064/cm-58-2-159-161&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;ChengFriedmanHamkins:LargeCardinalsNeedNotBeLargeInHOD&quot;&gt;Y. Cheng, S.-D. Friedman, and J. D. Hamkins, “Large cardinals need not be large in HOD,” &lt;i&gt;Ann. Pure Appl. Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 166, no. 11, pp. 1186–1198, 2015. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apal.2015.07.004&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;CummingsFriedmanGolshani:CollapsingCardinalsHOD&quot;&gt;J. Cummings, S. D. Friedman, and M. Golshani, “Collapsing the cardinals of HOD,” &lt;i&gt;J. Math. Log.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 15, no. 2, pp. 1550007, 32, 2015. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1142/S0219061315500075&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Mitchell:BeginningInnerModelTheory&quot;&gt;W. J. Mitchell, “Beginning inner model theory,” in &lt;i&gt;Handbook of set theory. Vols. 1, 2, 3&lt;/i&gt;, Springer, Dordrecht, 2010, pp. 1449–1495. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1007/978-1-4020-5764-9_18&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Zeman:InnerModelsLargeCardinals&quot;&gt;M. Zeman, &lt;i&gt;Inner Models and Large Cardinals&lt;/i&gt;. Walter de Gruyter, 2002. Available at: https://books.google.at/books?id=V0bLReBbRDEC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">{% reference page.ref %} The first author introduced the inner model stable core while investigating under what circumstances the universe $V$ is a class forcing extension of the inner model ${\rm HOD}$, the collection of all hereditarily ordinal definable sets {% cite Friedman:StableCore,Friedman:EnrichedStableCore %}. He showed in {% cite Friedman:StableCore %} that there is a robust $\Delta_2$-definable class $S$ contained in ${\rm HOD}$ such that $V$ is a class-forcing extension of the structure $\langle L[S],\in, S\rangle$, which he called the stable core, by an ${\rm Ord}$-cc class partial order $\mathbb P$ definable from $S$. Indeed, for any inner model $M$, $V$ is a $\mathbb P$-forcing extension of $\langle M[S],\in,S\rangle$, so that in particular, since ${\rm HOD}[S]={\rm HOD}$, $V$ is a $\mathbb P$-forcing extension of $\langle {\rm HOD},\in,S\rangle$. Let's explain the result in more detail for the stable core $L[S]$, noting that exactly the same analysis applies to ${\rm HOD}$. The partial order $\mathbb P$ is definable in $\langle L[S],\in,S\rangle$ and there is a generic filter $G$, meeting all dense sub-classes of $\mathbb P$ definable in $\langle L[S],\in,S\rangle$, such that $V=L[S][G]$. All standard forcing theorems hold for $\mathbb P$ since it has the ${\rm Ord}$-cc. Thus, we get that the forcing relation for $\mathbb P$ is definable in $\langle L[S],\in,S\rangle$ and the forcing extension $\langle V,\in,G\rangle\models{\rm ZFC}$. However, this particular generic filter $G$ is not definable in $V$. To obtain $G$, we first force with an auxiliary forcing $\mathbb Q$ to add a particular class $F$, without adding sets, such that $V=L[F]$. We then show that $G$ is definable from $F$ and $F$ is in turn definable in the structure $\langle L[S][G], \in, S,G\rangle$, so that $L[S][G]=V$. This gives a formulation of the result as a ${\rm ZFC}$-theorem because we can say (using the definitions of $\mathbb P$ and $\mathbb Q$) that it is forced by $\mathbb Q$ that $V=L[F]$, where $F$ is $V$-generic for $\mathbb Q$, and (the definition of) $G$ is $\langle L[S],\in,S\rangle$-generic, and finally that $F$ is definable in $\langle L[S][G],\in,S,G\rangle$. Of course, a careful formulation would say that the result holds for all sufficiently large natural numbers $n$, where $n$ bounds the complexity of the formulas used. Without the niceness requirement on $\mathbb P$ that it has the ${\rm Ord}$-cc, there is a much easier construction of a class forcing notion $\mathbb P$, suggested by Woodin, such that $V$ is a class forcing extension of $\langle {\rm HOD},\in, \mathbb P\rangle$. At the same time, some additional predicate must be added to ${\rm HOD}$ in order to realize all of $V$ as a class-forcing extension because, as Hamkins and Reitz observed in {% cite HamkinsReitz:The-set-theoretic-universe-is-not-necessarily-a-forcing-extension-of-HOD %}, it is consistent that $V$ is not a class-forcing extension of ${\rm HOD}$. To construct such a counterexample, we suppose that $\kappa$ is inaccessible in $L$ and force over the Kelley-Morse model $\mathcal L=\langle L_\kappa,\in, L_{\kappa+1}\rangle$ to code the truth predicate of $L_\kappa$ (which is an element of $L_{\kappa+1}$) into the continuum pattern below $\kappa$. The first-order part $L_\kappa[G]$ of this extension cannot be a forcing extension of ${\rm HOD}^{L_\kappa[G]}=L_\kappa$ (by the weak homogeneity of the coding forcing), because the truth predicate of $L_\kappa$ is definable there and this can be recovered via the forcing relation. While the definition of the partial order $\mathbb P$ is fairly involved, the stability predicate $S$ simply codes the elementarity relations between sufficiently nice initial segments $H_\alpha$ (the collection of all sets with transitive closure of size less than $\alpha$) of $V$. Given a natural number $n\geq 1$, call a cardinal $\alpha$ $n$-good if it is a strong limit cardinal and $H_\alpha$ satisfies $\Sigma_n$-collection. The predicate $S$ consists of triples $(n,\alpha,\beta)$ such that $n\geq 1$, $\alpha$ and $\beta$ are $n$-good cardinals and $H_\alpha\prec_{\Sigma_n}H_\beta$. We will denote by $S_n$ the $n$-th slice of the stability predicate $S$, namely $S_n=\{(\alpha,\beta)\mid (n,\alpha,\beta)\in S\}$. Clearly the stable core $L[S]\subseteq{\rm HOD}$, and the first author showed in {% cite Friedman:StableCore %} that it is consistent that $L[S]$ is smaller than ${\rm HOD}$. The stable core has several nice properties which fail for ${\rm HOD}$ such as that it is partially forcing absolute and, assuming ${\rm GCH}$, is preserved by forcing to code the universe into a real {% cite Friedman:StableCore %} In order to motivate the many questions which arise about the stable core let us briefly discuss the set-theoretic goals of studying inner models. The study of canonical inner models has proved to be one of the most fruitful directions of modern set-theoretic research. The canonical inner models, of which Gödel's constructible universe $L$ was the first example, are built bottom-up by a canonical procedure. The resulting fine structure of the models leads to regularity properties, such as the ${\rm GCH}$ and $\square$, and sometimes even absoluteness properties. But all known canonical inner models are incompatible with sufficiently large large cardinals, and indeed each such inner model is very far from the universe in the presence of sufficiently large large cardinals in the sense, for example, that covering fails and the large cardinals are not downward absolute. The inner model ${\rm HOD}$ was introduced by Gödel, who showed that in a universe of ${\rm ZF}$ it is always a model of ${\rm ZFC}$. But unlike the constructible universe which also shares this property, ${\rm HOD}$ has turned out to be highly non-canonical. While $L$ cannot be modified by forcing, ${\rm HOD}$ can be easily changed by forcing because we can use forcing to code information into ${\rm HOD}$. For instance, any subset of the ordinals from $V$ can be made ordinal definable in a set-forcing extension by coding its characteristic function into the continuum pattern, so that it becomes an element of the ${\rm HOD}$ of the extension. Indeed, by coding all of $V$ into the continuum pattern of a class-forcing extension, Roguski showed that every universe $V$ is the ${\rm HOD}$ of one of its class-forcing extensions {% cite Roguski:HOD %}. Thus, any consistent set-theoretic property, including all known large cardinals, consistently holds in ${\rm HOD}$. At the same time, the ${\rm HOD}$ of a given universe can be very far from it. It is consistent that every measurable cardinal is not even weakly compact in ${\rm HOD}$ and that a universe can have a supercompact cardinal which is not even weakly compact in ${\rm HOD}$ {% cite ChengFriedmanHamkins:LargeCardinalsNeedNotBeLargeInHOD %}. It is also consistent that ${\rm HOD}$ is wrong about all successor cardinals {% cite CummingsFriedmanGolshani:CollapsingCardinalsHOD %}. Does the stable core behave more like the canonical inner models or more like ${\rm HOD}$? Is there a fine structural version of the stable core, does it satisfy regularity properties such as the ${\rm GCH}$? Is there a bound on the large cardinals that are compatible with the stable core? Or, on the other hand, are the large cardinals downward absolute to the stable core? Can we code information into the stable core using forcing? In this article, we show the following results about the structure of the stable core, which answer some of the aforementioned questions as well as motivate further questions about the structure of the stable core in the presence of sufficiently large large cardinals. Measurable cardinals are consistent with the stable core. Theorem: The stable core of $L[\mu]$, the canonical model for one measurable cardinal, is $L[\mu]$. In particular, the stable core can have a measurable cardinal. If $\vec U=\langle U_\alpha\mid\alpha\in{\rm Ord}\rangle$ is a discrete collection of normal measures, then the stable core of $L[\vec U]$ is $L[\vec U]$. In particular, the stable core can have a discrete proper class of measurable cardinals. We can code information into the stable core over $L$ or $L[\mu]$ using forcing. Theorem: Suppose $\mathbb P\in L$ is a forcing notion and $G\subseteq \mathbb P$ is $L$-generic. Then there is a further forcing extension $L[G][H]$ such that $G\in L[S^{L[G][H]}]$ (the universe of the stable core). An analogous result holds for $L[\mu]$. An extension of the coding results shows that the ${\rm GCH}$ can fail badly in the stable core. Theorem: There is a class-forcing extension of $L$ such that in its stable core the ${\rm GCH}$ fails at every regular cardinal. There is a class-forcing extension of $L[\mu]$ such that in its stable core there is a measurable cardinal and the ${\rm GCH}$ fails on a tail of regular cardinals. Measurable cardinals need not be downward absolute to the stable core. Theorem: There is a forcing extension of $L[\mu]$ in which the measurable cardinal $\kappa$ of $L[\mu]$ remains measurable, but it is not even weakly compact in the stable core. Although we don't know whether the stable core can have a measurable limit of measurables, the stable core has inner models with measurable limits of measurables, and much more. Say that a cardinal $\kappa$ is $1$-measurable if it is measurable, and, for $n measurable if it is measurable and a limit of $n$-measurable cardinals. Write $m_0^\#$ for $0^\#$ and $m_n^\#$ for the minimal mouse which is a sharp for a proper class of $n$-measurable cardinals, namely, an active mouse $\mathcal M$ such that the critical point of the top extender is a limit of $n$-measurable cardinals in $\mathcal M$. Here we mean mouse in the sense of {% cite Mitchell:BeginningInnerModelTheory %} (Sections 1 and 2), i.e., a mouse has only total measures on its sequence. The mouse $m_n^{\#}$ can also be construed as a fine structural mouse with both total and partial extenders (see {% cite Zeman:InnerModelsLargeCardinals %}, Section 4). Theorem: For all $n Moreover, we obtain the following characterization of natural inner models of the stable core. Theorem: Let $n References {% bibliography --cited %}</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ground model definability in ${\rm ZF}$</title><link href="https://victoriagitman.github.io/talks/2019/10/10/ground-model-definability-in-zf.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ground model definability in ${\rm ZF}$" /><published>2019-10-10T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-10-10T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://victoriagitman.github.io/talks/2019/10/10/ground-model-definability-in-zf</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://victoriagitman.github.io/talks/2019/10/10/ground-model-definability-in-zf.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://jointmathematicsmeetings.org/jmm&quot;&gt;Joint Mathematics Meeting&lt;/a&gt;, special session on 'Choiceless Set Theory and related areas', University of Denver, January 15-16, 2020.&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/ZFGroundModelDefinability.pdf&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Laver, and independently Woodin, showed that a ground model is always definable (with a ground model parameter) in its set-forcing extensions &lt;a href=&quot;#laver:groundmodel&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;#woodin:groundmodel&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. More so, the definition is uniform for all ${\rm ZFC}$-universes: there is a single formula $\varphi(x,y)$ such that whenever $V\models{\rm ZFC}$ and $V[G]$ is a set-forcing extension of $V$ by a poset $\mathbb P\in V$ of size $|\mathbb P|^V=\gamma$, then $V$ is defined in $V[G]$ by $\varphi(x,P^V(\delta))$ with $\delta=(\gamma^+)^V(=(\gamma^+)^{V[G]})$. Let's explain what the formula $\varphi(x,P^V(\delta))$ says. Let ${\rm Z}^*$ be a certain finite fragment of ${\rm ZFC}$. We will say that a transitive model $M\in V[G]$ is &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; if $M\models {\rm Z}^*$, $P^M(\delta)=P^V(\delta)$ and $(\delta^+)^M=(\delta^+)^{V[G]}$. The formula $\varphi(x,P^V(\delta))$ then holds of a set $x$ if $x$ is an element of a good model $M$ of height $\lambda\gg\delta$ such that $V[G]_\lambda\models {\rm Z}^*$ and the pair $M\subseteq V[G]_\lambda$ has the $\delta$-cover and $\delta$-approximation properties (we will explain what those are in a moment). Here is the reason the formula works. Any forcing extension by a poset of size less than a regular cardinal $\delta$ has the property that there are unboundedly many ordinals $\lambda$ such that both $V_\lambda$ and $V[G]_\lambda$ satisfy ${\rm Z}^*$ and the pair $V_\lambda\subseteq V[G]_\lambda$ has the $\delta$-cover and $\delta$-approximation properties. Also, if there is a good model $M$ of height $\lambda$ with $P^M(\delta)=P^V(\delta)$ and $(\delta^+)^M=(\delta^+)^{V[G]}$ such that that pair $M\subseteq V[G]_\delta\models {\rm Z}^*$ has the the $\delta$-cover and $\delta$-approximation properties, then the model is unique. Hence such a model $M$ of height $\lambda$ can only be $V_\lambda$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The notions of $\delta$-cover and $\delta$-approximation properties are due to Hamkins &lt;a href=&quot;#hamkins:coverandapproximations&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;. Suppose that $V\subseteq W$ are transitive models of (some fragment of) ${\rm ZFC}$ and $\delta$ is a cardinal in $W$.
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
The pair $V\subseteq W$ satisfies the &lt;em&gt;$\delta$-cover property&lt;/em&gt; if for every $A\in W$ with $A\subseteq V$ and $|A|^W&lt;\delta$, there is $B\in V$ with $A\subseteq B$ and $|B|^V&lt;\delta$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The pair $V\subseteq W$ satisfies the &lt;em&gt;$\delta$-approximation property&lt;/em&gt; if whenever $A\in W$ with $A\subseteq V$ and $A\cap a\in V$ for every $a$ of size less than $\delta$ in $V$, then $A\in V$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Because the existence of cardinalities is fundamental to the definition of the cover and approximation properties, these notions appear to rely  essentially on the axiom of choice. Therefore proofs of ground model definability based on these properties cannot be easily modified to work in the absence of choice. It is not known yet whether ground definability holds in ${\rm ZF}$. There are partial positive results and no known counterexamples.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Tom Johnstone, we adapted the approximation and cover properties arguments to show that for a cardinal $\delta$, uniform ground model definability holds in models of ${\rm ZF}+{\rm DC}_\delta$ for posets admitting a gap at $\delta$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;: There is a single formula $\varphi(x,y)$ such that whenever $V\models{\rm ZF}+{\rm DC}_\delta$ and $V[G]$ is a set-forcing extension of $V$ by a poset $\mathbb P$ admitting a gap at $\delta$ in $V$, then $V$ is defined in $V[G]$ by $\varphi(x,P^V(\delta))$.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
A poset is said to &lt;em&gt;admit a gap at $\delta$&lt;/em&gt; if it has the form $\mathbb R*\dot{\mathbb Q}$ where $\mathbb R$ is a non-trivial forcing of size less than $\delta$ and it is forced by $\mathbb R$ that is $\dot{\mathbb Q}$ is $\leq\delta$-strategically closed. The $\delta$-dependent choice principle ${\rm DC}_\delta$, introduced by Lévy, allows us to make $\delta$-many dependent choices along any relation without terminal nodes. It asserts that for any non-empty set $S$ and any binary relation  $R$, if for each sequence $s\in S^{\lt\delta}$ there is a $y\in S$ such that $s$ is $R$ related $y$, then there is a function $f:\delta\to S$ such that $f\upharpoonright\alpha \,R\, f(\alpha)$ for all $\alpha&lt;\delta$. The principle ${\rm DC}_\delta$ is robust for forcing with posets admitting a gap at $\delta$ because they preserve it to the forcing extension (see &lt;a href=&quot;#gitmanjohnstone:groundmodels&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
A very different recent partial result on ${\rm ZF}$-ground model definability is due to Usuba &lt;a href=&quot;#Usuba:ZFGroundModelDefinability&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;. Usuba showed that if a ${\rm ZF}$-universe has a proper class of Löwenheim-Skolem cardinals, a notion which he introduces, then uniform ground model definability holds for it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;: There is a single formula $\varphi(x,y)$ such that whenever $V$ is a model of ${\rm ZF}$ with a proper class of Löwenheim-Skolem cardinals and $V[G]$ is a set-forcing extension of $V$ by a poset $\mathbb P\in V_\kappa$ for a Lowenheim-Skolem cardinal $\kappa$, then $V$ is defined in the extension $V[G]$ by $\varphi(x,V_\kappa)$.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;

Usuba's proof is another modification of the arguments using cover and approximation, where he replaces the notion of cardinality by a rough measure on sets, defining for a set $x$ that the measure $|\!|x|\!|$ is the least ordinal $\alpha$ such that there is a surjection from $V_\alpha$ onto $x$.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;p&gt;
An uncountable cardinal $\kappa$ is a &lt;em&gt;Löwenheim-Skolem&lt;/em&gt; (${\rm LS}$) &lt;em&gt;cardinal&lt;/em&gt; if for every $\gamma&lt;\kappa\leq\alpha$ and $x\in V_\alpha$, there is $\beta&gt;\alpha$ and an elementary $X\prec V_\beta$ such that
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$V_\gamma\subseteq X$,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$x\in X$,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the transitive collapse of $X$ belongs to $V_\kappa$,&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;$(X\cap V_\alpha)^{V_\gamma}\subseteq X$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
In a model of ${\rm ZFC}$, the ${\rm LS}$ cardinals are precisely the $\beth$-fixed point cardinals, and so in particular there are proper class many ${\rm LS}$ cardinals. Let us say, following Woodin, that an uncountable cardinal $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;supercompact&lt;/em&gt; in a model of ${\rm ZF}$ if for every $\alpha\geq\kappa$, there is $\beta\geq\alpha$, a transitive set $N$ and an elementary embedding $j:V_\beta\to N$ such that the critical point of $j$ is $\kappa$, $\alpha &lt; j(\kappa)$, and $N^{V_\alpha}\subseteq N$. It is not difficult to see that every supercompact cardinal is an ${\rm LS}$ cardinal. So, for example, models of ${\rm ZF}$ with a proper class of supercompact cardinals satisfy uniform ground model definability. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The existence of ${\rm LS}$ cardinals is absolute throughout the generic multiverse &lt;a href=&quot;#Usuba:ZFGroundModelDefinability&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;. It follows that if we can force choice over a ${\rm ZF}$-universe, then since its forcing extension has a proper class of ${\rm LS}$ cardinals, it must have a proper class of ${\rm LS}$ cardinals as well. Thus, in particular, ground model definability holds for any ${\rm ZF}$-universe, such as $L(\mathbb R)$, over which we can force the axiom of choice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
At the same time, it is known that there are ${\rm ZF}$ universes without any ${\rm LS}$-cardinals. Let's explain how. Usuba showed that if $\kappa$ is an ${\rm LS}$-cardinal, then the club filter on $\kappa^+$ must be $\kappa$-complete &lt;a href=&quot;#Usuba:ZFGroundModelDefinability&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;. Asaf Karagila showed that every model $V$ of ${\rm ZFC}$ satisfying ${\rm GCH}$ has an extension to a model of ${\rm ZF}$ with the same cofinalities in which the club filter is not $\sigma$-complete on every regular cardinal $\kappa$ &lt;a href=&quot;#karagila:Fodor&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;. This model cannot have any ${\rm LS}$ cardinals because if $\kappa$ in it was an ${\rm LS}$-cardinal, then $\kappa^+$ would be a regular cardinal (since cofinalities from $V$ are preserved) with a $\kappa$-complete club filter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
One important consequence of uniform ground model definability is that it makes it possible to define in a first-order way the collection of all grounds of a ${\rm ZFC}$-universe. A priori this is a collection of classes, a second-order notion, but using ground model definability we can write down a first-order formula $\psi(x,y)$ such that for every set $a$, the class $W_a=\{x\mid \psi(x,a)\}$ is a ground of $V$ and for every $W$ ground of $V$, there is a set $a$ such that $W=W_a$. The first-order definability of the collection of grounds makes it possible to study their structure in ${\rm ZFC}$. This has led to the very fruitful subject of set-theoretic geology, initiated by Fuchs, Hamkins, and Reitz, which explores the structure of grounds of a set-theoretic universe. Ground model definability for ${\rm ZF}$ would allow us to extend the same analysis to ${\rm ZF}$-universes, and Usuba's theorem has now made such an analysis possible for a large collection of models, namely those with a proper class of ${\rm LS}$ cardinals. 

We will have to wait to find out whether ground definability holds fully in ${\rm ZF}$.

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;laver:groundmodel&quot;&gt;R. Laver, “Certain very large cardinals are not created in small forcing
              extensions,” &lt;i&gt;Ann. Pure Appl. Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 149, no. 1-3, pp. 1–6, 2007. Available at: http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.apal.2007.07.002&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;woodin:groundmodel&quot;&gt;H. Woodin, “Recent developments on Cantor’s Continuum Hypothesis,” in &lt;i&gt;Proceedings of the continuum in Philosophy and Mathematics&lt;/i&gt;, 2004. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;hamkins:coverandapproximations&quot;&gt;J. D. Hamkins, “Extensions with the approximation and cover properties have no
              new large cardinals,” &lt;i&gt;Fund. Math.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 180, no. 3, pp. 257–277, 2003. Available at: http://dx.doi.org/10.4064/fm180-3-4&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;gitmanjohnstone:groundmodels&quot;&gt;V. Gitman and T. A. Johnstone, “On ground model definability,” in &lt;i&gt;Infinity, Computability, and Metamathematics: Festschrift in honour of the 60th birthdays of Peter Koepke and Philip Welch&lt;/i&gt;, London, GB: College publications, 2014. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Usuba:ZFGroundModelDefinability&quot;&gt;T. Usuba, “Choiceless Löwenheim-Skolem property and uniform definability of grounds,” &lt;i&gt;Manuscript&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;karagila:Fodor&quot;&gt;A. Karagila, “Fodor’s lemma can fail everywhere,” &lt;i&gt;Acta Math. Hungar.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 154, no. 1, pp. 231–242, 2018. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1007/s10474-017-0768-5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the Joint Mathematics Meeting, special session on 'Choiceless Set Theory and related areas', University of Denver, January 15-16, 2020.Slides</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Toy multiverses of set theory</title><link href="https://victoriagitman.github.io/talks/2019/07/17/toy-multiverses-of-set-theory.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Toy multiverses of set theory" /><published>2019-07-17T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-17T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://victoriagitman.github.io/talks/2019/07/17/toy-multiverses-of-set-theory</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://victoriagitman.github.io/talks/2019/07/17/toy-multiverses-of-set-theory.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://workshop2019.forcing-project.com/&quot;&gt;Philosophy of Set Theory and Foundations workshop&lt;/a&gt;, University of Konstanz, August 1, 2019.&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/files/toyMultiverses.pdf&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the early 20th century, optimism ran high that a formal development of mathematics through first-order logic within appropriate axiom systems would set up mathematical knowledge as incontrovertible truth. With the introdution of set theory, all mathematics could now be unified within a single field whose fundamental properties were codified by the Zermelo-Fraenkel axioms ${\rm ZFC}$. But already within a few decades, discoveries were made which suggested that the concept of set was prone to relativity. Löwenheim and Skolem showed that if there is a model of ${\rm ZFC}$, then there is a countable model of ${\rm ZFC}$. This countable model would, of course, think that its reals are uncountable, demonstrating the non-absoluteness of countability. Gödel proved the Completeness Theorem, an immediate consequences of which was the existence of nonstandard models of set theory, even with nonstandard natural numbers, demonstrating the non-absoluteness of well-foundedness. Soon afterwards, Gödel's First Incompleteness Theorem showed the general limitations inherent in formal method: no computable theory extending ${\rm ZFC}$ could decide the truth of all set theoretic assertions. In the next few decades came forcing, large cardinals, canonical inner models, and a model theoretic treatment of ${\rm ZFC}$. Set theory ever since has indisputably been the study of a multiverse of universes each instantiating its own concept of set. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cohen's technique of forcing showed how to extend a given universe of sets to a larger universe satisfying a desired list of properties. Forcing could be used to construct universes in which the continuum was any cardinal of uncountable cofinality (including singular cardinals), indeed the continuum function on the regular cardinals could be made to satisfy any desired pattern (modulo a few necessary restrictions). There could be universes with or without a Suslin line, universes with non-constructible reals, universes whose cardinal characteristics had different values and different relationships.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the same time, set theorists started exploring the consistency strength hierarchy of large cardinal axioms asserting existence of improbably large infinite objects. Other set theoretic assertions, no matter how unrelated to large cardinals, inevitably fell somewhere inside the hierarchy. Set theorists could now combine forcing with large cardinals to produce universes in which large cardinals were compatible with other desired properties. Many of the larger large cardinals implied that the universe had transitive sub-universes (inner models) into which it would elementarily embed. Such sub-universes, obtained from large cardinals or through other considerations, joined the menagerie of mathematical worlds populating the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In yet another direction, motivated by Godel's construction of $L$, set theorists began exploring how to build ever more sophisticated canonical inner models, universes built bottom-up from a recipe specifying what kind of sets should exists. &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Finally, a model theoretic treatment of ${\rm ZFC}$ produced some unexpected results. Given two models $M$ and $N$ of ${\rm ZFC}$, let us say that $N$ is an &lt;em&gt;end-extension&lt;/em&gt; of $M$ if $M$ is transitive in $N$, let us say that $N$ is a &lt;em&gt;top-extension&lt;/em&gt; of $M$ if every element of $N\setminus M$ has higher rank than all ordinals of $M$. Keisler and Morley showed that every countable model of ${\rm ZFC}$ has a proper elementary top-extension (Keisler-Morley Extension Theorem &lt;a href=&quot;#keislermorley:topextensions&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;). Thus, any countable model could be grown in height without changing its theory. Barwise showed that every countable model of ${\rm ZFC}$ has an end-extension to a model of $V=L$ (Barwise Extension Theorem &lt;a href=&quot;#Barwise:extensionTheorem&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;). Thus, sets could become constructible in a larger universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What does set theoretic practice tell us about the nature of sets? Is there the one true universe of sets, the mathematical world in which all mathematics lives, but our epistemic limitations have so far prevented us from understanding its structure? Or is there simply no one true universe, and instead the multiverse of universes encountered by set theorists is the true mathematical reality?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Universist position in the philosophy of set theory asserts that there is the one true universe of sets. Incompleteness is simply a by-product of formal methods we are forced to use to investigate mathematics, not an indication of some inherent relativity in the nature of sets. After all, in spite of a plethora of nonstandard models of arithmetic, most mathematicians would agree that the natural numbers is the only true model of arithmetic. The Peano Axioms, actually do a rather excellent job of capturing the fundamental properties of natural numbers, they are bound by the incompleteness phenomena but number theorists don't often run into statements independent of them. This certainty with regards to number theory comes from the deep intuition we believe we hold about the nature of natural numbers. The goal of set theory should then be to obtain the same deep intuition about the nature of sets so that ${\rm ZFC}$ can be extended to a theory deciding most of the more significant properties of sets. Woodin for instance believes that such a theory will come from a construction of a sufficiently sophisticated canonical inner model compatible with all known large cardinals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Multiversist position in the philosophy of set theory asserts that there is simply no one true universe of sets. All universes of sets discovered by set theorists: forcing extensions, canonical and non-canonical inner models, models with and without large cardinals, have equal ontological status. They all populate the multiverse of mathematical worlds, each instantiating its own equally valid concept of set. The Multiversist position splits along the lines of just how non-absolute should the notion of set be under this view. Can the multiverse contain models of different heights? Are ill-founded models allowed? The Radical Multiversist position, espoused most notably by Hamkins, asserts that all these models belong in the multiverse. Indeed, once you adapt the position that there is no absolute set theoretic background, no background aught to be better than any other and in fact each should be as bad as the next in the following sense. In the Hamkins perspective each universe in the multiverse will be seen to be countable and ill-founded from the perspective of a &lt;em&gt;better&lt;/em&gt; universe. In particular, under this view the universist is mistaken even about the nature of the natural numbers. The Hamkins position is captured by his &lt;em&gt;Multiverse Axioms&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Realizability&lt;/strong&gt;: If $M$ is a universe and $N$ is a definable class in $M$ such that $M$ believes that $N\models{\rm ZFC}$, then $N$ is a universe. (This includes set models, inner models, will-founded models, etc.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Forcing Extension&lt;/strong&gt;: If $M$ is a universe and $\mathbb P\in M$ is a forcing notion, then there is a universe $M[G]$ where $G\subseteq\mathbb P$ is $M$-generic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Class Forcing Extension&lt;/strong&gt;: If $M$ is a universe  and $\mathbb P$ is a definable ${\rm ZFC}$-preserving forcing notion in $M$, then there is a universe $M[G]$ where $G\subseteq \mathbb P$ is $V$-generic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reflection&lt;/strong&gt;: If $M$ is a universe, then there is a universe $N$ such that $M\prec V^N_\theta\prec N$ for some rank initial segment $V^N_\theta$ of $N$. (Recall the Keisler-Morley Extension Theorem.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Countability&lt;/strong&gt;: Every universe $M$ is a countable set in another universe $N$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Well-founded Mirage&lt;/strong&gt;: Every universe $M$ is a set in another universe $N$ which thinks that $\mathbb N^M$ is ill-founded.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Reverse Embedding&lt;/strong&gt;: If $M$ is a universe and $j:M\to N$ is an elementary embedding definable in $M$, then there is a universe $M^*$ and an elementary embedding $j^*:M^*\to M$ definable in $M^*$ such that $j=j^*(j^*)$. (Every elementary embedding has already been iterated many times.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Absorbtion into $L$&lt;/strong&gt;: Every universe $M$ is a transitive set in another universe $N$ satisfying $V=L$. (This is stronger than the Barwise Extension Theorem.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A way to investigate the viability of a collection of multiverse axioms, without coming up with a formal background beyond ${\rm ZFC}$, is by considering toy multiverses of ${\rm ZFC}$ models. Assuming that ${\rm ZFC}$ is consistent, a toy multiverse is some set collection of models of ${\rm ZFC}$. Does a given collection of multiverse axioms have a toy multiverse, does it have a &lt;em&gt;natural&lt;/em&gt; toy multiverse? With Hamkins, we showed that his Multiverse Axioms, radical as their assertions may seem, have a very natural toy multiverse, namely the collection of all countable computably saturated models &lt;a href=&quot;#multiverse:gitmanhamkins&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;. In fact, every model in any toy multiverse satisfying the Hamkins Multiverse Axioms must be computably saturated because every model of ${\rm ZFC}$ that is an element of a model of ${\rm ZFC}$ with an ill-founded $\omega$ is computably saturated (see the previous &lt;a href=&quot;/research/2019/06/04/some-cute-observations-about-computably-saturated-models/&quot;&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a recent joint work with Godziszewski, Meadows, and Williams, we consider various weakenings of the Hamkins Multiverse Axioms that have toy multiverses not consisting entirely of computably saturated models. First, we consider the Hamkins Multiverse Axioms with a weak version of well-founded mirage which asserts that every universe in the multiverse is merely ill-founded, not necessarily at $\omega$, from the perspective of a better universe. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Weak well-founded mirage&lt;/strong&gt;: Every universe $M$ is a set in another universe which thinks that its membership relation is ill-founded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recall that if there is a transitive model of ${\rm ZFC}$, then the &lt;em&gt;Cohen-Shepherdson model $L_\alpha$&lt;/em&gt; is the minimum transitive model of ${\rm ZFC}$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;: (G., Godziszewki, Meadows, Williams) The collection in $L_\alpha$ of all models $M$ such that $L_\alpha$ thinks that $M$ is a countable model of ${\rm ZFC}$ satisfies:
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Realizability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Set Forcing and Class Forcing Extension&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Countability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Weak Well-founded Mirage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next we consider weakening the axioms to the so-called covering versions, where instead of demanding that a universe be a set inside another universe, we ask that each universe has, a &lt;em&gt;cover&lt;/em&gt;, an end-extension that is a set in a better universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Covering Countability&lt;/strong&gt;: For every universe $M$, there is a universe $N$ and a countable set $A\in N$ with $M\subseteq A$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Covering Well-founded Mirage&lt;/strong&gt;: For every universe $M$, there is a universe $N$ and a model $M^*\in N$ end-extending $M$ such that $N$ thinks that $\mathbb N^{M^*}$ is ill-founded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Covering Absorbtion into $L$&lt;/strong&gt;: For every universe $M$, there is a universe $N\models{\rm ZFC}+V=L$ and a model $M^*\in N$ end-extending $M$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;: (G., Godziszewki, Meadows, Williams) There is a toy multiverse, not all of whose models are computably saturated, satisfying:
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Realizability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Forcing Extension&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Class Forcing Extension for ${\rm Ord}$-cc forcing&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Covering Countability&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Covering Well-founded Mirage&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Covering Absorbtion into $L$&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I purposely didn't tell you what my philosophical position is on all of this. I will leave it up to the reader to guess.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;keislermorley:topextensions&quot;&gt;H. J. Keisler and M. Morley, “Elementary extensions of models of set theory,” &lt;i&gt;Israel J. Math.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 6, pp. 49–65, 1968. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Barwise:extensionTheorem&quot;&gt;J. Barwise, “Infinitary methods in the model theory of set theory,” in &lt;i&gt;Logic Colloquium ’69 (Proc. Summer School and
              Colloq., Manchester, 1969)&lt;/i&gt;, North-Holland, Amsterdam, 1971, pp. 53–66. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;multiverse:gitmanhamkins&quot;&gt;V. Gitman and J. D. Hamkins, “A natural model of the multiverse axioms,” &lt;i&gt;Notre Dame J. Form. Log.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 51, no. 4, pp. 475–484, 2010. Available at: http://dx.doi.org/10.1215/00294527-2010-030&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the Philosophy of Set Theory and Foundations workshop, University of Konstanz, August 1, 2019.Slides</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Computably saturated models of ZFC</title><link href="https://victoriagitman.github.io/research/2019/07/16/computably-saturated-models-of-zfc.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Computably saturated models of ZFC" /><published>2019-07-16T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-07-16T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://victoriagitman.github.io/research/2019/07/16/computably-saturated-models-of-zfc</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://victoriagitman.github.io/research/2019/07/16/computably-saturated-models-of-zfc.html">&lt;p&gt;
Let $\mathcal L$ be any computable first-order language. A type $p(\bar x,\bar y)$ in $\mathcal L$ is said to be &lt;em&gt;computable&lt;/em&gt; if the collection of Gödel codes of the formulas in the type $$\{\ulcorner \varphi\urcorner\mid \varphi\in p(\bar x,\bar y)\}$$ is a computable set. A model $M$ of $\mathcal L$ is said to be &lt;em&gt;computably saturated&lt;/em&gt; if for every tuple $\bar a\in M$ and every computable type $p(\bar x,\bar y)$, whenever $p(\bar x,\bar a)$ is finitely realizable in $M$, then $p(\bar x,\bar a)$ is realized: there is a tuple $\bar b\in M$ such that for every $\varphi\in p(\bar x,\bar y)$, $M\models\varphi(\bar b,\bar a)$. It is not difficult to see that any model $M$ of cardinality $\kappa$ has a computably saturated elementary extension of cardinality $\kappa$. We build the elementary extension in $\omega$-many steps, at each step realizing all finitely realizable computable types with parameters from the previous stage. Observe that any computably saturated model of ${\rm ZFC}$ must have nonstandard natural numbers because it realizes the computable type $$p(x)=\{x&gt;\underbrace{1+\cdots+1}_{n\text{-times}}\mid n\in\mathbb N\}.$$ Computable saturation was introduced in &lt;a href=&quot;#BarwiseSchlipf:recursiveSaturation&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's call a model of ${\rm ZFC}$ &lt;em&gt;$\omega$-nonstandard&lt;/em&gt; if it has nonstandard natural numbers. In the model theory of $\omega$-nonstandard models of ${\rm ZFC}$ (as in the model theory of nonstandard models of ${\rm PA}$) one of the most important notions is the standard system introduced by Friedman in &lt;a href=&quot;#friedman:countableModelsOfSetTheory&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;em&gt;standard system &lt;/em&gt; of an $\omega$-nonstandard model of ${\rm ZFC}$ is a collection of subsets of $\mathbb N$ consisting of the traces of sets in $M$ on the natural numbers: $${\rm SSy}(M)=\{A\cap \mathbb N\mid A\in M\}.$$ Standard systems are clearly Boolean algebras. Standard systems are closed under computability: whenever $A$ is in it and $B$ is computable from $A$, then $B$ is in it. To see this, fix $A\in {\rm SSy}(M)$ and let $B$ be computed from $A$ by a program $p$. The set $A=A^*\cap \mathbb N$ for some $A^*\in M$ and we can assume without loss that $A^*\subseteq\mathbb N^M$. The computation of program $P$ with oracle $A^*$ inside $M$ agrees with the actual computation of $p$ with oracle $A$ on the standard part, which is $B$. In particular, it follows that a standard system has all computable sets, and so computable theories such as ${\rm PA}$ and ${\rm ZFC}$ are (coded) in the standard system. Finally, whenever a set $T$ in a standard system codes an infinite binary tree, the standard system must have some infinite branch through $T$. Such a set $T$ must have come from a set $T^*\in M$, which has to look like a binary tree up to some nonstandard level (because otherwise the true natural numbers would be definable in $M$). So we fix some node $c$ on a nonstandard level of $T^*$ and its predecessors in $T^*$ give a branch through $T$. Observe also if $M$ and $N$ are $\omega$-nonstandard models of ${\rm ZFC}$ such that $\mathbb N^M$ is an initial segment of $\mathbb N^N$, then ${\rm SSy}(M)\subseteq {\rm SSy}(N)$. The reason is that if a set $A\in {\rm SSy}(M)$, then there is a nonstandard natural number $a\in M$ such that the characteristic function of $A$ is coded on the standard part of the binary expansion of $a$, and indeed $M$ has such numbers arbitrarily low above the standard $\mathbb N$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An $\omega$-nonstandard model $M\models{\rm ZFC}$ is said to be &lt;em&gt;${\rm SSy}(M)$-saturated&lt;/em&gt; if for every type $p(\bar x,\bar y)$ (coded) in ${\rm SSy}(M)$, whenever there is $\bar a\in M$ such that $p(\bar x,\bar a)$ is finitely realizable, then $p(\bar x,\bar a)$ is realized. Since ${\rm SSy}(M)$ has all the computable sets, ${\rm SSy}(M)$-saturated models are computably saturated. But the converse holds as well. To see this, fix a type $p(\bar x,\bar y)$ in ${\rm SSy}(M)$ and let $A\in M$ such that $A\cap\mathbb N=\{\ulcorner\varphi\urcorner\mid \varphi\in p(\bar x,\bar y)\}$. Suppose that for $\bar a\in M$, $p(\bar x,\bar a)$ is finitely realizable. Consider the computable type $$p^*(\bar x,\bar y,z)=\{\varphi(\bar x,\bar y)\leftrightarrow \ulcorner\varphi\urcorner\in z\mid \varphi\text{ is a formula}\}.$$ Since $p(\bar x,\bar a)$ is finitely realizable, then so is $p^*(\bar x,\bar a,A)$, but the realization of $p^*(\bar x,\bar a,A)$ also realizes $p(\bar x,\bar a)$. Standard system saturation was introduced by Wilmers in an unpublished 1975 thesis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
We can use standard system saturation to show several key properties of computably saturated models. The standard system of a computably saturated model has all the types of its elements ($\text{tp}^M(\bar a)$ for $\bar a\in M$), and in particular its theory. Suppose $M$ is ${\rm SSy}(M)$-saturated and $\bar a\in M$. We need to show that there is $A\in M$ such that $A\cap \mathbb N=\{\ulcorner\varphi\urcorner\mid M\models\varphi(\bar a)\}$. Consider the computable type $$p(x,\bar y)=\{\varphi(\bar y)\leftrightarrow \ulcorner\varphi\urcorner\in\bar x\mid\varphi\text{ is a formula}\}.$$ Since $M$ has $\Sigma_n$-truth predicates for every true natural number $n$, $p(x,\bar a)$ is finitely realizable in $M$, and thus there is $A\in M$ realizing $p(\bar x,\bar a)$. Once we have that all types are in the standard system, we obtain a remarkable characterization of countable computably saturated models.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;: Countable computably saturated models $M$ and $N$ of ${\rm ZFC}$ are isomorphic if and only if they have the same theory and the same standard system. Indeed, if $\text{tp}^M(\bar a)=\text{tp}^N(\bar b)$, then there is an isomorphism taking $\bar a$ to $\bar b$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Proof&lt;/strong&gt;: This is a back-and-forth argument. Let's extend the partial isomorphism taking $\bar a$ to $\bar b$ one more step. Fix $c\in M$. Then $\text{tp}(c,\bar a)\in {\rm SSy}(M)={\rm SSy}(N)$ and $p(x,\bar y)=\{\varphi(x,\bar y)\mid \varphi\in \text{tp}(x,\bar y)\}$ is finitely realizable in $N$. Thus, by standard system saturation, there is $d\in N$ such that $\text{tp}(c,\bar a)=\text{tp}(d,\bar b)$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Corollary&lt;/strong&gt;: Countable computably saturated models $M\models{\rm ZFC}$ have many automorphisms. Whenever $a,b\in M$ are such that $\text{tp}(a)=\text{tp}(b)$, then there is an automorphism of $M$ taking $a$ to $b$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Computably saturated models of ${\rm ZFC}$ arise naturally as follows. If $M\models{\rm ZFC}$ is an element of an $\omega$-nonstandard model of ${\rm ZFC}$, then $M$ is computably saturated. To see this, fix a computable type $p(\bar x,\bar y)$ and a tuple $\bar a\in M$ such that $p(\bar x,\bar a)$ is finitely realizable. Also fix a set $A\in N$ such that $A\cap \mathbb N$ codes $p(\bar x,\bar y)$. Since $M$ is a set in $N$, $N$ has a truth predicate for $M$, which by absoluteness of satisfaction must be correct for standard formulas. The model $N$ sees, for every true natural number $n$, that $M$ realizes all $\varphi(\bar x,\bar a)$ such that $\ulcorner\varphi\urcorner\in A\cap n$. But then there must be some nonstandard $c\in N$ such that $N$ thinks that $M$ realizes all $\varphi(\bar x,\bar a)$ such that $\ulcorner\varphi\urcorner\in A\cap c$. Any such realization $\bar b$ realizes $p(\bar x,\bar a)$ because $A\cap c$ includes all standard assertions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Here are some other remarkable results about computably saturated models of ${\rm ZFC}$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem:&lt;/strong&gt;: Every computably saturated model $M\models{\rm ZFC}$ has an elementary rank initial segment $V_\alpha^M\prec M$ &lt;a href=&quot;#Ressayre:recursiveSaturation&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proof&lt;/strong&gt;: Consider the computable type $p(x)$ consisting of assertions $$\forall \ulcorner\varphi\urcorner\in\Sigma_n\,\text{Tr}_{\Sigma_n}(\ulcorner\varphi\urcorner)\leftrightarrow \text{Tr}_{\Delta_0}(\ulcorner x\models\varphi\urcorner)$$ for every $n$ (where $\text{Tr}_{\Sigma_n}$ is a $\Sigma_n$-truth predicate) together with the assertion 
&quot;$x$ is a rank initial segment&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The following observation was the key to our theorem with Joel Hamkins that the collection of all countable computably saturated models satisfies the Hamkins Multiverse Axioms &lt;a href=&quot;#multiverse:gitmanhamkins&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem:&lt;/strong&gt; Every countable computably saturated model of ${\rm ZFC}$ has an isomorphic copy of itself as an element which it thinks is countable and $\omega$-nonstandard.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proof:&lt;/strong&gt; Suppose $N$ is countable and computably saturated. The theory $\mathcal T$ of $N$ is in ${\rm SSy}(N)$ and so we can fix a theory $\mathcal T^*\in N$ such that $\mathcal T^*\cap\mathbb N=\mathcal T$. The model $N$ sees that $\mathcal T^*\cap n$ is consistent for every true natural number $n$ and therefore $N$ has some nonstandard natural number $c$ such that it thinks that $\mathcal T^*\cap c$ is consistent. Thus, $N$ has a model of $\mathcal T^*\cap c$. But then $N$ also thinks that $\mathcal T^*\cap c$ also has an $\omega$-nonstandard model $M$. Since $\mathbb N^N$ is an initial segment of $\mathbb N^M$, the two models have the same standard system and by construction they have the same theory. Therefore $M\cong N$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
For the final result I want to mention, let's recall that a &lt;em&gt;truth predicate&lt;/em&gt; for an $\omega$-nonstandard model $M\models{\rm ZFC}$ is a subset $T\subseteq M$ such that in the structure $\langle M,\in,T\rangle$, $T$ satisfies the Tarskian truth conditions for $\langle M,\in\rangle$. In particular, $T$ must be a truth predicate for standard formulas. A set $T\subseteq M$ is a &lt;em&gt;partial truth predicate&lt;/em&gt; if in $\langle M,\in,T\rangle$, there is a nonstandard number $c$ such that $T$ restricted to formulas of length less than $c$ satisfies Tarskian truth conditions.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;: The following are equivalent for a countable $\omega$-nonstandard $M\models{\rm ZFC}$.
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt; $M$ is computably saturated.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; $M$ has a partial truth predicate $T$ such that $\langle M,\in,T\rangle$ satisfies ${\rm ZFC}$ in the extended language.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; $M$ has a truth predicate.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The same result for models of ${\rm PA}$ was shown by Kotlarski, Krajewski, and Lachlan &lt;a href=&quot;#KotlarskiKrajewskiLachlan:fullSatisfactionClass&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;#Lachlan:fullSatisfactionClass&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;. In his dissertation Bartosz Wcisło showed that a truth predicate can be used to define a partial truth predicate preserving ${\rm PA}$ and Michał Godzisgewski observed that with this new result the theorem extends to models of ${\rm ZFC}$. Note that it is impossible to extend condition $(3)$ to say that $\langle M,\in,T\rangle\models{\rm ZFC}$ because any such $M$ would be a model of $\text{Con}({\rm ZFC})$.&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;BarwiseSchlipf:recursiveSaturation&quot;&gt;J. Barwise and J. Schlipf, “An introduction to recursively saturated and resplendent
              models,” &lt;i&gt;J. Symbolic Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 41, no. 2, pp. 531–536, 1976. Available at: https://doi.org/10.2307/2272253&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;friedman:countableModelsOfSetTheory&quot;&gt;H. Friedman, “Countable models of set theories,” in &lt;i&gt;Cambridge Summer School in Mathematical Logic
              (Cambridge, 1971)&lt;/i&gt;, Berlin: Springer, 1973, pp. 539–573. Lecture Notes in Math., Vol. 337. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Ressayre:recursiveSaturation&quot;&gt;J. P. Ressayre, “Introduction aux modèles récursivement saturés,” in &lt;i&gt;Séminaire Général de Logique 1983–1984 (Paris,
              1983–1984)&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 27, Univ. Paris VII, Paris, 1986, pp. 53–72. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;multiverse:gitmanhamkins&quot;&gt;V. Gitman and J. D. Hamkins, “A natural model of the multiverse axioms,” &lt;i&gt;Notre Dame J. Form. Log.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 51, no. 4, pp. 475–484, 2010. Available at: http://dx.doi.org/10.1215/00294527-2010-030&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;KotlarskiKrajewskiLachlan:fullSatisfactionClass&quot;&gt;H. Kotlarski, S. Krajewski, and A. H. and Lachlan, “Construction of satisfaction classes for non-standard models,” &lt;i&gt;Canad. Math. Bull.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 24, no. 3, pp. 283–293, 1981. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Lachlan:fullSatisfactionClass&quot;&gt;A. H. Lachlan, “Full satisfaction classes and recursive saturation,” &lt;i&gt;Canad. Math. Bull.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 24, no. 3, pp. 295–297, 1981. Available at: https://doi.org/10.4153/CMB-1981-046-0&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Let $\mathcal L$ be any computable first-order language. A type $p(\bar x,\bar y)$ in $\mathcal L$ is said to be computable if the collection of Gödel codes of the formulas in the type $$\{\ulcorner \varphi\urcorner\mid \varphi\in p(\bar x,\bar y)\}$$ is a computable set. A model $M$ of $\mathcal L$ is said to be computably saturated if for every tuple $\bar a\in M$ and every computable type $p(\bar x,\bar y)$, whenever $p(\bar x,\bar a)$ is finitely realizable in $M$, then $p(\bar x,\bar a)$ is realized: there is a tuple $\bar b\in M$ such that for every $\varphi\in p(\bar x,\bar y)$, $M\models\varphi(\bar b,\bar a)$. It is not difficult to see that any model $M$ of cardinality $\kappa$ has a computably saturated elementary extension of cardinality $\kappa$. We build the elementary extension in $\omega$-many steps, at each step realizing all finitely realizable computable types with parameters from the previous stage. Observe that any computably saturated model of ${\rm ZFC}$ must have nonstandard natural numbers because it realizes the computable type $$p(x)=\{x&gt;\underbrace{1+\cdots+1}_{n\text{-times}}\mid n\in\mathbb N\}.$$ Computable saturation was introduced in {% cite BarwiseSchlipf:recursiveSaturation %}. Let's call a model of ${\rm ZFC}$ $\omega$-nonstandard if it has nonstandard natural numbers. In the model theory of $\omega$-nonstandard models of ${\rm ZFC}$ (as in the model theory of nonstandard models of ${\rm PA}$) one of the most important notions is the standard system introduced by Friedman in {% cite friedman:countableModelsOfSetTheory %}. The standard system of an $\omega$-nonstandard model of ${\rm ZFC}$ is a collection of subsets of $\mathbb N$ consisting of the traces of sets in $M$ on the natural numbers: $${\rm SSy}(M)=\{A\cap \mathbb N\mid A\in M\}.$$ Standard systems are clearly Boolean algebras. Standard systems are closed under computability: whenever $A$ is in it and $B$ is computable from $A$, then $B$ is in it. To see this, fix $A\in {\rm SSy}(M)$ and let $B$ be computed from $A$ by a program $p$. The set $A=A^*\cap \mathbb N$ for some $A^*\in M$ and we can assume without loss that $A^*\subseteq\mathbb N^M$. The computation of program $P$ with oracle $A^*$ inside $M$ agrees with the actual computation of $p$ with oracle $A$ on the standard part, which is $B$. In particular, it follows that a standard system has all computable sets, and so computable theories such as ${\rm PA}$ and ${\rm ZFC}$ are (coded) in the standard system. Finally, whenever a set $T$ in a standard system codes an infinite binary tree, the standard system must have some infinite branch through $T$. Such a set $T$ must have come from a set $T^*\in M$, which has to look like a binary tree up to some nonstandard level (because otherwise the true natural numbers would be definable in $M$). So we fix some node $c$ on a nonstandard level of $T^*$ and its predecessors in $T^*$ give a branch through $T$. Observe also if $M$ and $N$ are $\omega$-nonstandard models of ${\rm ZFC}$ such that $\mathbb N^M$ is an initial segment of $\mathbb N^N$, then ${\rm SSy}(M)\subseteq {\rm SSy}(N)$. The reason is that if a set $A\in {\rm SSy}(M)$, then there is a nonstandard natural number $a\in M$ such that the characteristic function of $A$ is coded on the standard part of the binary expansion of $a$, and indeed $M$ has such numbers arbitrarily low above the standard $\mathbb N$. An $\omega$-nonstandard model $M\models{\rm ZFC}$ is said to be ${\rm SSy}(M)$-saturated if for every type $p(\bar x,\bar y)$ (coded) in ${\rm SSy}(M)$, whenever there is $\bar a\in M$ such that $p(\bar x,\bar a)$ is finitely realizable, then $p(\bar x,\bar a)$ is realized. Since ${\rm SSy}(M)$ has all the computable sets, ${\rm SSy}(M)$-saturated models are computably saturated. But the converse holds as well. To see this, fix a type $p(\bar x,\bar y)$ in ${\rm SSy}(M)$ and let $A\in M$ such that $A\cap\mathbb N=\{\ulcorner\varphi\urcorner\mid \varphi\in p(\bar x,\bar y)\}$. Suppose that for $\bar a\in M$, $p(\bar x,\bar a)$ is finitely realizable. Consider the computable type $$p^*(\bar x,\bar y,z)=\{\varphi(\bar x,\bar y)\leftrightarrow \ulcorner\varphi\urcorner\in z\mid \varphi\text{ is a formula}\}.$$ Since $p(\bar x,\bar a)$ is finitely realizable, then so is $p^*(\bar x,\bar a,A)$, but the realization of $p^*(\bar x,\bar a,A)$ also realizes $p(\bar x,\bar a)$. Standard system saturation was introduced by Wilmers in an unpublished 1975 thesis. We can use standard system saturation to show several key properties of computably saturated models. The standard system of a computably saturated model has all the types of its elements ($\text{tp}^M(\bar a)$ for $\bar a\in M$), and in particular its theory. Suppose $M$ is ${\rm SSy}(M)$-saturated and $\bar a\in M$. We need to show that there is $A\in M$ such that $A\cap \mathbb N=\{\ulcorner\varphi\urcorner\mid M\models\varphi(\bar a)\}$. Consider the computable type $$p(x,\bar y)=\{\varphi(\bar y)\leftrightarrow \ulcorner\varphi\urcorner\in\bar x\mid\varphi\text{ is a formula}\}.$$ Since $M$ has $\Sigma_n$-truth predicates for every true natural number $n$, $p(x,\bar a)$ is finitely realizable in $M$, and thus there is $A\in M$ realizing $p(\bar x,\bar a)$. Once we have that all types are in the standard system, we obtain a remarkable characterization of countable computably saturated models. Theorem: Countable computably saturated models $M$ and $N$ of ${\rm ZFC}$ are isomorphic if and only if they have the same theory and the same standard system. Indeed, if $\text{tp}^M(\bar a)=\text{tp}^N(\bar b)$, then there is an isomorphism taking $\bar a$ to $\bar b$. Proof: This is a back-and-forth argument. Let's extend the partial isomorphism taking $\bar a$ to $\bar b$ one more step. Fix $c\in M$. Then $\text{tp}(c,\bar a)\in {\rm SSy}(M)={\rm SSy}(N)$ and $p(x,\bar y)=\{\varphi(x,\bar y)\mid \varphi\in \text{tp}(x,\bar y)\}$ is finitely realizable in $N$. Thus, by standard system saturation, there is $d\in N$ such that $\text{tp}(c,\bar a)=\text{tp}(d,\bar b)$. Corollary: Countable computably saturated models $M\models{\rm ZFC}$ have many automorphisms. Whenever $a,b\in M$ are such that $\text{tp}(a)=\text{tp}(b)$, then there is an automorphism of $M$ taking $a$ to $b$. Computably saturated models of ${\rm ZFC}$ arise naturally as follows. If $M\models{\rm ZFC}$ is an element of an $\omega$-nonstandard model of ${\rm ZFC}$, then $M$ is computably saturated. To see this, fix a computable type $p(\bar x,\bar y)$ and a tuple $\bar a\in M$ such that $p(\bar x,\bar a)$ is finitely realizable. Also fix a set $A\in N$ such that $A\cap \mathbb N$ codes $p(\bar x,\bar y)$. Since $M$ is a set in $N$, $N$ has a truth predicate for $M$, which by absoluteness of satisfaction must be correct for standard formulas. The model $N$ sees, for every true natural number $n$, that $M$ realizes all $\varphi(\bar x,\bar a)$ such that $\ulcorner\varphi\urcorner\in A\cap n$. But then there must be some nonstandard $c\in N$ such that $N$ thinks that $M$ realizes all $\varphi(\bar x,\bar a)$ such that $\ulcorner\varphi\urcorner\in A\cap c$. Any such realization $\bar b$ realizes $p(\bar x,\bar a)$ because $A\cap c$ includes all standard assertions. Here are some other remarkable results about computably saturated models of ${\rm ZFC}$. Theorem:: Every computably saturated model $M\models{\rm ZFC}$ has an elementary rank initial segment $V_\alpha^M\prec M$ {% cite Ressayre:recursiveSaturation %}. Proof: Consider the computable type $p(x)$ consisting of assertions $$\forall \ulcorner\varphi\urcorner\in\Sigma_n\,\text{Tr}_{\Sigma_n}(\ulcorner\varphi\urcorner)\leftrightarrow \text{Tr}_{\Delta_0}(\ulcorner x\models\varphi\urcorner)$$ for every $n$ (where $\text{Tr}_{\Sigma_n}$ is a $\Sigma_n$-truth predicate) together with the assertion &quot;$x$ is a rank initial segment&quot;. The following observation was the key to our theorem with Joel Hamkins that the collection of all countable computably saturated models satisfies the Hamkins Multiverse Axioms {% cite multiverse:gitmanhamkins %}. Theorem: Every countable computably saturated model of ${\rm ZFC}$ has an isomorphic copy of itself as an element which it thinks is countable and $\omega$-nonstandard. Proof: Suppose $N$ is countable and computably saturated. The theory $\mathcal T$ of $N$ is in ${\rm SSy}(N)$ and so we can fix a theory $\mathcal T^*\in N$ such that $\mathcal T^*\cap\mathbb N=\mathcal T$. The model $N$ sees that $\mathcal T^*\cap n$ is consistent for every true natural number $n$ and therefore $N$ has some nonstandard natural number $c$ such that it thinks that $\mathcal T^*\cap c$ is consistent. Thus, $N$ has a model of $\mathcal T^*\cap c$. But then $N$ also thinks that $\mathcal T^*\cap c$ also has an $\omega$-nonstandard model $M$. Since $\mathbb N^N$ is an initial segment of $\mathbb N^M$, the two models have the same standard system and by construction they have the same theory. Therefore $M\cong N$. For the final result I want to mention, let's recall that a truth predicate for an $\omega$-nonstandard model $M\models{\rm ZFC}$ is a subset $T\subseteq M$ such that in the structure $\langle M,\in,T\rangle$, $T$ satisfies the Tarskian truth conditions for $\langle M,\in\rangle$. In particular, $T$ must be a truth predicate for standard formulas. A set $T\subseteq M$ is a partial truth predicate if in $\langle M,\in,T\rangle$, there is a nonstandard number $c$ such that $T$ restricted to formulas of length less than $c$ satisfies Tarskian truth conditions. Theorem: The following are equivalent for a countable $\omega$-nonstandard $M\models{\rm ZFC}$. $M$ is computably saturated. $M$ has a partial truth predicate $T$ such that $\langle M,\in,T\rangle$ satisfies ${\rm ZFC}$ in the extended language. $M$ has a truth predicate. The same result for models of ${\rm PA}$ was shown by Kotlarski, Krajewski, and Lachlan {% cite KotlarskiKrajewskiLachlan:fullSatisfactionClass %}, {% cite Lachlan:fullSatisfactionClass %}. In his dissertation Bartosz Wcisło showed that a truth predicate can be used to define a partial truth predicate preserving ${\rm PA}$ and Michał Godzisgewski observed that with this new result the theorem extends to models of ${\rm ZFC}$. Note that it is impossible to extend condition $(3)$ to say that $\langle M,\in,T\rangle\models{\rm ZFC}$ because any such $M$ would be a model of $\text{Con}({\rm ZFC})$. References {% bibliography --cited %}</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Completely ineffable cardinals</title><link href="https://victoriagitman.github.io/research/2019/06/05/completely-ineffable-cardinals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Completely ineffable cardinals" /><published>2019-06-05T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2019-06-05T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://victoriagitman.github.io/research/2019/06/05/completely-ineffable-cardinals</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://victoriagitman.github.io/research/2019/06/05/completely-ineffable-cardinals.html">&lt;p&gt;
I have to admit that I always thought completely ineffable cardinals to be a rather boring technical notion. But I recently came across several equivalent characterizations of complete ineffability that are quite surprising and natural. I also think I stumbled upon an interesting consistency strength implication from completely ineffable cardinals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Completely ineffable cardinals sit atop the ineffability hierarchy. A cardinal $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;ineffable&lt;/em&gt; if every coloring $f:[\kappa]^2\to 2$, coloring pairs of ordinals in 2 colors, has a stationary homogeneous subset. A cardinal $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;$n$-ineffable&lt;/em&gt; if every coloring $f:[\kappa]^n\to 2$ has a stationary homogeneous subset. A cardinal $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;totally ineffable&lt;/em&gt; if it is $n$-ineffable for every $n$. It is not easy to remember the definition of completely ineffable cardinals. A cardinal $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;completely ineffable&lt;/em&gt; if there is a collection $\mathcal R$ of stationary subsets of $\kappa$ closed under supersets such that every coloring $f:[A]^2\to 2$ for $A\in\mathcal R$ has a homogeneous subset in $\mathcal R$. So a completely ineffable $\kappa$ has a set of stationary subsets of $\kappa$ that is closed under the operation of obtaining homogeneous sets for colorings. Completely ineffable cardinals are limits of totally ineffable cardinals. They are also totally indescribable. Completely ineffable cardinals lie relatively low in the large cardinal hierarchy. They are much weaker than Ramsey or even $\omega$-Erdos cardinals, in particular, they can exist in $L$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
I call a transitive model $M\models{\rm ZFC}^-$ (${\rm ZFC}$ with the powerset axiom removed) a &lt;em&gt;weak $\kappa$-model&lt;/em&gt; if it has size $\kappa$ and $\kappa\in M$. Many of the smaller large cardinals, those below a measurable cardinal, have characterizations in terms of existence of elementary embeddings of weak $\kappa$-models. For example, $\kappa$ is weakly compact if (it is inaccessible and) every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ for which there is an elementary embedding $j:M\to N$ with critical point $\kappa$ and $N$ transitive. Equivalently, every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ for which there is an $M$-ultrafilter $U$ on $\kappa$ with a well-founded ultrapower. An &lt;em&gt;$M$-ultrafilter&lt;/em&gt; on $\kappa$ is an ultrafilter on $P(\kappa)^M$, not necessarily from $M$, that is normal for sequences from $M$. A well-founded ultrapower by an $M$-ultrafilter yields an elementary embedding $j:M\to N$ with critical point $\kappa$ and conversely given an elementary embedding $j:M\to N$ with critical point $\kappa$ and $N$ transitive, we have that $$U=\{A\in M\mid A\subseteq\kappa\text{ and }\kappa\in j(A)\}$$ is an $M$-ultrafilter with a well-founded ultrapower (the ultrapower embeds into $N$).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Although we can take the ultrapower by an $M$-ultrafilter, we cannot necessarily iterate the ultrapower construction. If $U$ is not in $M$, how do we define $j(U)$? It turns out that you can do this if the $M$-ultrafilter has the additional property of being weakly amenable, that is being partially internal to $M$. An $M$-ultrafilter $U$ on $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;weakly amenable&lt;/em&gt; if for every $A\in M$ which $M$ thinks has size $\kappa$, $A\cap U\in M$. A well-founded ultrapower $j:M\to N$ by a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter $U$ on $\kappa$ has the property that $P(\kappa)^M=P(\kappa)^N$ and if $j:M\to N$ is any embedding with critical point $\kappa$ such that $P(\kappa)^M=P(\kappa)^N$, then the derived $M$-ultrafilter $U$ (defined as above) is weakly amenable. In my dissertation, I introduced the $\alpha$-iterability hierarchy by exploring iterability properties of weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilters. A cardinal $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;1-iterable&lt;/em&gt; if every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ for which there is a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter with a well-founded ultrapower. More generally, a cardinal $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;$\alpha$-iterable&lt;/em&gt; for $1\leq\alpha\leq\omega_1$ if every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ for which there is a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter with $\alpha$-many well-founded iterated ultrapowers (once you have $\omega_1$-many well-founded iterated ultrapowers, then all the rest are well-founded as well).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The point here is that a $1$-iterable cardinal $\kappa$ is a already a limit of completely ineffable cardinals. To see this, let $M$ be a weak $\kappa$-model with $V_\kappa\in M$ for which there is a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter $U$ with a well-founded ultrapower. First, let's argue that for every $A\in U$ and coloring $f:[A]^2\to 2$ in $M$, there is a homogeneous set for $f$ in $U$. Let $h:M\to K$ be the (possibly ill-founded) ultrapower by $U\times U$, which exists by weak amenability. It is still the case that $A\subseteq \kappa\times\kappa$ is in $U\times U$ if and only if $[\text{id}]_{U\times U}\in h(A)$. Say $h(f)([\text{id}]_{U\times U})=1$. Then $$A=\{(\xi_1,\xi_2)\mid f(\xi_1,\xi_2)=1\}\in U\times U.$$ An easy argument shows that whenever $X\in U\times U$, then there is a set $\bar X\in U$ such that for all $\xi_1&lt;\xi_2$ in $\bar X$, $(\xi_1,\xi_2)\in X$. So $U$ has a set $\bar A$ such that whenever $\xi_1&lt;\xi_2$ are in $\bar A$, then $(\xi_1,\xi_2)\in A$, and so $f(\xi_1,\xi_2)=1$, meaning that $\bar A$ is homogeneous for $f$. Now let $j:M\to N$ be the ultrapower by $U$. We will argue that $\kappa$ is completely ineffable in $N$, and hence by elementarity $M$ thinks that $\kappa$ is a limit of completely ineffable cardinals, but it must be correct about it because it has the true $V_\kappa$. We work now inside $N$. Let $\mathcal R_0$ be the collection of all stationary subsets of $\kappa$. Given $R_\xi$, let $R_{\xi+1}$ be the collection of all sets $A$ in $R_\xi$ such that for every coloring $f:[A]^2\to 2$, $R_\xi$ has a homogeneous set for $A$. At limits take intersections. There must be some $\theta$ such that $R_\theta=R_{\theta+1}$ and if $R_\theta$ is not empty, then by construction it will witness that $\kappa$ is completely ineffable. But this is the case because $U\subseteq R_\xi$ for every $\xi$. Note though that a 1-iterable cardinals may not be completely ineffable itself because it is $\Pi^1_2$-describable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Next, let's talk about one of the game Ramsey cardinals introduced by Holy and Schlicht in &lt;a href=&quot;#HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. First, let's modify the definition of a weak $\kappa$-model to allow &lt;em&gt;non-transitive&lt;/em&gt; $\in$-models. We need this because we want to consider models of size $\kappa$ elementary in large $H_\theta$ (collection of all sets whose transitive closure has size less than $\theta$). Let's call a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ a &lt;em&gt;$\kappa$-model&lt;/em&gt; if it is closed under sequences of length less than $\kappa$. Now fix an inaccessible cardinal $\kappa$ and a regular cardinal $\theta&gt;\kappa$. Consider a two player game of perfect information of length $\omega$ between the challenger and the judge, where at each step $n$ of the game, the challenger plays a $\kappa$-model $M_n\prec H_\theta$ and the judge responds with an $M_n$-ultrafilter $U_n$. Additionally, at each step the challenger needs to make sure that $M_n\subseteq M_{n+1}$ and $M_n,U_n\cap M_n\in M_{n+1}$. The judge wins the game if she is able to play for $\omega$-many steps and otherwise the challenger wins. A cardinal $\kappa$ has the &lt;em&gt;$\omega$-filter property&lt;/em&gt; if the challenger doesn't have a winning strategy for any regular $\theta$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, let's talk about Paul Corazza's &lt;em&gt;Wholeness Axiom&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#corazza:wholenessAxiom&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. Kunen's Inconsistency, which says that there cannot be an elementary embedding $j:V\to V$ can be formalized in several ways. The proof shows that in a model of the second-order Kelley-Morse set theory $(V,\in,\mathcal S)$ there cannot be a class $j\in \mathcal S$ which is an elementary embedding of the first-order part $(V,\in)$. We can also consider expanding the language $\{\in\}$ of set theory by a binary predicate $j$ and considering the theory ${\rm ZFC}$ in this expanded language (with separation and replacement applying to formulas with $j$) together with a scheme of assertions that $j$ is a non-trivial elementary embedding. Kunen's result can also be viewed as asserting that such a theory is inconsistent. What fragment of this theory in the language with $j$ can we salvage? Suppose we just assert that $j$ is non-trivial and elementary. This theory is equiconsistent with ${\rm ZFC}$ because if there is a model of ${\rm ZFC}$, then there is a model of ${\rm ZFC}$ that is computably saturated and hence has plenty of not just elementary embeddings, but automorphisms (see &lt;a href=&quot;/research/2019/06/04/some-cute-observations-about-computably-saturated-models/&quot;&gt;this post&lt;/a&gt;).  How about the theory saying that $j$ is elementary and has a critical point (meaning that some ordinal $\kappa$ is moved and every ordinal 
$\alpha&lt;\kappa$ is fixed)? Corazza calls this theory ${\rm BTEE}$ (basic theory of elementary embeddings). So there is a model $M\models{\rm ZFC}$ and an elementary embedding $j:M\to M$ with critical point $\kappa\in M$. It is easy to see that $\kappa$ must be at least inaccessible in $M$. The argument we gave for 1-iterable cardinals shows that $\kappa$ is $n$-ineffable in $M$ for every natural number $n$ of the metatheory because we can use $j$ to derive an $M$-ultrafilter $U$, which must be weakly amenable, and use product ultrafilters $U^n$ to obtain homogeneous sets. If we additionally assume that $\Sigma_0$-separation holds for formulas with $j$, then it follows that $j$ is amenable to $M$ (for every $a\in M$, $j\upharpoonright a\in M$), which implies that $\kappa$ is at least super $n$-huge in $M$ for every $n\in\omega$. That's quite a jump in consistency strength! It is not known whether assuming full separation for $j$ gives a consistency-wise stronger theory although it is known that weaker and stronger separation have different consequences. Stronger separation implies for example that iterate embeddings $j^n$ are definable in $M$ for every natural number $n\in M$, but this is known to fail with just $\Sigma_0$-separation (the issues here arise for nonstandard $n$).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
The following theorem gives several very different characterizations of completely ineffable cardinals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;:
The following are equivalent to $\kappa$ being completely ineffable.
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
(Nielsen and Welch &lt;a href=&quot;#NielsenWelch:GamesAndRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;) $\kappa$ has the $\omega$-filter property.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;(&lt;a href=&quot;#AbramsonHarringtonKleinbergZwicker:FlippingProperties&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;) In a forcing extension $V[G]$, there is a weakly amenable $V$-ultrafilter and hence a generic elementary embedding $j:V\to N$ with critical point $\kappa$ such that $V_{\kappa+1}^V=V_{\kappa+1}^N$ (it follows that $\kappa^+$ is in the well-founded part of $j$).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; For every regular $\theta&gt;\kappa$, every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M\prec H_\theta$ for which there is a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter $U$ (but the ultrapower may fail to be well-founded).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proof&lt;/strong&gt;:
For equivalence with (1) see &lt;a href=&quot;#NielsenWelch:GamesAndRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;. For equivalence with (2), see the the argument in &lt;a href=&quot;#AbramsonHarringtonKleinbergZwicker:FlippingProperties&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt; for forcing over countable models and instead force over $V$. (3) follows from (2) by playing the game for $\omega$-many steps to build $U$. Finally suppose (3) and let's argue that $\kappa$ is completely ineffable. The same argument which shows that $\kappa$ is completely ineffable in $N$ for a 1-iterable embedding $j:M\to N$ will show that $\kappa$ is completely ineffable in $M$ and this suffices because $M\prec H_\theta$ is correct about complete ineffability.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Completely ineffable cardinals now look very similar to 1-iterable cardinals, but the true analogue is actually the $\omega$-Ramsey cardinals, another game Ramsey cardinal notion of Holy and Schlicht from &lt;a href=&quot;#HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. A cardinal $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;$\omega$-Ramsey&lt;/em&gt; if the challenger has no winning strategy in the games described as above only with the additional condition that in order for the judge to win, after the $\omega$-many steps, $U=\bigcup_{n&lt;\omega}U_n$ has to have a well-founded ultrapower. Equivalently, for every regular $\theta&gt;\kappa$, every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M\prec H_\theta$ for which there is a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter $U$ with a well-founded ultrapower. $\omega$-Ramsey cardinals are between 1-iterable and 2-iterable cardinals in consistency strength.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Theorem&lt;/strong&gt;:
Consistency of a completely ineffable cardinal implies consistency of the theory ${\rm BTEE}$.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Proof&lt;/strong&gt;:
Suppose that $\kappa$ is completely ineffable in a model $V\models{\rm ZFC}$ and move to a forcing extension $V[G]$, in which there is a generic embedding $j:V\to N$ by a weakly amenable $V$-ultrafilter $U$. Since $U$ is weakly amenable, we can iterate the ultrapower construction $\omega$-many times, obtaining iterate embeddings $j_{mn}:N_m\to N_n$ with critical point $\kappa_n$. Let $\mathcal N$ be the direct limit of this system. Standard arguments show that the critical sequence $\{\kappa_n\mid n&lt;\omega\}$ are indiscernibles for $\mathcal N$ even for formulas with parameters $\alpha&lt;\kappa$. (Note that $V_{\kappa+1}^{\mathcal N}=V_{\kappa+1}^V$.) Now let $M$ be generated in $\mathcal N$ by $\alpha&lt;\kappa$ and the critical sequence $\kappa_n$ for $n&lt;\omega$. Define $h:M\to M$ to be the elementary embedding generated by the shift of indiscernibles map taking $\kappa_n$ to $\kappa_{n+1}$. In other words, a term $t(\alpha_0,\ldots,\alpha_n,\kappa_0,\ldots,\kappa_m)$, with $\alpha_i&lt;\kappa$, gets mapped to the term $t(\alpha_0,\ldots\alpha_n,\kappa_1,\ldots,\kappa_{n+1})$. Because the $\kappa_n$ are indiscernibles for formulas with parameters $\alpha&lt;\kappa$, $h$ is a well-defined elementary embedding with critical point $\kappa=\kappa_0$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This squizes the consistency strength of ${\rm BTEE}$ between $n$-ineffable cardinals for every $n$ and completely ineffable cardinals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;P. Holy and P. Schlicht, “A hierarchy of Ramsey-like cardinals.” &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;corazza:wholenessAxiom&quot;&gt;P. Corazza, “The spectrum of elementary embeddings $j\:V\to V$,” &lt;i&gt;Ann. Pure Appl. Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 139, no. 1-3, pp. 327–399, 2006. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apal.2005.06.014&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;NielsenWelch:GamesAndRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;D. S. Nielsen and P. D. Welch, “Games and Ramsey-like cardinals,” &lt;i&gt;Submitted&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;AbramsonHarringtonKleinbergZwicker:FlippingProperties&quot;&gt;F. G. Abramson, L. A. Harrington, E. M. Kleinberg, and W. S. Zwicker, “Flipping properties: a unifying thread in the theory of large
              cardinals,” &lt;i&gt;Ann. Math. Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 12, no. 1, pp. 25–58, 1977. Available at: http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/0003-4843(77)90005-5&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">I have to admit that I always thought completely ineffable cardinals to be a rather boring technical notion. But I recently came across several equivalent characterizations of complete ineffability that are quite surprising and natural. I also think I stumbled upon an interesting consistency strength implication from completely ineffable cardinals. Completely ineffable cardinals sit atop the ineffability hierarchy. A cardinal $\kappa$ is ineffable if every coloring $f:[\kappa]^2\to 2$, coloring pairs of ordinals in 2 colors, has a stationary homogeneous subset. A cardinal $\kappa$ is $n$-ineffable if every coloring $f:[\kappa]^n\to 2$ has a stationary homogeneous subset. A cardinal $\kappa$ is totally ineffable if it is $n$-ineffable for every $n$. It is not easy to remember the definition of completely ineffable cardinals. A cardinal $\kappa$ is completely ineffable if there is a collection $\mathcal R$ of stationary subsets of $\kappa$ closed under supersets such that every coloring $f:[A]^2\to 2$ for $A\in\mathcal R$ has a homogeneous subset in $\mathcal R$. So a completely ineffable $\kappa$ has a set of stationary subsets of $\kappa$ that is closed under the operation of obtaining homogeneous sets for colorings. Completely ineffable cardinals are limits of totally ineffable cardinals. They are also totally indescribable. Completely ineffable cardinals lie relatively low in the large cardinal hierarchy. They are much weaker than Ramsey or even $\omega$-Erdos cardinals, in particular, they can exist in $L$. I call a transitive model $M\models{\rm ZFC}^-$ (${\rm ZFC}$ with the powerset axiom removed) a weak $\kappa$-model if it has size $\kappa$ and $\kappa\in M$. Many of the smaller large cardinals, those below a measurable cardinal, have characterizations in terms of existence of elementary embeddings of weak $\kappa$-models. For example, $\kappa$ is weakly compact if (it is inaccessible and) every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ for which there is an elementary embedding $j:M\to N$ with critical point $\kappa$ and $N$ transitive. Equivalently, every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ for which there is an $M$-ultrafilter $U$ on $\kappa$ with a well-founded ultrapower. An $M$-ultrafilter on $\kappa$ is an ultrafilter on $P(\kappa)^M$, not necessarily from $M$, that is normal for sequences from $M$. A well-founded ultrapower by an $M$-ultrafilter yields an elementary embedding $j:M\to N$ with critical point $\kappa$ and conversely given an elementary embedding $j:M\to N$ with critical point $\kappa$ and $N$ transitive, we have that $$U=\{A\in M\mid A\subseteq\kappa\text{ and }\kappa\in j(A)\}$$ is an $M$-ultrafilter with a well-founded ultrapower (the ultrapower embeds into $N$). Although we can take the ultrapower by an $M$-ultrafilter, we cannot necessarily iterate the ultrapower construction. If $U$ is not in $M$, how do we define $j(U)$? It turns out that you can do this if the $M$-ultrafilter has the additional property of being weakly amenable, that is being partially internal to $M$. An $M$-ultrafilter $U$ on $\kappa$ is weakly amenable if for every $A\in M$ which $M$ thinks has size $\kappa$, $A\cap U\in M$. A well-founded ultrapower $j:M\to N$ by a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter $U$ on $\kappa$ has the property that $P(\kappa)^M=P(\kappa)^N$ and if $j:M\to N$ is any embedding with critical point $\kappa$ such that $P(\kappa)^M=P(\kappa)^N$, then the derived $M$-ultrafilter $U$ (defined as above) is weakly amenable. In my dissertation, I introduced the $\alpha$-iterability hierarchy by exploring iterability properties of weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilters. A cardinal $\kappa$ is 1-iterable if every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ for which there is a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter with a well-founded ultrapower. More generally, a cardinal $\kappa$ is $\alpha$-iterable for $1\leq\alpha\leq\omega_1$ if every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ for which there is a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter with $\alpha$-many well-founded iterated ultrapowers (once you have $\omega_1$-many well-founded iterated ultrapowers, then all the rest are well-founded as well). The point here is that a $1$-iterable cardinal $\kappa$ is a already a limit of completely ineffable cardinals. To see this, let $M$ be a weak $\kappa$-model with $V_\kappa\in M$ for which there is a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter $U$ with a well-founded ultrapower. First, let's argue that for every $A\in U$ and coloring $f:[A]^2\to 2$ in $M$, there is a homogeneous set for $f$ in $U$. Let $h:M\to K$ be the (possibly ill-founded) ultrapower by $U\times U$, which exists by weak amenability. It is still the case that $A\subseteq \kappa\times\kappa$ is in $U\times U$ if and only if $[\text{id}]_{U\times U}\in h(A)$. Say $h(f)([\text{id}]_{U\times U})=1$. Then $$A=\{(\xi_1,\xi_2)\mid f(\xi_1,\xi_2)=1\}\in U\times U.$$ An easy argument shows that whenever $X\in U\times U$, then there is a set $\bar X\in U$ such that for all $\xi_1 Next, let's talk about one of the game Ramsey cardinals introduced by Holy and Schlicht in {% cite HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals %}. First, let's modify the definition of a weak $\kappa$-model to allow non-transitive $\in$-models. We need this because we want to consider models of size $\kappa$ elementary in large $H_\theta$ (collection of all sets whose transitive closure has size less than $\theta$). Let's call a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ a $\kappa$-model if it is closed under sequences of length less than $\kappa$. Now fix an inaccessible cardinal $\kappa$ and a regular cardinal $\theta&gt;\kappa$. Consider a two player game of perfect information of length $\omega$ between the challenger and the judge, where at each step $n$ of the game, the challenger plays a $\kappa$-model $M_n\prec H_\theta$ and the judge responds with an $M_n$-ultrafilter $U_n$. Additionally, at each step the challenger needs to make sure that $M_n\subseteq M_{n+1}$ and $M_n,U_n\cap M_n\in M_{n+1}$. The judge wins the game if she is able to play for $\omega$-many steps and otherwise the challenger wins. A cardinal $\kappa$ has the $\omega$-filter property if the challenger doesn't have a winning strategy for any regular $\theta$. Finally, let's talk about Paul Corazza's Wholeness Axiom {% cite corazza:wholenessAxiom %}. Kunen's Inconsistency, which says that there cannot be an elementary embedding $j:V\to V$ can be formalized in several ways. The proof shows that in a model of the second-order Kelley-Morse set theory $(V,\in,\mathcal S)$ there cannot be a class $j\in \mathcal S$ which is an elementary embedding of the first-order part $(V,\in)$. We can also consider expanding the language $\{\in\}$ of set theory by a binary predicate $j$ and considering the theory ${\rm ZFC}$ in this expanded language (with separation and replacement applying to formulas with $j$) together with a scheme of assertions that $j$ is a non-trivial elementary embedding. Kunen's result can also be viewed as asserting that such a theory is inconsistent. What fragment of this theory in the language with $j$ can we salvage? Suppose we just assert that $j$ is non-trivial and elementary. This theory is equiconsistent with ${\rm ZFC}$ because if there is a model of ${\rm ZFC}$, then there is a model of ${\rm ZFC}$ that is computably saturated and hence has plenty of not just elementary embeddings, but automorphisms (see this post). How about the theory saying that $j$ is elementary and has a critical point (meaning that some ordinal $\kappa$ is moved and every ordinal $\alpha The following theorem gives several very different characterizations of completely ineffable cardinals. Theorem: The following are equivalent to $\kappa$ being completely ineffable. (Nielsen and Welch {% cite NielsenWelch:GamesAndRamseyLikeCardinals %}) $\kappa$ has the $\omega$-filter property. ({% cite AbramsonHarringtonKleinbergZwicker:FlippingProperties %}) In a forcing extension $V[G]$, there is a weakly amenable $V$-ultrafilter and hence a generic elementary embedding $j:V\to N$ with critical point $\kappa$ such that $V_{\kappa+1}^V=V_{\kappa+1}^N$ (it follows that $\kappa^+$ is in the well-founded part of $j$). For every regular $\theta&gt;\kappa$, every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M\prec H_\theta$ for which there is a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter $U$ (but the ultrapower may fail to be well-founded). Proof: For equivalence with (1) see {% cite NielsenWelch:GamesAndRamseyLikeCardinals %}. For equivalence with (2), see the the argument in {% cite AbramsonHarringtonKleinbergZwicker:FlippingProperties %} for forcing over countable models and instead force over $V$. (3) follows from (2) by playing the game for $\omega$-many steps to build $U$. Finally suppose (3) and let's argue that $\kappa$ is completely ineffable. The same argument which shows that $\kappa$ is completely ineffable in $N$ for a 1-iterable embedding $j:M\to N$ will show that $\kappa$ is completely ineffable in $M$ and this suffices because $M\prec H_\theta$ is correct about complete ineffability. Completely ineffable cardinals now look very similar to 1-iterable cardinals, but the true analogue is actually the $\omega$-Ramsey cardinals, another game Ramsey cardinal notion of Holy and Schlicht from {% cite HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals %}. A cardinal $\kappa$ is $\omega$-Ramsey if the challenger has no winning strategy in the games described as above only with the additional condition that in order for the judge to win, after the $\omega$-many steps, $U=\bigcup_{n\kappa$, every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M\prec H_\theta$ for which there is a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter $U$ with a well-founded ultrapower. $\omega$-Ramsey cardinals are between 1-iterable and 2-iterable cardinals in consistency strength. Theorem: Consistency of a completely ineffable cardinal implies consistency of the theory ${\rm BTEE}$. Proof: Suppose that $\kappa$ is completely ineffable in a model $V\models{\rm ZFC}$ and move to a forcing extension $V[G]$, in which there is a generic embedding $j:V\to N$ by a weakly amenable $V$-ultrafilter $U$. Since $U$ is weakly amenable, we can iterate the ultrapower construction $\omega$-many times, obtaining iterate embeddings $j_{mn}:N_m\to N_n$ with critical point $\kappa_n$. Let $\mathcal N$ be the direct limit of this system. Standard arguments show that the critical sequence $\{\kappa_n\mid n This squizes the consistency strength of ${\rm BTEE}$ between $n$-ineffable cardinals for every $n$ and completely ineffable cardinals. References {% bibliography --cited %}</summary></entry></feed>