<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2018-12-05T15:12:07-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Victoria Gitman</title><entry><title type="html">The Stable Core</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/talks/2018/10/15/the-stable-core-Barcelona.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Stable Core" /><published>2018-10-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-10-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/talks/2018/10/15/the-stable-core-Barcelona</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/talks/2018/10/15/the-stable-core-Barcelona.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ub.edu/RSTR2018/&quot;&gt;Reflections on Set Theoretic Reflection Conference&lt;/a&gt;, University of Barcelona, November 16-19, 2018.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract:&lt;/strong&gt; Sy Friedman introduced an inner model, which he called the &lt;em&gt;stable core&lt;/em&gt;, in order to study under what circumstances the universe $V$ is a class forcing extension of ${\rm HOD}$. He showed there is a definable predicate $S$, amenable to ${\rm HOD}$, such that $V$ is a class forcing extension of the structure $\langle {\rm HOD},\in,S\rangle$. Namely, there is an ${\rm ORD}$-cc class partial order $\mathbb P$ definable in $\langle {\rm HOD},\in,S\rangle$ and a generic filter $G\subseteq \mathbb P$ such that ${\rm HOD}[G]=V$, however the filter $G$ itself is not definable over $V$. The predicate $S$, consisting of triples $(\alpha,\beta,n)$ for $\alpha$ and $\beta$ strong limit cardinals and $n\geq 1$ such that $H_\alpha\prec_{\Sigma_n}H_\beta$ and $\Sigma_n$-collection holds in $H_\beta$, codes elementarity relations between nice enough initial segments $H_\alpha$ of $V$. Friedman's argument showed that the information necessary to define $\mathbb P$ is already contained in $S$ so that $V$ is already a class forcing extension of the stable core $\langle L[S],\in,S\rangle$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a joint work with Friedman and Sandra Müller, we investigated the properties of the stable core. We were interested to see whether the stable core is in any sense a canonical inner model, whether it has regularity properties, whether it is consistent with large cardinals, and whether we can code information into it using forcing. We showed that the stable core of $L[\mu]$, the canonical model for a single measurable cardinal, is $L[\mu]$ and therefore measurable cardinals are consistent with the stable core. By coding generic sets into the stable core over $L$ or $L[\mu]$, we showed that there is a generic extension of $L$ in which the ${\rm GCH}$ fails at every regular cardinal in the stable core and there is a generic extension of $L[\mu]$ in which there is a measurable cardinal which is not even weakly compact in the stable core. Our work leaves numerous open questions about the structure of the stable core in the presence of large cardinals beyond a measurable cardinal.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the Reflections on Set Theoretic Reflection Conference, University of Barcelona, November 16-19, 2018.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Stable Core</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/talks/2018/09/11/the-stable-core.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Stable Core" /><published>2018-09-11T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-09-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/talks/2018/09/11/the-stable-core</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/talks/2018/09/11/the-stable-core.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://network2018.forcing-project.com/&quot;&gt;Mathematical Philosophy and Mathematical Practice Conference&lt;/a&gt;, University of Konstanz, September 20, 2018.&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;files/stableCoreTalk.pdf&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sy Friedman introduced an inner model, which he called the &lt;em&gt;Stable Core&lt;/em&gt;, in the process of trying to understand how close the inner model ${\rm HOD}$ can be to the universe $V$ &lt;a href=&quot;#Friedman:stableCore&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. An &lt;em&gt;inner model&lt;/em&gt; is a definable (possibly with parameters) transitive sub-model of the universe satisfying ${\rm ZF}({\rm C})$ and containing all the ordinals. It has long been the goal of the inner model theory program to construct a canonical inner model that is close to $V$ in the presence of very large large cardinals. Canonical inner models are built from the bottom up using absolute rules, and as a result of this construction process satisfy regularity properties, such as the ${\rm GCH}$ and $\square$, and are (generally) unaffected by enlargements of the universe via forcing. Each of these canonical inner models, for example, $L$, $K^{DJ}$, $L[U]$, are close to the universe $V$ in the absence of certain large cardinals, but are very far from a universe having those large cardinals. There are several ways in which we can request that an inner model is close to $V$. The inner model can have some form of covering, agree on large cardinals, or reach the universe $V$ by forcing, so that $V$ is a forcing extension of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The canonical inner models ultimately attempt to generalize Gödel's constructible universe $L$, making it compatible with large cardinals. Another inner model introduced by Gödel, the collection ${\rm HOD}$ of all hereditarily ordinal definable sets, lacks the fine structure of the canonical inner models and therefore their absoluteness and regularity properties, but it makes up for it by being compatible with all known large cardinals and in fact all known set theoretic assertions. This is essentially because using coding any set or class can become ordinal definable in a forcing extension. Every set $A$ is coded by a set of ordinals because we can recover a set from its transitive closure, the transitive closure can be coded by a binary relation on some cardinal, which maps to it via the Mostowski collapse, and a set of pairs of ordinals can in turn be coded by a subset of the cardinal. Now given a subset $A$ of a cardinal $\kappa$, we use forcing to code it into the continuum pattern of the extension, thus making $A$ ordinal definable in the extension. Indeed, in this manner, we can code the entire universe $V$ into the continuum function of a class forcing extension, making $V$ be precisely the ${\rm HOD}$ of this extension $V[G]$ (this was apparently first shown by Roguski &lt;a href=&quot;#Roguski:HOD&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;, the coding idea is due to McAloon). It follows that any universe is the ${\rm HOD}$ of some larger universe, so that ${\rm HOD}$ can satisfy any (believed to be) consistent set-theoretic assertion. It is known that ${\rm HOD}$ can be quite far from $V$. Cheng, Hamkins, and Friedman showed that it is consistent that every measurable cardinal is not even weakly compact in ${\rm HOD}$ and that there can be a supercompact cardinal that is not even weakly compact in ${\rm HOD}$ &lt;a href=&quot;#ChengFriedmanHamkins:LargeCardinalsNeedNotBeLargeInHOD&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;. Cummings, Friedman, and Golshani showed that it is also consistent that $(\alpha^+)^{\rm{HOD}}&lt;\alpha^+$ for every infinite cardinal $\alpha$ (missing reference). Woodin, however has conjectured that in the presence of very large large cardinals ${\rm HOD}$ will be much closer to $V$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In further trying to understand the relationship between ${\rm HOD}$ and $V$, Sy Friedman defined the ordinal definable &lt;em&gt;stability predicate&lt;/em&gt; $S$ and showed that $V$ is a forcing extension of the structure $({\rm HOD},S)$, ${\rm HOD}$ together with a predicate for $S$ &lt;a href=&quot;#Friedman:stableCore&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. The stability predicate $S$ codes the elementarity relations between initial segments $H_\alpha$ of $V$. It consists of triples $(\alpha,\beta,n)$ where $\alpha$ and $\beta$ are strong limit cardinals such that $H_\alpha$ and $H_\beta$ satisfy $\Sigma_n$-Collection and $H_\alpha\prec_{\Sigma_n}H_\beta$. More precisely, Friedman showed that in the structure $({\rm HOD}, S)$, there is a definable class partial order $\mathbb P$ for which there is a generic filter $G\subseteq \mathbb P$ such that ${\rm HOD}[G]=V$. The result is quite subtle in that even though $(V,G)\models{\rm ZFC}$, $G$ is not definable over $V$. Hamkins and Reitz later showed that it is consistent for $V$ to not be a class forcing extension of ${\rm HOD}$, so some additional information is indeed required to make $V$ a forcing extension of ${\rm HOD}$ &lt;a href=&quot;#HamkinsReitz:The-set-theoretic-universe-is-not-necessarily-a-forcing-extension-of-HOD&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Friedman's result showed that $V$ is already a class forcing extension of the structure $(L[S],S)$, which is the Stable Core of the title of the post. Because $S$ is ordinal definable, $L[S]\subseteq {\rm HOD}$, and Friedman showed that consistently $L[S]$ can be smaller than ${\rm HOD}$. It remained unknown whether the new inner model had any regularity properties or whether it was consistent with large cardinals. In a joint work with Sy Friedman and Sandra Müller we establish some further properties that are consistent with the Stable Core &lt;a href=&quot;#FriedmanGitmanMuller:StableCore&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We generalized the recent work of Kennedy, Magidor, and Väänänen on the model $L[{\rm Card}]$ &lt;a href=&quot;#KennedyMagidorVaananen:extendedLogics&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt; to show that $K^{DJ}$ and $L[U]$ are always contained in the Stable Core. Recall that $K^{DJ}$ is the Dodd-Jensen core model below a measurable cardinal and $L[U]$ is the canonical inner model for one measurable cardinal. This shows, in particular, that the Stable Core of $L[U]$ is $L[U]$, so that the Stable Core can have a measurable cardinal. Same techniques, using Kunen's generalization of the $L[U]$ construction, can be used to show that the Stable Core can have a number of measurable cardinals. The next open question is whether the Stable Core can have a measurable limit of measurable cardinals. The question arises because Kennedy, Magidor, Väänänen and Welch (the result is still unpublished) showed that if the universe has a (little more than) a measurable limit of measurable cardinals, then $L[{\rm Card}]$ is a very simple model, in particular, it satisfies the ${\rm GCH}$ and has no measurable cardinals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is relatively easy to code information into the Stable Core over canonical models ($L$, $K^{DJ}$, or $L[U]$) because we can use their definability inside the Stable Core to compare the changes we made to the elementarity relations between the $H_\alpha$ to the original relations. Using a coding along these lines, we show that any set which can be added generically to $L$ (or $L[U]$) can be coded into the Stable Core of a further forcing extension. From this it follows that the ${\rm GCH}$ can fail at every regular cardinal in the Stable Core, that ${\rm CH}$ can fail and Martin's Axiom can hold in the Stable Core, that any cardinal of $L$ can become countable in the Stable Core, etc. We also show that there is a forcing extension of $L[U]$ in which the measurable cardinal $\kappa$ remains measurable but $\kappa$ is not even weakly compact in the Stable Core. Thus, measurable cardinals are not downward absolute to the Stable Core. Because we don't know how to code information into the Stable Core over arbitrary models, these results leave open the general question about what does the Stable Core look like the presence of larger large cardinals such as a measurable limit of measurable cardinals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The open questions here are numerous! Here are a few. It is easy to see using coding that the ${\rm HOD}$ of ${\rm HOD}$ can be smaller than ${\rm HOD}$. Can the Stable Core of the Stable Core be smaller? Is there a bound on the large cardinals compatible with the Stable Core? Or are larger large cardinals downward absolute to the Stable Core? Is the Stable Core of $M_1$, the canonical model for one Woodin cardinal, $M_1$?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Friedman:stableCore&quot;&gt;S.-D. Friedman, “The stable core,” &lt;i&gt;Bull. Symbolic Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 18, no. 2, pp. 261–267, 2012. Available at: https://doi.org/10.2178/bsl/1333560807&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Roguski:HOD&quot;&gt;S. Roguski, “Cardinals and iterations of ${\rm HOD}$,” &lt;i&gt;Colloq. Math.&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 58, no. 2, pp. 159–161, 1990. Available at: https://doi.org/10.4064/cm-58-2-159-161&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;ChengFriedmanHamkins:LargeCardinalsNeedNotBeLargeInHOD&quot;&gt;Y. Cheng, S.-D. Friedman, and J. D. Hamkins, “Large cardinals need not be large in HOD,” &lt;i&gt;Ann. Pure Appl. Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 166, no. 11, pp. 1186–1198, 2015. Available at: https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apal.2015.07.004&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;HamkinsReitz:The-set-theoretic-universe-is-not-necessarily-a-forcing-extension-of-HOD&quot;&gt;J. D. Hamkins and J. Reitz, “The set-theoretic universe $V$ is not necessarily a class-forcing extension of HOD,” &lt;i&gt;ArXiv e-prints&lt;/i&gt;, Sep. 2017. Available at: http://jdh.hamkins.org/the-universe-need-not-be-a-class-forcing-extension-of-hod&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;FriedmanGitmanMuller:StableCore&quot;&gt;S.-D. Friedman, V. Gitman, and S. Müller, “Some properties of the Stable Core,” &lt;i&gt;In preparation&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;KennedyMagidorVaananen:extendedLogics&quot;&gt;J. Kennedy, M. Magidor, and J. Väänänen, “Inner models from extended logics,” &lt;i&gt;In preparation&lt;/i&gt;. Available at: https://www.newton.ac.uk/files/preprints/ni16006.pdf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/vikaKonstanz.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the Mathematical Philosophy and Mathematical Practice Conference, University of Konstanz, September 20, 2018.Slides</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Virtual Vopěnka’s Principle</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/talks/2018/07/15/virtual-Vopenka-principle.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Virtual Vopěnka's Principle" /><published>2018-07-15T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-07-15T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/talks/2018/07/15/virtual-Vopenka-principle</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/talks/2018/07/15/virtual-Vopenka-principle.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www1.maths.leeds.ac.uk/~pmtadb/AccessibleCategories2018/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Accessible categories and their connections Conference&lt;/a&gt;, University of Leeds, July 18, 2018. &lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;files/accessibleGVP.pdf&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: A major segment of modern research in set theory focuses on the topics of forcing and large cardinals. Forcing, introduced by Cohen to show the independence of the Continuum Hypothesis, is a technique for building set-theoretic universes satisfying a desired list of properties. Large cardinal axioms are strong axioms positing the existence of very large infinite objects and (often) elementary embeddings between set-theoretic structures. These axioms form a hierarchy against which the strength of any set-theoretic assertion can be measured. Forcing and large cardinals  interact in a number of unexpected ways. In this talk, I will discuss a relatively new avenue of research involving the notion of virtual large cardinals. Given a large cardinal property $A$ characterized by the existence of elementary embeddings of first-order structures, we say that the property $A$ holds virtually if embeddings on structures from the universe $V$ characterizing $A$ exists in forcing extensions of $V$. Virtual large cardinals are much weaker than their original counterparts, for instance being compatible with the constructible universe $L$. This line of research leads naturally to considering a virtual version of Vopěnka's Principle, a large cardinal principle which has found applications in other branches of math. Virtual Vopěnka's Principle states that given a proper class of first-order structures in a common language, two of them must elementary embed in a forcing extension of $V$. I will discuss the consistency strength of the new principle, which like other virtual large cardinal principles, is compatible with $L$, and some open questions concerning stronger version of the principle, where we demand that the forcing extension in which the embeddings exist preserves a large initial segment of the universe. Parts of this work are joint with Bagaria, Schindler, and Hamkins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/LeedsConfPhoto.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/LeedsBridge.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt;With Joan Bagaria and Andrés Villaveces&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the Accessible categories and their connections Conference, University of Leeds, July 18, 2018. Slides</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Boolean-valued class forcing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publications/2018/05/20/boolean-valued-class-forcing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Boolean-valued class forcing" /><published>2018-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-05-20T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publications/2018/05/20/boolean-valued-class-forcing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publications/2018/05/20/boolean-valued-class-forcing.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;AntosFriedmanGitman:booleanclassforcing&quot;&gt;C. Antos, S. D. Friedman, and V. Gitman, “Boolean-valued class forcing,” &lt;i&gt;Submitted&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two standard approaches to carrying out the forcing construction over a model of ${\rm ZFC}$ set theory: with partial orders or with complete Boolean algebras. The two approaches yield the same forcing extensions because every partial order densely embeds into a complete Boolean algebra, and when a partial order densely embeds into another partial order, the two have the same forcing extensions. Although the partial order construction can be viewed as more straightforward, the complete Boolean algebras approach offers some advantages. For instance, there are theorems about forcing which have no known proofs without the use of Boolean algebras. One such fundamental result is the Intermediate Model Theorem, which states that if a universe $V\models{\rm ZFC}$ and $W\models{\rm ZFC}$ is an intermediate model between $V$ and one of its set-forcing extensions, then $W$ is itself a forcing extension of $V$. The theorem makes a fundamental use of the Axiom of Choice, but a weaker version of it still holds for models of ${\rm ZF}$. If $V\models{\rm ZF}$ and $V[a]\models{\rm ZF}$, with $a\subseteq V$, is an intermediate model between $V$ and one of its set-forcing extensions, then $V[a]$ is itself a set-forcing extension of $V$. Grigorieff in &lt;a href=&quot;#Grigorieff:IntermediateModels&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; attributes the Intermediate Model Theorem to Solovay.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The standard Boolean algebras approach is not available in the context of class forcing because most class partial orders cannot be densely embedded into a sufficiently complete class Boolean algebra. Set forcing uses complete Boolean algebras, those which have suprema for all their subsets, because completeness is required for assigning Boolean values to formulas in the forcing language.  With a class Boolean algebra, which has suprema for all its subsets, we can still define the Boolean values of atomic formulas, but the definition of Boolean values for existential formulas needs to take suprema of subclasses, meaning that we must require a Boolean algebra to have those in order to be able to construct the Boolean-valued model. However, as shown in &lt;a href=&quot;#PeterHolyRegulaKrapfPhilippLuckeAnaNjegomirPhilippSchlicht:classforcing1&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;, a class Boolean algebra with a proper class antichain can never have this level of completeness. Thus, only ${\rm ORD}$-cc Boolean algebras (having set-sized antichains) can potentially have suprema for all their subclasses. Indeed, it is shown in &lt;a href=&quot;#PeterHolyRegulaKrapfPhilippLuckeAnaNjegomirPhilippSchlicht:classforcing1&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt; that every ${\rm ORD}$-cc partial order densely embeds into a complete Boolean algebra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this article we nevertheless show that the Boolean algebras approach to class forcing can be carried out in sufficiently strong second-order set theories, for example, the theory Kelley-Morse plus the Choice Scheme, using hyperclass Boolean completions. We apply the Boolean algebras approach to show that the ${\rm ZF}$-analogue of the Intermediate Model Theorem holds for models of Kelley-Morse plus the Choice Scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us call an extension $\mathscr W$ of a model $\mathscr V$ of second-order set theory &lt;em&gt;simple&lt;/em&gt; if it is generated by the classes of $\mathscr V$ together with a single new class. In particular, every forcing extension of $\mathscr V$ is simple. We show that every simple intermediate model between a model of ${\rm KM}+{\rm CC}$ and one of its class forcing extensions is itself a forcing extension, so that the Intermediate Model Theorem holds for simple extensions. We also show that an intermediate model between a model of ${\rm KM}+{\rm CC}$ and one of its class forcing extensions need not be simple, and thus the Intermediate Model Theorem can fail. For models of ${\rm KM}$, the Intermediate Model Theorem can fail even where the forcing has the ${\rm ORD}$-cc because a model of ${\rm KM}$ and its forcing extension by ${\rm ORD}$-cc forcing can have non-simple intermediate models. We don't know whether this can happen for models of ${\rm KM}+{\rm CC}$. Finally, we show that if an intermediate model $\mathscr W$ between a model $\mathscr V\models{\rm KM}+{\rm CC}$ and its forcing extension $\mathscr V[G]$ has a definable global well-ordering of classes, and we have additionally that $\mathscr W$ is definable in $\mathscr [G]$, then $\mathscr W$ must be a simple extension of $\mathscr V$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Grigorieff:IntermediateModels&quot;&gt;S. Grigorieff, “Intermediate submodels and generic extensions in set theory,” &lt;i&gt;Ann. Math. (2)&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 101, pp. 447–490, 1975. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;PeterHolyRegulaKrapfPhilippLuckeAnaNjegomirPhilippSchlicht:classforcing1&quot;&gt;P. Holy, R. Krapf, P. Lücke, A. Njegomir, and P. Schlicht, “Class Forcing, the Forcing Theorem and Boolean Completions.” &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">{% reference page.ref %} There are two standard approaches to carrying out the forcing construction over a model of ${\rm ZFC}$ set theory: with partial orders or with complete Boolean algebras. The two approaches yield the same forcing extensions because every partial order densely embeds into a complete Boolean algebra, and when a partial order densely embeds into another partial order, the two have the same forcing extensions. Although the partial order construction can be viewed as more straightforward, the complete Boolean algebras approach offers some advantages. For instance, there are theorems about forcing which have no known proofs without the use of Boolean algebras. One such fundamental result is the Intermediate Model Theorem, which states that if a universe $V\models{\rm ZFC}$ and $W\models{\rm ZFC}$ is an intermediate model between $V$ and one of its set-forcing extensions, then $W$ is itself a forcing extension of $V$. The theorem makes a fundamental use of the Axiom of Choice, but a weaker version of it still holds for models of ${\rm ZF}$. If $V\models{\rm ZF}$ and $V[a]\models{\rm ZF}$, with $a\subseteq V$, is an intermediate model between $V$ and one of its set-forcing extensions, then $V[a]$ is itself a set-forcing extension of $V$. Grigorieff in {% cite Grigorieff:IntermediateModels %} attributes the Intermediate Model Theorem to Solovay. The standard Boolean algebras approach is not available in the context of class forcing because most class partial orders cannot be densely embedded into a sufficiently complete class Boolean algebra. Set forcing uses complete Boolean algebras, those which have suprema for all their subsets, because completeness is required for assigning Boolean values to formulas in the forcing language. With a class Boolean algebra, which has suprema for all its subsets, we can still define the Boolean values of atomic formulas, but the definition of Boolean values for existential formulas needs to take suprema of subclasses, meaning that we must require a Boolean algebra to have those in order to be able to construct the Boolean-valued model. However, as shown in {% cite PeterHolyRegulaKrapfPhilippLuckeAnaNjegomirPhilippSchlicht:classforcing1 %}, a class Boolean algebra with a proper class antichain can never have this level of completeness. Thus, only ${\rm ORD}$-cc Boolean algebras (having set-sized antichains) can potentially have suprema for all their subclasses. Indeed, it is shown in {% cite PeterHolyRegulaKrapfPhilippLuckeAnaNjegomirPhilippSchlicht:classforcing1 %} that every ${\rm ORD}$-cc partial order densely embeds into a complete Boolean algebra. In this article we nevertheless show that the Boolean algebras approach to class forcing can be carried out in sufficiently strong second-order set theories, for example, the theory Kelley-Morse plus the Choice Scheme, using hyperclass Boolean completions. We apply the Boolean algebras approach to show that the ${\rm ZF}$-analogue of the Intermediate Model Theorem holds for models of Kelley-Morse plus the Choice Scheme. Let us call an extension $\mathscr W$ of a model $\mathscr V$ of second-order set theory simple if it is generated by the classes of $\mathscr V$ together with a single new class. In particular, every forcing extension of $\mathscr V$ is simple. We show that every simple intermediate model between a model of ${\rm KM}+{\rm CC}$ and one of its class forcing extensions is itself a forcing extension, so that the Intermediate Model Theorem holds for simple extensions. We also show that an intermediate model between a model of ${\rm KM}+{\rm CC}$ and one of its class forcing extensions need not be simple, and thus the Intermediate Model Theorem can fail. For models of ${\rm KM}$, the Intermediate Model Theorem can fail even where the forcing has the ${\rm ORD}$-cc because a model of ${\rm KM}$ and its forcing extension by ${\rm ORD}$-cc forcing can have non-simple intermediate models. We don't know whether this can happen for models of ${\rm KM}+{\rm CC}$. Finally, we show that if an intermediate model $\mathscr W$ between a model $\mathscr V\models{\rm KM}+{\rm CC}$ and its forcing extension $\mathscr V[G]$ has a definable global well-ordering of classes, and we have additionally that $\mathscr W$ is definable in $\mathscr [G]$, then $\mathscr W$ must be a simple extension of $\mathscr V$. References {% bibliography --cited %}</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Boolean-valued class forcing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/talks/2018/05/01/boolean-valued-class-forcing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Boolean-valued class forcing" /><published>2018-05-01T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-05-01T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/talks/2018/05/01/boolean-valued-class-forcing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/talks/2018/05/01/boolean-valued-class-forcing.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://boolesrings.org/victoriagitman/cuny-logic-seminars/cuny-logic-workshop/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CUNY Logic Workshop&lt;/a&gt; in New York, May 4, 2018.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two standard ways to do forcing: using partial orders or using complete Boolean algebras. Since every partial order densely embeds into a complete Boolean algebra and whenever two partial orders densely embed, they produce the same forcing extensions, the two approaches to forcing are essentially interchangeable. But meanwhile each approach offers distinct advantages. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The kind of new object we would like to have in the forcing extension dictates what the conditions in the partial order should be. If you would like to add a new real, make the partial order consist of finite binary sequences. If you would like to add a tree, make the partial order consist of small trees. It is usually clear how different conditions in the partial order alter the properties of the new object. The Boolean completion of the partial order breaks the direct connection between the properties of the object we would like to add and the conditions in the forcing, which is precisely why pretty much no one uses the Boolean algebras approach in forcing practice. The Boolean algebras approach however offers both philosophical and practical advantages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We often speak of the forcing relation for a partial order being definable. But what does the forcing relation really mean when we are talking about forcing over the entire universe $V$ and not just some toy countable model? In this context it does not make sense to say that $p\Vdash\varphi$ means that whenever $p$ is an element of a generic filter $G$, then $V[G]\models\varphi$. On the other hand, the Boolean-valued model construction with a complete Boolean algebra makes sense without reference to any transitive set models. Indeed, using any ultrafilter $U$ on the Boolean algebra, we can turn the Boolean-valued model into a definable model $M\models{\rm ZFC}$ of the form $\bar V[G]$, a forcing extension of submodel $\bar V$, where $V$ elementarily embeds into $\bar V$. So that by passing from $V$ to $\bar V$, a model with the same theory, we get access to both the universe and its forcing extension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are theorems about forcing which have no known proofs without the use of complete Boolean algebras. A fundamental result about forcing is the Intermediate Model Theorem, which states that every intermediate universe $W\models{\rm ZFC}$ between a universe $V$ and its forcing extension $V[G]$ is itself a forcing extension of $V$. Indeed, if $V[G]$ is a forcing extension by $\mathbb P$ and $\mathbb B_{\mathbb P}$ is a Boolean completion of $\mathbb P$, then $\mathbb B_{\mathbb P}$ has a complete subalgebra $\mathbb D$ such that $W=V[\mathbb D\cap G]$ is a forcing extension by $\mathbb D$. Grigorief in &lt;a href=&quot;#Grigorieff:IntermediateModels&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; attributes the Intermediate Model Theorem to Solovay. The theorem makes a fundamental use of the Axiom of Choice, but is true in a weaker form for models of ${\rm ZF}$. If $V[a]\models{\rm ZF}$ with $a\subseteq V$ is an intermediate universe between $V\models{\rm ZF}$ and its forcing extension $V[G]$, then $V[a]$ is a forcing extension of $V$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everything that has been said so far holds true for &lt;em&gt;set&lt;/em&gt; partial orders. What about class partial orders? Analyzing the properties of class partial orders is best done in a second-order setting where we have objects for classes as well as sets. One of the weakest second-order theories is the Gödel-Bernays set theory ${\rm GBC}$, so let's take it for the moment as our second-order foundation. We will think of models of second-order set theory as triples $\mathscr V=\langle V,\in,\mathcal C\rangle$, where $V$ is the collection of sets and $\mathcal C$ is the collection of classes. If $\mathbb P\in\mathcal C$ is partial order and $G\subseteq \mathbb P$ is $\mathscr V$-generic, then the forcing extension $\mathscr V[G]=\langle V[G],\in,\mathcal C[G]\rangle$, where $V[G]$ is all interpretations of $\mathbb P$-names and $\mathcal C[G]$ is all interpretations of &lt;em&gt;class&lt;/em&gt; $\mathbb P$-names, which are collections of pairs $\langle \sigma,p\rangle$ where $\sigma$ is a $\mathbb P$-name and $p\in\mathbb P$. Now we can talk about the properties of class partial orders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the perspective of forcing, class partial orders don't behave anywhere as nicely as set partial orders. Class partial orders may not preserve ${\rm GBC}$. Think for example, of the partial order to add bijection from $\omega$ onto ${\rm ORD}$. The forcing relation for a class partial order may not be definable because it can, for instance, code in a truth predicate for $\mathscr V$. Two class partial orders can densely embed but produce different forcing extensions. Class partial orders may not have Boolean completions. (The results are from &lt;a href=&quot;#PeterHolyRegulaKrapfPhilippSchlicht:classforcing2&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;) To understand this last point, let's be more precise about the kind of Boolean completion we would like a class partial order to have.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The completeness of a Boolean algebra is used in defining the Boolean values of formulas in the forcing language. Suppose $\mathbb B$ is a Boolean algebra. For example, the Boolean value of an atomic assertion $$[[\sigma\in \tau]]=\bigwedge_{\langle \mu,b\rangle\in \tau}[[\sigma=\mu]]\cdot b$$ and the Boolean value of an existential assertion $$[[\exists x\varphi(x,\tau)]]=\bigvee_{\sigma\in V^{\mathbb B}}[[\varphi(\sigma,\tau)]].$$ So if $\mathbb B$ is class, then the definition of Boolean values for atomic assertions requires the existence suprema for sets (set-completeness), but the existential assertions require the existence of suprema for classes as well (class-completeness).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A class partial order can be densely embedded into a set-complete Boolean algebra if and only if its forcing relation is definable &lt;a href=&quot;#PeterHolyRegulaKrapfPhilippLuckeAnaNjegomirPhilippSchlicht:classforcing1&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;. So in ${\rm GBC}$, it is not the case that every class partial order can be embedded into a set-complete Boolean algebra. To define the forcing relation however requires only a bit more comprehension, already in ${\rm GBC}$ together with $\Pi^1_1$-comprehension (for assertions with a single class quantifier) every class partial order has a definable forcing relation (indeed this is already true for a much weaker theory ${\rm GBC}+{\rm ETR}_{\rm {ORD}}$, see &lt;a href=&quot;#GitmanHamkinsHolySchlichtWilliams:ForcingTheorem&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;). So in the much stronger theory Kelley-Morse ${\rm KM}$ (which consists of ${\rm GBC}$ together with comprehension for all second-order assertions) every class partial order can be embedded into a set-complete Boolean algebra. But indeed, it will never be possible to embed every class partial order into a class-complete Boolean algebra. A Boolean algebra with a proper class antichain can never be class complete, and therefore no class partial order with a proper class antichain can be embedded into such a Boolean algebra &lt;a href=&quot;#PeterHolyRegulaKrapfPhilippLuckeAnaNjegomirPhilippSchlicht:classforcing1&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;. But without class completeness, we cannot define the Boolean-valued model!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happens when we try to carry out the standard Boolean completion construction with a class partial order? The elements of the completion are subsets of $\mathbb P$ that are regular cuts (a &lt;em&gt;cut&lt;/em&gt; is subset of $\mathbb P$ that is closed downwards and a cut $U$ is &lt;em&gt;regular&lt;/em&gt; if whenever $p\notin U$, then there is $q\leq p$ such that $U_q\cap U=\emptyset$, where $U_q$ is the cut consisting of all conditions in the cone below $p$). If $\mathbb P$ is a class, then regular cuts are definable sub-classes of $\mathbb P$, and so the collection of regular cuts of $\mathbb P$ is a &lt;em&gt;hyperclass&lt;/em&gt; - a (second-order) definable collection of classes. What properties does this hyperclass, call it $\mathbb B_{\mathbb P}$, have? We can definably impose a Boolean operations structure on it in the usual way, so it is a Boolean algebra. How complete is it? First, let's explain how some hyperclasses can actually be quite small, namely class-sized. We will say that a hyperclass, given a formula $\varphi(X,A)$, is &lt;em&gt;coded&lt;/em&gt; by a class $S$ if the classes satisfying $\varphi(X,A)$ are precisely the slices of $S$, where a class $T$ is a slice of $S$ if there is a set $a$ such that $T=\{y\mid \langle y,a\rangle\in S\}$. We should think of coded hyperclasses as being class-sized. The hyperclass Boolean algebra $\mathbb B_{\mathbb P}$ is class-complete in the sense that it is complete for all coded hyperclasses. Given a hyperclass coded by $S$, its join is the least regular cut containing the union of all slices $S_a$. But because the elements of $\mathbb B_{\mathbb P}$ are now classes, it should be intuitively clear that to have any hope of using it to define a Boolean-valued model, we need $\mathbb B_{\mathbb  P}$ to be complete for all hyperclasses, not just the coded ones. Remarkably it turns out that given any partial order $\mathbb P$ with a proper class antichain, if $\mathbb B_{\mathbb P}$ is hyperclass complete, then we have comprehension for all second-order assertions, and therefore ${\rm KM}$ holds &lt;a href=&quot;#AntosFriedmanGitman:booleanclassforcing&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;. Thus, the completeness of the hyperclass object is directly connected to the amount of comprehension a model satisfies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In models of ${\rm KM}$, the hyperclass object $\mathbb B_{\mathbb P}$ has all the desired properties. It is complete for all hyperclasses and indeed, as aught to be the case because it has a class-sized dense sub-partial-order, all its hyperclass antichains are coded. But it is still very difficult if not impossible to define the Boolean-valued model with a Boolean algebra whose elements are classes. A natural solution to this problem is to move a slightly stronger second-order set theory Kelley-Morse together with the Choice Scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;Choice Scheme&lt;/em&gt; ${\rm CC}$ is a choice principle (or a collection principle depending on the point of view) for classes which states for every second-order assertion $\varphi(x,X,A)$ that if for every set $x$, there is a witnessing class $X$ such that $\varphi(x,X,A)$ holds, then there is a single class $Y$ collecting witnesses for every set $x$, in the sense that $\varphi(x,Y_x,A)$ holds for every set $x$ (where $Y_x$ is the $x$-th slice of $Y$ defined as above). Kelley-Morse does not prove even the weakest instances of the Choice Scheme, those for first-order assertions and making just $\omega$-many choices &lt;a href=&quot;#GitmanHamkinsJohnstone:KMplus&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;. But nevertheless the two theories ${\rm KM}$ and ${\rm KM}+{\rm CC}$ are equiconsistent, basically because the &quot;constructible universe&quot; of a model of ${\rm KM}$ satisfies ${\rm KM}+{\rm CC}$. The theory ${\rm KM}+{\rm CC}$ has one remarkable feature. It is bi-interpretable with a very well-understood first-order set theory. Given a model $\mathscr V\models{\rm KM}+{\rm CC}$ we can consider its class well-founded relations. For instance, $\mathscr V$ has relations coding ${\rm ORD}+{\rm ORD}$, ${\rm ORD}\times\omega$, $V\cup{\{V\}}$, etc. We can view such relations as coding transitive sets that sit &quot;above&quot; the sets of $V$. Modulo isomorphism, we can define a membership relation on the equivalence classes of these relations resulting in a first-order structure extending $V$. We will call this structure the companion model $M_{\mathscr V}$ of $\mathscr V$. The model $M_{\mathscr V}$ satisfies the theory ${\rm ZFC}^-_I$, consisting of the axioms of ${\rm ZFC}$ without powerset $(-)$, with the assertion that there is a largest cardinal $\kappa$ which is inaccessible ($I$). Natural models of ${\rm ZFC}^-_I$ are $H_{\kappa^+}$ for an inaccessible cardinal $\kappa$. The $V_\kappa$ of $M_{\mathscr V}$ consists of the sets $V$ of $\mathscr V$ and the subsets of $V_\kappa$ are the classes of $\mathscr V$. In the other direction if $M\models{\rm ZFC}^-_I$, then $\mathscr V=\langle V_\kappa^M,\in,\mathcal C\rangle$, where $\mathcal C$ consists of the subsets of $V_\kappa$ in $M$, is a model of ${\rm KM}+{\rm CC}$ whose companion model $M_{\mathscr V}$ is isomorphic to $M$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thus, whenever we work in a model $\mathscr V\models{\rm KM}+{\rm CC}$, we might as well be working in its companion model $M_{\mathscr V}$. But now the trick is that in $M_{\mathscr V}$, the class partial order $\mathbb P$ is a set (subset of $V_\kappa^{M_{\mathscr V}}$) and the hyperclass $\mathbb B_{\mathbb P}$ is a class-complete Boolean algebra with set-sized antichains. In $M_{\mathscr V}$, it is now easy to define the collection $M_{\mathscr V}^{\mathbb B_{\mathbb P}}$ of $\mathbb B_{\mathbb P}$-names as well the Boolean values of all assertions in the forcing language, using the completeness of $\mathbb B_{\mathbb P}$. In this sense, we have the Boolean algebras approach to forcing in models of ${\rm KM}+{\rm CC}$. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One consequence of this is that we get the ${\rm ZF}$-analogue of the Intermediate Model Theorem for models of ${\rm KM}+{\rm CC}$. Let us say that $\mathscr W$ is a &lt;em&gt;simple&lt;/em&gt; extension of $\mathscr V\models{\rm KM}+{\rm CC}$ if $\mathscr W$ is generated by the classes of $\mathscr V$ together with a single class. In particular, forcing extensions of $\mathscr V$ are simple. Using, the Boolean-valued model, we can show that every intermediate simple extension $\mathscr W\models{\rm KM}+{\rm CC}$ between a model $\mathscr V\models{\rm KM}+{\rm CC}$ and its forcing extension $\mathscr V[G]\models{\rm KM}+{\rm CC}$ is itself a forcing extension of $\mathscr V$. The result is optimal because it is possible to have intermediate models between a model $\mathscr V\models{\rm KM}+{\rm CC}$ and its forcing extension $\mathscr V[G]\models\rm KM+{\rm CC}$ that are not simple, and therefore cannot be forcing extensions themselves. &lt;a href=&quot;#AntosFriedmanGitman:booleanclassforcing&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is joint work with Carolin Antos and Sy-David Friedman.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Grigorieff:IntermediateModels&quot;&gt;S. Grigorieff, “Intermediate submodels and generic extensions in set theory,” &lt;i&gt;Ann. Math. (2)&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 101, pp. 447–490, 1975. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;PeterHolyRegulaKrapfPhilippSchlicht:classforcing2&quot;&gt;P. Holy, R. Krapf, and P. Schlicht, “Characterizations of Pretameness and the Ord-cc.” &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;PeterHolyRegulaKrapfPhilippLuckeAnaNjegomirPhilippSchlicht:classforcing1&quot;&gt;P. Holy, R. Krapf, P. Lücke, A. Njegomir, and P. Schlicht, “Class Forcing, the Forcing Theorem and Boolean Completions.” &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;GitmanHamkinsHolySchlichtWilliams:ForcingTheorem&quot;&gt;V. Gitman, J. D. Hamkins, P. Holy, P. Schlicht, and K. Williams, “The exact strength of the class forcing theorem,” &lt;i&gt;Submitted&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;AntosFriedmanGitman:booleanclassforcing&quot;&gt;C. Antos, S. D. Friedman, and V. Gitman, “Boolean-valued class forcing,” &lt;i&gt;Submitted&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;GitmanHamkinsJohnstone:KMplus&quot;&gt;V. Gitman, J. D. Hamkins, and T. Johnstone, “Kelley-Morse set theory and choice principles for classes.” &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the CUNY Logic Workshop in New York, May 4, 2018.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Virtual large cardinal principles at KGRC</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/talks/2018/03/21/virtual-large-cardinals-at-kgrc.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Virtual large cardinal principles at KGRC" /><published>2018-03-21T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-03-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/talks/2018/03/21/virtual-large-cardinals-at-kgrc</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/talks/2018/03/21/virtual-large-cardinals-at-kgrc.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the &lt;a \href=&quot;http://www.logic.univie.ac.at/Home.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Kurt Gödel Research Center&lt;/a&gt; Research Seminar in Vienna, Austria, April 14, 2018.&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;files/ViennaSeminarVirtual.pdf&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/images/Josephinum.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:left; padding: 10px;&quot; /&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: Given a set-theoretic property $\mathcal P$ characterized by the existence of elementary embeddings between some first-order structures, we say that $\mathcal P$ holds &lt;em&gt;virtually&lt;/em&gt; if the embeddings between structures from $V$ characterizing $\mathcal P$ exist somewhere in the generic multiverse. We showed with Schindler that virtual versions of supercompact, $C^{(n)}$-extendible, $n$-huge and rank-into-rank cardinals form a large cardinal hierarchy consistent with $V=L$. Sitting atop the hierarchy are virtual versions of inconsistent large cardinal principles such as the existence of an elementary embedding $j:V_\lambda\to V_\lambda$ for $\lambda$ much larger than the supremum of the critical sequence. The Silver indiscernibles, under $0^\sharp$, which have a number of large cardinal properties in $L$, are also natural examples of virtual large cardinals. With Bagaria, Hamkins and Schindler, we investigated  properties of the virtual version of Vopěnka's Principle, which is consistent with $V=L$, and established some surprising differences from Vopenka's Principle, stemming from the failure of Kunen's Inconsistency in the virtual setting. A recent new direction in the study of virtual large cardinal principles involves asking that the required embeddings exist in forcing extensions preserving a large segment of the cardinals. In the talk, I will discuss a mixture of results about the virtual large cardinal hierarchy and virtual Vopěnka's  Principle. Time permitting, I will give an overview of Woodin's new results on virtual large cardinals in cardinal preserving extensions. 

&lt;div class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/vienna.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the Kurt Gödel Research Center Research Seminar in Vienna, Austria, April 14, 2018.Slides</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A model of second-order arithmetic satisfying AC but not DC</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/publications/2018/03/21/a-model-of-second-order-arithmetic-satisfying-AC-but-not-DC.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A model of second-order arithmetic satisfying AC but not DC" /><published>2018-03-21T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2018-03-21T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/publications/2018/03/21/a-model-of-second-order-arithmetic-satisfying-AC-but-not-DC</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/publications/2018/03/21/a-model-of-second-order-arithmetic-satisfying-AC-but-not-DC.html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;FriedmanGitman:ModelOfACNotDC&quot;&gt;S.-D. Friedman, V. Gitman, and V. Kanovei, “A model of second-order arithmetic satisfying AC but not DC,” &lt;i&gt;To appear in the Journal of Mathematical Logic&lt;/i&gt;. Available at: https://victoriagitman.github.io/files/ModelOfACNotDC.pdf&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Models of arithmetic are two-sorted structures, having two types of objects, which we think of as numbers and sets of numbers. Their properties are formalized using a two-sorted logic with separate variables and quantifiers for numbers and sets. By convention, we will denote number variables by lower-case letters and sets variables by upper-case letters. The language of second-order arithmetic is the language of first-order arithmetic $\mathcal L_A=\{+,\cdot,&lt;,0,1\}$ together with a membership relation $\in$ between numbers and sets. A multitude of second-order arithmetic theories, as well as the relationships between them, have been extensively studied (see &lt;a href=&quot;#simpson:second-orderArithmetic&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An example of a weak second-order arithmetic theory is ${\rm ACA_0}$, whose axioms consist of the modified Peano axioms, where instead of the induction scheme we have the single second-order induction axiom $$\forall X [(0\in X\wedge \forall n(n\in X\rightarrow n+1\in X))\rightarrow \forall n (n\in X)],$$ and the &lt;em&gt;comprehension scheme&lt;/em&gt; for first-order formulas. The latter is a scheme of assertions stating for every first-order formula, possibly with class parameters, that there is a set whose elements are exactly the numbers satisfying the formula. One of the strongest second-order arithmetic theories is ${\rm Z}_2$, often referred to as &lt;em&gt;full second-order arithmetic&lt;/em&gt;, which strengthens comprehension for first-order formulas in ${\rm ACA}_0$ to full comprehension for all second-order assertions. This means that for a formula with any number of second-order quantifiers, there is a set whose elements are exactly the numbers satisfying the formula. The reals of any model of ${\rm ZF}$ is a model of ${\rm Z}_2$. We can further strengthen the theory ${\rm Z}_2$ by adding choice principles for sets: the choice scheme and the dependent choice scheme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;choice scheme&lt;/em&gt; is a scheme of assertions, which states for every second-order formula $\varphi(n,X,A)$ with a set parameter $A$ that if for every number $n$, there is a set $X$ witnessing $\varphi(n,X,A)$, then there is a single set $Y$ collecting witnesses for every $n$, in the sense that $\varphi(n,Y_n,A)$ holds, where $Y_n=\{m\mid \langle n,m\rangle\in Y\}$ and $\langle n,m\rangle$ is any standard coding of pairs. More precisely, an instance of the choice scheme for the formula $\varphi(n,X,A)$ is $$\forall n\exists X\varphi(n,X,A)\rightarrow \exists Y\forall n\varphi(n,Y_n,A).$$ We will denote by $\Sigma^1_n$-${\rm AC}$ the fragment of the choice scheme for $\Sigma^1_n$-assertions, making an analogous definition for $\Pi^1_n$, and we will denote the full choice scheme by $\Sigma^1_\infty$-${\rm AC}$. The reals of any model of ${\rm ZF}+{\rm AC}_\omega$ (countable choice) satisfy ${\rm Z}_2+\Sigma^1_\infty$-${\rm AC}$. It is a folklore result, going back possibly to Mostowski, that the theory ${\rm Z}_2+\Sigma^1_\infty$-${\rm AC}$ is bi-interpretable with the theory ${\rm ZFC}^-$ (${\rm ZFC}$ without the powerset axiom, with Collection instead of Replacement) together with the statement that every set is countable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;em&gt;dependent choice scheme&lt;/em&gt; is a scheme of assertions, which states for every second-order formula $\varphi(X,Y,A)$ with set parameter $A$ that if for every set $X$, there is a set $Y$ witnessing $\varphi(X,Y,A)$, then there is a single set $Z$ making infinitely many dependent choices according to $\varphi$. More precisely, an instance of the dependent choice scheme for the formula $\varphi(X,Y,A)$ is $$\forall X\exists Y\varphi(X,Y,A)\rightarrow \exists Z\forall n\varphi(Z_n,Z_{n+1},A).$$ We will denote by $\Sigma^1_n$-${\rm DC}$ the dependent choice scheme for $\Sigma^1_n$-assertions, with an analogous definition for $\Pi^1_n$, and we will denote the full dependent choice scheme by $\Sigma^1_\infty$-${\rm DC}$. The reals of a model of ${\rm ZF}+{\rm DC}$ (dependent choice) satisfy ${\rm Z}_2+\Sigma^1_\infty$-${\rm DC}$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is not difficult to see that the theory ${\rm Z}_2$ implies $\Sigma^1_2$-${\rm AC}$, the choice scheme for $\Sigma^1_2$-assertions. Models of ${\rm Z}_2$ can build their own version of Gödel's constructible universe $L$. If a model of ${\rm Z}_2$ believes that a set $\Gamma$ is a well-order, then it has a set coding a set-theoretic structure constructed like $L$ along the well-order $\Gamma$.  It turns out that models of ${\rm Z}_2$ satisfy a version of Shoenfield's absoluteness with respect to their constructible universes. For every $\Sigma^1_2$-assertion $\varphi$, a model of ${\rm Z}_2$ satisfies $\varphi$ if and only its constructible universe satisfies $\varphi$ with set quantifiers naturally interpreted as ranging over the reals. All of the above generalizes to constructible universes $L[A]$ relativized to a set parameter $A$. Thus, given a $\Sigma^1_2$-assertion $\varphi(n,X,A)$ for which the model satisfies $\forall n\exists X\varphi(n,X,A)$, the model can go to its constructible universe $L[A]$ to pick the least witness $X$ for $\varphi(n,X,A)$ for every $n$, because $L[A]$ agrees when $\varphi$ is satisfied, and then put the witnesses together into a single set using comprehension. So long as the unique witnessing set can be obtained for each $n$, comprehension suffices to obtain a single set of witnesses. How much more of the choice scheme follows from ${\rm Z}_2$? The reals of the classical Feferman-Lévy model of ${\rm ZF}$ (see &lt;a href=&quot;#levy:choicescheme&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;, Theorem 8), in which $\aleph_1$ is a countable union of countable sets, is a $\beta$-model of ${\rm Z}_2$ in which $\Pi^1_2$-${\rm AC}$ fails. This is a particulary strong failure of the choice scheme because, as we explain below, $\beta$-models are meant to strongly resemble the full standard model $P(\omega)$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two ways in which a model of second-order arithmetic can resemble the full standard model $P(\omega)$. A model of second-order arithmetic is called an $\omega$-&lt;em&gt;model&lt;/em&gt; if its first-order part is $\omega$, and it follows that its second-order part is some subset of $P(\omega)$. But even an $\omega$-model can poorly resemble $P(\omega)$ because it may be wrong about well-foundedness by missing $\omega$-sequences. An $\omega$-model of second-order arithmetic which is correct about well-foundedness is called a $\beta$-&lt;em&gt;model&lt;/em&gt;. The reals of any transitive ${\rm ZF}$-model is a $\beta$-model of ${\rm Z}_2$. One advantage to having a $\beta$-model of ${\rm Z}_2$ is that the constructible universe it builds internally is isomorphic to an initial segment $L_\alpha$ of the actual constructible universe $L$.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The theory ${\rm Z}_2$ also implies $\Sigma^1_2$-${\rm DC}$ (see &lt;a href=&quot;#simpson:second-orderArithmetic&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, Theorem VII.9.2), the dependent choice scheme for $\Sigma^1_2$-assertions.  In this article, we construct a symmetric submodel of a forcing extension of $L$ whose reals form a model of second-order arithmetic in which ${\rm Z}_2$ together with $\Sigma^1_\infty$-${\rm AC}$ holds, but $\Pi^1_2$-${\rm DC}$ fails. The forcing notion we use is a tree iteration of a forcing for adding a real due to Jensen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Jensen's forcing, which we will call here $\mathbb P^J$, introduced by Jensen in &lt;a href=&quot;#jensen:real&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;, is a subposet of Sacks forcing constructed in $L$ using the $\diamondsuit$ principle. The poset $\mathbb P^J$ has the ccc and adds a unique generic real over $L$. The collection of all $L$-generic reals for $\mathbb P^J$ in any model is $\Pi^1_2$-definable. Jensen used his forcing to show that it is consistent with ${\rm ZFC}$ that there is a $\Sigma^1_3$-definable non-constructible real &lt;a href=&quot;#jensen:real&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;. Recently Lyubetsky and Kanovei extended the &quot;uniqueness of generic filters&quot; property of Jensen's forcing to finite-support products of $\mathbb P^J$ &lt;a href=&quot;#kanovei:productOfJensenReals&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;. They showed that in a forcing extension $L[G]$ by the $\omega$-length finite support-product of $\mathbb P^J$, the only $L$-generic reals for $\mathbb P^J$ are the slices of the generic filter $G$. The result easily extends to $\omega_1$-length finite support-products as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We in turn extend the ``uniqueness of generic filters&quot; property to tree iterations of Jensen's forcing. We first define finite iterations $\mathbb P^J_n$ of Jensen's forcing $\mathbb P^J$, and then define an iteration of $\mathbb P^J$ along a tree $\mathcal T$ to be a forcing whose conditions are functions from a finite subtree of $\mathcal T$ into $\bigcup_{n&lt;\omega}\mathbb P_n^J$ such that nodes on level $n$ get mapped to elements of the $n$-length iteration $\mathbb P_n^J$ and conditions on higher nodes extend conditions on lower nodes. The functions are ordered by extension of domain and strengthening on each coordinate. We show that in a forcing extension $L[G]$ by the tree iteration of $\mathbb P^J$ along the tree ${}^{\lt\omega}\omega_1$ (or the tree ${}^{\lt\omega}\omega$) the only $L$-generic filters for $\mathbb P_n^J$ are the restrictions of $G$ to level $n$ nodes of tree. We proceed to construct a symmetric submodel of $L[G]$ which has the tree of $\mathbb P_n^J$-generic filters added by $G$ but no branch through it. The symmetric model we construct satisfies ${\rm AC}_\omega$ and the tree of $\mathbb P_n^J$-generic filters is $\Pi^1_2$-definable in it. The reals of this model thus provide the desired $\beta$-model of ${\rm Z}_2$ in which $\Sigma^1_\infty$-${\rm AC}$ holds, but $\Pi^1_2$-${\rm DC}$ fails.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our results also answer a long-standing open question of Zarach from &lt;a href=&quot;#Zarach1996:ReplacmentDoesNotImplyCollection&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt; about whether the Reflection Principle holds in models of ${\rm ZFC}^-$. The &lt;em&gt;Reflection Principle&lt;/em&gt; states that every formula can be reflected to a transitive set, and holds in ${\rm ZFC}$ by the Lévy-Montague reflection because every formula is reflected by some $V_\alpha$. In the absence of the von Neumann hierarchy, it is not clear how to realize reflection, and indeed we show that it fails in $H_{\omega_1}\models{\rm ZFC}^-$ of the symmetric model we construct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;simpson:second-orderArithmetic&quot;&gt;S. G. Simpson, &lt;i&gt;Subsystems of second order arithmetic&lt;/i&gt;, Second. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge; Association for
              Symbolic Logic, Poughkeepsie, NY, 2009, p. xvi+444. Available at: http://dx.doi.org/10.1017/CBO9780511581007&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;levy:choicescheme&quot;&gt;A. Lévy, “Definability in axiomatic set theory. II,” in &lt;i&gt;Mathematical Logic and Foundations of Set Theory
              (Proc. Internat. Colloq., Jerusalem, 1968)&lt;/i&gt;, North-Holland, Amsterdam, 1970, pp. 129–145. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;jensen:real&quot;&gt;R. Jensen, “Definable sets of minimal degree,” in &lt;i&gt;Mathematical logic and foundations of set theory (Proc.
              Internat. Colloq., Jerusalem, 1968)&lt;/i&gt;, North-Holland, Amsterdam, 1970, pp. 122–128. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;kanovei:productOfJensenReals&quot;&gt;V. Kanovei and V. Lyubetsky, “A countable definable set of reals containing no definable elements.” &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Zarach1996:ReplacmentDoesNotImplyCollection&quot;&gt;A. M. Zarach, “Replacement $\nrightarrow$ collection,” in &lt;i&gt;Gödel ’96 (Brno, 1996)&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 6, Berlin: Springer, 1996, pp. 307–322. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">{% reference page.ref %} Models of arithmetic are two-sorted structures, having two types of objects, which we think of as numbers and sets of numbers. Their properties are formalized using a two-sorted logic with separate variables and quantifiers for numbers and sets. By convention, we will denote number variables by lower-case letters and sets variables by upper-case letters. The language of second-order arithmetic is the language of first-order arithmetic $\mathcal L_A=\{+,\cdot, An example of a weak second-order arithmetic theory is ${\rm ACA_0}$, whose axioms consist of the modified Peano axioms, where instead of the induction scheme we have the single second-order induction axiom $$\forall X [(0\in X\wedge \forall n(n\in X\rightarrow n+1\in X))\rightarrow \forall n (n\in X)],$$ and the comprehension scheme for first-order formulas. The latter is a scheme of assertions stating for every first-order formula, possibly with class parameters, that there is a set whose elements are exactly the numbers satisfying the formula. One of the strongest second-order arithmetic theories is ${\rm Z}_2$, often referred to as full second-order arithmetic, which strengthens comprehension for first-order formulas in ${\rm ACA}_0$ to full comprehension for all second-order assertions. This means that for a formula with any number of second-order quantifiers, there is a set whose elements are exactly the numbers satisfying the formula. The reals of any model of ${\rm ZF}$ is a model of ${\rm Z}_2$. We can further strengthen the theory ${\rm Z}_2$ by adding choice principles for sets: the choice scheme and the dependent choice scheme. The choice scheme is a scheme of assertions, which states for every second-order formula $\varphi(n,X,A)$ with a set parameter $A$ that if for every number $n$, there is a set $X$ witnessing $\varphi(n,X,A)$, then there is a single set $Y$ collecting witnesses for every $n$, in the sense that $\varphi(n,Y_n,A)$ holds, where $Y_n=\{m\mid \langle n,m\rangle\in Y\}$ and $\langle n,m\rangle$ is any standard coding of pairs. More precisely, an instance of the choice scheme for the formula $\varphi(n,X,A)$ is $$\forall n\exists X\varphi(n,X,A)\rightarrow \exists Y\forall n\varphi(n,Y_n,A).$$ We will denote by $\Sigma^1_n$-${\rm AC}$ the fragment of the choice scheme for $\Sigma^1_n$-assertions, making an analogous definition for $\Pi^1_n$, and we will denote the full choice scheme by $\Sigma^1_\infty$-${\rm AC}$. The reals of any model of ${\rm ZF}+{\rm AC}_\omega$ (countable choice) satisfy ${\rm Z}_2+\Sigma^1_\infty$-${\rm AC}$. It is a folklore result, going back possibly to Mostowski, that the theory ${\rm Z}_2+\Sigma^1_\infty$-${\rm AC}$ is bi-interpretable with the theory ${\rm ZFC}^-$ (${\rm ZFC}$ without the powerset axiom, with Collection instead of Replacement) together with the statement that every set is countable. The dependent choice scheme is a scheme of assertions, which states for every second-order formula $\varphi(X,Y,A)$ with set parameter $A$ that if for every set $X$, there is a set $Y$ witnessing $\varphi(X,Y,A)$, then there is a single set $Z$ making infinitely many dependent choices according to $\varphi$. More precisely, an instance of the dependent choice scheme for the formula $\varphi(X,Y,A)$ is $$\forall X\exists Y\varphi(X,Y,A)\rightarrow \exists Z\forall n\varphi(Z_n,Z_{n+1},A).$$ We will denote by $\Sigma^1_n$-${\rm DC}$ the dependent choice scheme for $\Sigma^1_n$-assertions, with an analogous definition for $\Pi^1_n$, and we will denote the full dependent choice scheme by $\Sigma^1_\infty$-${\rm DC}$. The reals of a model of ${\rm ZF}+{\rm DC}$ (dependent choice) satisfy ${\rm Z}_2+\Sigma^1_\infty$-${\rm DC}$. It is not difficult to see that the theory ${\rm Z}_2$ implies $\Sigma^1_2$-${\rm AC}$, the choice scheme for $\Sigma^1_2$-assertions. Models of ${\rm Z}_2$ can build their own version of Gödel's constructible universe $L$. If a model of ${\rm Z}_2$ believes that a set $\Gamma$ is a well-order, then it has a set coding a set-theoretic structure constructed like $L$ along the well-order $\Gamma$. It turns out that models of ${\rm Z}_2$ satisfy a version of Shoenfield's absoluteness with respect to their constructible universes. For every $\Sigma^1_2$-assertion $\varphi$, a model of ${\rm Z}_2$ satisfies $\varphi$ if and only its constructible universe satisfies $\varphi$ with set quantifiers naturally interpreted as ranging over the reals. All of the above generalizes to constructible universes $L[A]$ relativized to a set parameter $A$. Thus, given a $\Sigma^1_2$-assertion $\varphi(n,X,A)$ for which the model satisfies $\forall n\exists X\varphi(n,X,A)$, the model can go to its constructible universe $L[A]$ to pick the least witness $X$ for $\varphi(n,X,A)$ for every $n$, because $L[A]$ agrees when $\varphi$ is satisfied, and then put the witnesses together into a single set using comprehension. So long as the unique witnessing set can be obtained for each $n$, comprehension suffices to obtain a single set of witnesses. How much more of the choice scheme follows from ${\rm Z}_2$? The reals of the classical Feferman-Lévy model of ${\rm ZF}$ (see {% cite levy:choicescheme %}, Theorem 8), in which $\aleph_1$ is a countable union of countable sets, is a $\beta$-model of ${\rm Z}_2$ in which $\Pi^1_2$-${\rm AC}$ fails. This is a particulary strong failure of the choice scheme because, as we explain below, $\beta$-models are meant to strongly resemble the full standard model $P(\omega)$. There are two ways in which a model of second-order arithmetic can resemble the full standard model $P(\omega)$. A model of second-order arithmetic is called an $\omega$-model if its first-order part is $\omega$, and it follows that its second-order part is some subset of $P(\omega)$. But even an $\omega$-model can poorly resemble $P(\omega)$ because it may be wrong about well-foundedness by missing $\omega$-sequences. An $\omega$-model of second-order arithmetic which is correct about well-foundedness is called a $\beta$-model. The reals of any transitive ${\rm ZF}$-model is a $\beta$-model of ${\rm Z}_2$. One advantage to having a $\beta$-model of ${\rm Z}_2$ is that the constructible universe it builds internally is isomorphic to an initial segment $L_\alpha$ of the actual constructible universe $L$. The theory ${\rm Z}_2$ also implies $\Sigma^1_2$-${\rm DC}$ (see {% cite simpson:second-orderArithmetic%}, Theorem VII.9.2), the dependent choice scheme for $\Sigma^1_2$-assertions. In this article, we construct a symmetric submodel of a forcing extension of $L$ whose reals form a model of second-order arithmetic in which ${\rm Z}_2$ together with $\Sigma^1_\infty$-${\rm AC}$ holds, but $\Pi^1_2$-${\rm DC}$ fails. The forcing notion we use is a tree iteration of a forcing for adding a real due to Jensen. Jensen's forcing, which we will call here $\mathbb P^J$, introduced by Jensen in {% cite jensen:real %}, is a subposet of Sacks forcing constructed in $L$ using the $\diamondsuit$ principle. The poset $\mathbb P^J$ has the ccc and adds a unique generic real over $L$. The collection of all $L$-generic reals for $\mathbb P^J$ in any model is $\Pi^1_2$-definable. Jensen used his forcing to show that it is consistent with ${\rm ZFC}$ that there is a $\Sigma^1_3$-definable non-constructible real {% cite jensen:real%}. Recently Lyubetsky and Kanovei extended the &quot;uniqueness of generic filters&quot; property of Jensen's forcing to finite-support products of $\mathbb P^J$ {% cite kanovei:productOfJensenReals %}. They showed that in a forcing extension $L[G]$ by the $\omega$-length finite support-product of $\mathbb P^J$, the only $L$-generic reals for $\mathbb P^J$ are the slices of the generic filter $G$. The result easily extends to $\omega_1$-length finite support-products as well. We in turn extend the ``uniqueness of generic filters&quot; property to tree iterations of Jensen's forcing. We first define finite iterations $\mathbb P^J_n$ of Jensen's forcing $\mathbb P^J$, and then define an iteration of $\mathbb P^J$ along a tree $\mathcal T$ to be a forcing whose conditions are functions from a finite subtree of $\mathcal T$ into $\bigcup_{n Our results also answer a long-standing open question of Zarach from {% cite Zarach1996:ReplacmentDoesNotImplyCollection %} about whether the Reflection Principle holds in models of ${\rm ZFC}^-$. The Reflection Principle states that every formula can be reflected to a transitive set, and holds in ${\rm ZFC}$ by the Lévy-Montague reflection because every formula is reflected by some $V_\alpha$. In the absence of the von Neumann hierarchy, it is not clear how to realize reflection, and indeed we show that it fails in $H_{\omega_1}\models{\rm ZFC}^-$ of the symmetric model we construct. References {% bibliography --cited %}</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The emerging zoo of second-order set theories</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/talks/2018/01/03/the-emerging-zoo-of-second-order-set-theories.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The emerging zoo of second-order set theories" /><published>2018-01-03T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2018-01-03T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/talks/2018/01/03/the-emerging-zoo-of-second-order-set-theories</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/talks/2018/01/03/the-emerging-zoo-of-second-order-set-theories.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uni-konstanz.de/en/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Young Researchers' Workshop: Forcing and Philosophy&lt;/a&gt;, University of Konstanz, January 18, 2018.&lt;br&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;files/SecondOrderSetTheory.pdf&quot;&gt;Slides&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/konstanz.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:left; padding: 10px;&quot; /&gt;
In set theory, classes are collections of sets which are ``too large&quot; to be sets themselves. More formally, a &lt;em&gt;class&lt;/em&gt;, in a model of first-order set theory, is a definable (with parameters) collection of sets. Classes play an important role in modern set theory. Class forcing can make global changes to a universe of set theory, such as making the ${\rm GCH}$ fail at all regular cardinals. Large cardinals imply the existence of class elementary embeddings $j:V\to M$ from the universe into a transitive class submodel. Inner model theory studies canonical &lt;em&gt;inner models&lt;/em&gt; (transitive class submodels containing all the ordinals).

&lt;p&gt;The restriction to the study of only the definable large collections of sets is a limitation of first-order set theory which prevents us from exploring some natural properties of set-theoretic universes. For instance, consider the long standing open question whether Reinhardt cardinals are consistent with ${\rm ZF}$, which has been revisited only a few days ago in &lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/abs/1712.09678&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;this article&lt;/a&gt;. The &lt;em&gt;Reinhardt cardinal&lt;/em&gt; is the critical point of an elementary embedding $j:V\to V$. It is not difficult to show that there cannot be a definable elementary $j:V\to V$ in a model of ${\rm ZF}$, so the open question is about the existence of an undefinable such embedding. Other recent examples of the use of general classes comes from the study of inner model reflection principles. Motivated by a question of Neil Barton, Barton, Caicedo, Fuchs, Hamkins, and Reitz recently introduced and studied the &lt;em&gt;Inner Model Reflection Principle&lt;/em&gt; stating that every first-order formula reflects to a proper inner model &lt;a href=&quot;#BartonCaicedoFuchsHamkinsReitz:Inner-model-reflection-principles&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. The statement of the principle cannot be expressed in first-order set theory because it requires quantifying over classes. Along similar lines, Friedman had previously introduced the &lt;em&gt;Inner Model Hypothesis&lt;/em&gt; which states that if a first-order sentence holds in an outer model (extension universe) of an inner model, then it already holds in some inner model &lt;a href=&quot;#Friedman2006:InternalConsistencyAndIMH&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. For a long time it was not clear in what framework this principle could be formalized because it requires not only quantifying over classes but also referring to classes that are potentially outside the universe itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how do we undertake a general study of classes? What is the framework in which we can have undefinable classes and where we can study the properties of classes in the same way we study sets? This framework is second-order set theory, formalized in a two-sorted logic with separate objects and quantifiers for sets and classes. Models of second-order set theory are triples $\mathscr V=\langle V,\in,\mathcal C\rangle$ where $\mathcal C$ is the collection of classes of $\mathscr V$. One of the weakest reasonable axiomatizations of second-order theory is the Gödel-Bernays set theory ${\rm GBC}$ whose axioms consist of the ${\rm ZFC}$ axioms for sets, extensionality, replacement, and existence of global well-order axioms for classes, together with a weak comprehension scheme stating that every first-order formula defines a class. If a universe of set theory has a definable global well-order, then it together with its definable classes is a model of ${\rm GBC}$. Indeed, ${\rm GBC}$ is equiconsistent with ${\rm ZFC}$ and has the same first-order consequences as ${\rm ZFC}$. If we just add to ${\rm GBC}$ comprehension for $\Sigma^1_1$-formulas (formulas with a single class existential quantifier), we get a much stronger theory with many desirable properties. The theory ${\rm GBC}$ + $\Sigma^1_1$-Comprehension implies that that any two &lt;em&gt;meta-ordinals&lt;/em&gt; (class well-orders) are comparable, that we can iterate the $L$ construction along any meta-ordinal, that there is an iterated truth predicate along any meta-ordinal, that determinacy holds for open class games, and that the class forcing theorem holds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;em&gt;truth predicate&lt;/em&gt; is a class of Gödel codes of first-order formulas obeying Tarskian truth conditions. Tarski's Theorem on the undefinablity of truth implies that a truth predicate cannot be definable and therefore ${\rm GBC}$, because it can have models with only the definable classes, cannot imply the existence of such a class. Indeed, the existence of a truth predicate class implies $\text{Con}({\rm ZFC})$, $\text{Con}(\text{Con}({\rm ZFC}))$ and much more. ${\rm GBC}$ + $\Sigma^1_1$-Comprehension implies that there is a truth predicate for every structure $\langle V,\in, A\rangle$ for a class $A$. In particular, if $T_0$ is the truth predicate (for $\langle V,\in,A\rangle$), then we have a truth predicate $T_1$ for the structure $\langle V,\in, T_0,A\rangle$, that is we have truth for truth. How far can we iterate the truth operation? ${\rm GBC}$ + $\Sigma^1_1$-Comprehension implies that we get an iterated truth predicate along any meta-ordinal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By analogy with games on $X^\omega$, for a set $X$, where the players take turns playing elements from $X$ for $\omega$-many steps, in the second-order context we can consider games on ${\rm ORD}^\omega$. It turns out ${\rm GBC}$ + $\Sigma^1_1$-Comprehension implies determinacy for all such open class games &lt;a href=&quot;#GitmanHamkins:OpenDeterminacyForClassGames&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The strength of the forcing construction comes from the &lt;em&gt;Forcing Theorem&lt;/em&gt; which states that the forcing relation (for a fixed first-order formula) is definable. The analogue of the Forcing Theorem for class partial orders says that the forcing relation (for a fixed first-order formula) is a class. The &lt;em&gt;Class Forcing Theorem&lt;/em&gt; can fail in a model of ${\rm GBC}$ because there are class forcing notions from whose forcing relation for atomic formulas we can define a truth predicate. But ${\rm GBC}$ + $\Sigma^1_1$-Comprehension implies the Class Forcing Theorem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, in ${\rm GBC}$ + $\Sigma^1_1$-Comprehension, we can even formalize Friedman's Inner Model Hypothesis because the properties of outer models can be expressed via a strong logic, called $V$-logic, whose proof system is expressible in this theory &lt;a href=&quot;#AntosBartonFriedman:VLogic&quot;&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Indeed, it turns out that most of these principles are implied by a weaker natural theory ${\rm GBC}$ + ${\rm ETR}$ elementary transfinite recursion. The principle ${\rm ETR}$, which is an analogue of the Recursion Theorem in first-order set theory, states that every first-order definable recursion along a meta-ordinal has a solution. The principle ${\rm ETR}$ implies over ${\rm GBC}$ that we can iterate the $L$ construction along any meta-ordinal. Over ${\rm GBC}$, the principle ${\rm ETR}$ is equivalent to determinacy for clopen class games and to the existence of an iterated truth predicate along any meta-ordinal &lt;a href=&quot;#GitmanHamkins:OpenDeterminacyForClassGames&quot;&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;. The Class Forcing Theorem is equivalent over ${\rm GBC}$, to the principle $\rm {ETR}_{\rm {ORD}}$, stating that we can perform recursions along ${\rm ORD}$ &lt;a href=&quot;#GitmanHamkinsHolySchlichtWilliams:ForcingTheorem&quot;&gt;[5]&lt;/a&gt;. The amount of available ${\rm ETR}$ gives a natural hierarchy of second-order set theories above ${\rm GBC}$ with ${\rm ETR}_\omega$ already implying the existence of a truth predicate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only principle we have considered so far which is known to be stronger than ${\rm ETR}$ is open determinacy, a result due to Sato &lt;a href=&quot;#Sato:determinacy&quot;&gt;[6]&lt;/a&gt;. Hamkins and Woodin showed recently that open determinacy implies that forcing does not add meta-ordinals, a natural analogue to the statement that forcing does not add ordinals (personal communication).

&lt;p&gt;Of course, the amount of available comprehension itself gives a hierarchy of second-order set theories culminating with the Kelley-Morse set theory ${\rm KM}$, which consists of ${\rm GBC}$ together with the full comprehension scheme for all second-order formulas. Beyond ${\rm KM}$ are theories which include choice principles for classes, such as the &lt;em&gt;choice scheme&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;dependent choice scheme&lt;/em&gt;. These theories have the advantage of bi-interpretability with extensions of the well-understood first-order set theory ${\rm ZFC}^-_I$ (${\rm ZFC}$ without powerset and with the existence of the largest cardinal which is inaccessible). An even stronger principle, which endows classes with more set-like properties, is the existence of a canonically definable well-order of the classes. The existence of a definable well-ordering on classes makes it possible, for instance, to carry out the Boolean valued model forcing construction for class forcing notions (work in progress with Carolin Antos and Sy-David Friedman).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are there natural second-order set-theoretic principles between ${\rm GBC}$ + $\Sigma^1_1$-comprehension and ${\rm KM}?$ What natural principles lie beyond ${\rm KM}$ together with the choice scheme and the dependent choice scheme? &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;BartonCaicedoFuchsHamkinsReitz:Inner-model-reflection-principles&quot;&gt;N. Barton, A. E. Caicedo, G. Fuchs, J. D. Hamkins, and J. Reitz, “Inner-model reflection principles,” &lt;i&gt;ArXiv e-prints&lt;/i&gt;, 2017. Available at: http://jdh.hamkins.org/inner-model-reflection-principles&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Friedman2006:InternalConsistencyAndIMH&quot;&gt;S.-D. Friedman, “Internal consistency and the inner model hypothesis,” &lt;i&gt;Bull. Symbolic Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 12, no. 4, pp. 591–600, 2006. Available at: http://projecteuclid.org/getRecord?id=euclid.bsl/1164056808&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;GitmanHamkins:OpenDeterminacyForClassGames&quot;&gt;V. Gitman and J. D. Hamkins, “Open determinacy for class games,” in &lt;i&gt;Foundations of mathematics&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 690, Amer. Math. Soc., Providence, RI, 2017, pp. 121–143. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;AntosBartonFriedman:VLogic&quot;&gt;N. Barton, C. Antos, and S.-D. Friedman, “Universism and extensions of V,” &lt;i&gt;ArXiv e-prints&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;GitmanHamkinsHolySchlichtWilliams:ForcingTheorem&quot;&gt;V. Gitman, J. D. Hamkins, P. Holy, P. Schlicht, and K. Williams, “The exact strength of the class forcing theorem,” &lt;i&gt;Submitted&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;Sato:determinacy&quot;&gt;K. Sato, “Inductive dichotomy: separation of open and clopen class determinacies.” &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/vika_konstanz4.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;figure&quot;&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/vika_konstanz1.jpg&quot; /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the Young Researchers' Workshop: Forcing and Philosophy, University of Konstanz, January 18, 2018.Slides</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Virtual large cardinal principles</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/talks/2017/10/12/virtual-large-cardinal-principles.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Virtual large cardinal principles" /><published>2017-10-12T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-10-12T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/talks/2017/10/12/virtual-large-cardinal-principles</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/talks/2017/10/12/virtual-large-cardinal-principles.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the &lt;a href=&quot;http://logic.harvard.edu/colloquium.php&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Harvard Logic Colloquium&lt;/a&gt;, Cambridge, November 8, 2017.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;img src=&quot;/images/harvard.jpg&quot; style=&quot;float:left; padding: 10px;&quot; /&gt;

&lt;strong&gt;Abstract&lt;/strong&gt;: 
Given a set-theoretic property $\mathcal P$ characterized by the existence of elementary embeddings between some first-order structures, let's say that $\mathcal P$ holds &lt;em&gt;virtually&lt;/em&gt; if the embeddings between structures from $V$ characterizing $\mathcal P$ exist somewhere in the generic multiverse. We showed with Schindler that virtual versions of supercompact, $C^{(n)}$-extendible, $n$-huge and rank-into-rank cardinals form a large cardinal hierarchy consistent with $V=L$. Included in the hierarchy are virtual versions of inconsistent large cardinal notions such as the existence of an elementary embedding $j:V_\lambda\to V_\lambda$ for $\lambda$ much larger than the supremum of the critical sequence. The Silver indiscernibles, under $0^\sharp$, which have a number of large cardinal properties in $L$, are also natural examples of virtual large cardinals.   Virtual versions of forcing axioms, including ${\rm PFA}$, ${\rm SCFA}$, and resurrection axioms, have been studied by Schindler and Fuchs, who showed that they are equiconsistent with virtual large cardinals. We showed with Bagaria and Schindler that the virtual version of Vopěnka's  Principle is consistent with $V=L$. Bagaria had showed that Vopěnka's  Principle holds if and only if the universe has a proper class of $C^{(n)}$-extendible cardinals for every $n\in\omega$. We almost generalized his result by showing that the virtual version is equiconsistent with the existence, for every $n\in\omega$, of a proper class of virtually $C^{(n)}$-extendible cardinals. With Hamkins we showed that Bagaria's result cannot generalize by constructing a model of virtual Vopěnka's  Principle in which there are no virtually extendible cardinals. The difference arises from the failure of Kunen's Inconsistency in the virtual setting. In the talk, I will discuss a mixture of results about the virtual large cardinal hierarchy and virtual Vopěnka's  Principle.</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the Harvard Logic Colloquium, Cambridge, November 8, 2017.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Filter games and Ramsey-like cardinals</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/talks/2017/09/27/filter-games-and-ramsey-like-cardinals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Filter games and Ramsey-like cardinals" /><published>2017-09-27T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2017-09-27T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/talks/2017/09/27/filter-games-and-ramsey-like-cardinals</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/talks/2017/09/27/filter-games-and-ramsey-like-cardinals.html">&lt;p&gt;This is a talk at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://boolesrings.org/victoriagitman/cuny-logic-seminars/cuny-set-theory-seminar/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CUNY Set Theory Seminar&lt;/a&gt;, October 20, 2017.&lt;!--more--&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Peter Holy and Philipp Schlicht recently introduced a robust hierarchy of Ramsey-like cardinals $\kappa$ using games in which player I plays an increasing sequence of $\kappa$-models and player II responds by playing an increasing sequence of $M$-ultrafilters for some cardinal $\alpha\leq\kappa$ many steps, with player II winning if she is able to continue finding the required filters &lt;a href=&quot;#HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. The entire hierarchy sits below a measurable cardinal and intertwines with Ramsey cardinals, as well as the Ramsey-like cardinals I introduced in &lt;a href=&quot;#gitman:ramsey&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. The cardinals in the hierarchy can also be defined by the existence of the kinds of elementary embeddings characterizing Ramsey cardinals and other cardinals in that neighborhood. Before getting to their hierarchy and the filter games, we need some background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Large cardinals $\kappa$ below a measurable cardinal tend to be characterized by the existence of certain elementary embeddings of weak $\kappa$-models or $\kappa$-models. A &lt;em&gt;weak $\kappa$-model&lt;/em&gt; is a transitive model of ${\rm ZFC}^-$ of size $\kappa$ and height above $\kappa$, which we should think of as a mini-universe of set theory; a $\kappa$-model is additionally closed under $\lt\kappa$-sequences. Given a weak $\kappa$-model $M$, we call $U\subseteq P(\kappa)\cap M$ an $M$-&lt;em&gt;ultrafilter&lt;/em&gt; if the structure $\langle M,\in, U\rangle$ satisfies that $U$ is a normal ultrafilter. (Note that since an $M$-ultrafilter is only $\lt\kappa$-complete for sequences from $M$, the ultrapower by it need not be well-founded.) Obviously, if the ultrapower of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ by an $M$-ultrafilter on $\kappa$ is well-founded, then we get an elementary embedding of $M$ into a transitive model $N$, and conversely if there is an elementary embedding $j:M\to N$ with $N$ transitive and critical point $\kappa$, then $U=\{A\in M\mid A\subseteq\kappa\text{ and }\kappa\in j(A)\}$ is an $M$-ultrafilter with a well-founded ultrapower. These types of elementary embeddings characterize, for instance, weakly compact cardinals. If $\kappa^{\lt\kappa}=\kappa$, then $\kappa$ is weakly compact whenever every $\kappa$-model has an $M$-ultrafilter on $\kappa$ (and hence a well-founded ultrapower).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An $M$-ultrafilter $U$, for a weak $\kappa$-model $M$, is called &lt;em&gt;weakly amenable&lt;/em&gt; if for every $X\in M$, which $M$ thinks has size $\kappa$, $X\cap U\in M$. Because a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter is partially internal to $M$, we are able to define its iterates and iterate the ultrapower construction as we would do with a measure on $\kappa$. If $j:M\to N$ is the ultrapower by a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter on $\kappa$, then $M$ and $N$ have the same subsets of $\kappa$, and conversely if $M$ and $N$ have the same subsets of $\kappa$ and $j:M\to N$ is an elementary embedding with critical point $\kappa$, then the induced $M$-ultrafilter is weakly amenable. In a striking contrast with the characterization of weakly compact cardinals, it is inconsistent to assume that &lt;em&gt;every&lt;/em&gt; $\kappa$-model $M$ has a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter! Looking at this from the perspective of the corresponding elementary embeddings $j:M\to N$, this happens because there is too much reflection between $M$ and $N$ for objects of size $\kappa$. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The existence of weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilters for some weak $\kappa$-models characterizes Ramsey cardinals. A cardinal $\kappa$ is Ramsey whenever every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ which has a weakly amenable countably complete $M$-ultrafilter. If we assume that every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a $\kappa$-model $M$ which has such an $M$-ultrafilter, then we get a stronger large cardinal notion, the &lt;em&gt;strongly Ramsey&lt;/em&gt; cardinal. If we further assume that every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a $\kappa$-model $M\prec H_{\kappa^+}$ for which there is such an $M$-ultrafilter, then we get an even stronger notion, the &lt;em&gt;super Ramsey&lt;/em&gt; cardinal. Both notions are still weaker than a measurable cardinal. If we instead weaken our requirements and assume that every $A\subseteq\kappa$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model for which there is a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter with a well-founded ultrapower, we get a &lt;em&gt;weakly Ramsey&lt;/em&gt; cardinal, which sits between ineffable and Ramsey cardinals. I introduced these notions and showed that a super Ramsey cardinal is a limit of strongly Ramsey cardinals, which is in turn a limit of Ramsey cardinals, which is in turn a limit of weakly Ramsey cardinals, which is in turn a limit of completely ineffable cardinals &lt;a href=&quot;#gitman:ramsey&quot;&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. I also called weakly Ramsey cardinals &lt;em&gt;$1$-iterable&lt;/em&gt; because they are the first step in a hierarchy of &lt;em&gt;$\alpha$-iterable&lt;/em&gt; cardinals for $\alpha\leq\omega_1$, which all sit below a Ramsey cardinal (see [bibcite key=gitman:welch] for definitions and properties). What happens if we consider intermediate versions between Ramsey and strongly Ramsey cardinals where we stratify the closure on the model $M$, considering models with $M^\alpha\subseteq M$ for cardinals $\alpha&lt;\kappa$? What happens if we consider models $M\prec H_\theta$ for large $\theta$ and not just models $M\prec H_{\kappa^+}$?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Obviously we cannot have a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ elementary in $H_\theta$ for $\theta&gt;\kappa^+$. So let's drop the requirement of transitivity from the definition of a weak $\kappa$-model, but only require that $\kappa+1\subseteq M$. Now it makes sense to ask for a weak $\kappa$-model $M\prec H_\theta$ for arbitrarily large $\theta$. Suppose $\alpha\leq\kappa$ is a regular cardinal. Holy and Schlicht defined that $\kappa$ is &lt;em&gt;$\alpha$-Ramsey&lt;/em&gt; if for every $A\subseteq\kappa$ and arbitrarily large regular $\theta&gt;\kappa$, there is a weak $\kappa$-model $M\prec H_\theta$, closed under $\lt\alpha$-sequences, with $A\in M$ for which there is a weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilter on $\kappa$ (in the lone case $\alpha=\omega$, add that the ultrapower must be well-founded) &lt;a href=&quot;#HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. It is not difficult to see that it is equivalent to require that the models exist for &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; regular $\theta&gt;\kappa$. Also, for a fixed $\theta$, it suffices to have a single such weak $\kappa$-model $M\prec H_\theta$, meaning that the requirement that every $A$ is an element of such a model is superfluous. An $\omega$-Ramsey cardinal is a limit of weakly Ramsey cardinals, and I showed that it is weaker than a 2-iterable cardinal, and hence much weaker than a Ramsey cardinal. An $\omega_1$-Ramsey cardinal is a limit of Ramsey cardinals. A $\kappa$-Ramsey cardinal is a limit of super Ramsey cardinals. I will say where the strongly Ramsey cardinals fit in below. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It turns out that the $\alpha$-Ramsey cardinals have a game theoretic characterization! To motivate it, let's consider the following natural strengthening of the characterization of weakly compact cardinals. Suppose that whenever $M$ is a weak $\kappa$-model, $F$ is an $M$-ultrafilter and $N$ is another weak $\kappa$-model extending $M$, then we can find an $N$-ultrafilter $\bar F\supseteq F$. What is the strength of this property? I showed that it is inconsistent. Roughly, it implies the existence of too many weakly amenable $M$-ultrafilters, which we already saw leads to inconsistency (see &lt;a href=&quot;#HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt; for proof). So here is instead a game version of extending models and filters formulated by Holy and Schlicht.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let us say that a &lt;em&gt;filter&lt;/em&gt; is any subset of $P(\kappa)$ with the property that the intersection of any finite number of its elements has size $\kappa$. We will say that a filter $F$ &lt;em&gt;measures&lt;/em&gt; $A\subseteq \kappa$ if $A\in F$ or $\kappa\setminus A\in F$ and we will say that $F$ &lt;em&gt;measures&lt;/em&gt; $X\subseteq P(\kappa)$ if $F$ measures all $A\in X$. If $M$ is a weak $\kappa$-model, we will say that a filter $F$ is &lt;em&gt;$M$-normal&lt;/em&gt; if $F\cap M$ is an $M$-ultrafilter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Suppose $\kappa$ is weakly compact. Given an ordinal $\alpha\leq\kappa^+$ and a regular $\theta&gt;\kappa$, consider the following two-player game of perfect information $G^\theta_\alpha(\kappa)$. Two players, the &lt;em&gt;challenger&lt;/em&gt; and the &lt;em&gt;judge&lt;/em&gt;, take turns to play $\subseteq$-increasing sequences $\langle M_\gamma\mid \gamma&lt;\alpha\rangle$ of $\kappa$-models, and $\langle F_\gamma\mid\gamma&lt;\alpha\rangle$ of filters on $\kappa$, such that the following hold for every $\gamma&lt;\alpha$.
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt; The challenger plays $M_\gamma\prec H_\theta$, and then the judge plays a filter $F_\gamma$ on $\kappa$ that measures $P(\kappa)\cap M_\gamma$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt; $\langle M_{\bar\gamma}\mid \bar\gamma&lt;\gamma\rangle,\,\langle F_{\bar \gamma}\cap M_{\bar\gamma}\mid\bar\gamma&lt;\gamma\rangle\in M_\gamma$.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
Let $M_\alpha=\bigcup_{\gamma&lt;\alpha}M_\gamma$ and $F_\alpha=\bigcup_{\gamma&lt;\alpha}F_\gamma$. If $F_\alpha$ is a $M_\alpha$-normal filter, then the judge wins, and otherwise the challenger wins. Note that in order to have any hope of winning the judge must play a filter $F_\gamma$ at each stage such that $F_\gamma\cap M_\gamma$ is an $M_\gamma$-ultrafilter.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Holy and Schlicht showed that if the challenger has a winning strategy in $G^\theta_\alpha(\kappa)$ for a single $\theta$, then the challenger has a winning strategy for all $\theta$, and similarly for the judge. Thus, we will say that $\kappa$ has the &lt;em&gt;$\alpha$-filter property&lt;/em&gt; if the challenger has no winning strategy in the game $G^\theta_\alpha(\kappa)$ for some (all) regular $\theta&gt;\kappa$. &lt;a href=&quot;#HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Holy and Schlicht showed that for regular $\alpha&gt;\omega$, $\kappa$ has the $\alpha$-filter property if and only if $\kappa$ is $\alpha$-Ramsey! Using the game characterization, they showed that $\kappa$ is $\alpha$-Ramsey ($\alpha&gt;\omega$) if and only if every $A\in H_{2^{\kappa^+}}$ is an element of a weak $\kappa$-model $M\prec H_{2^{\kappa^+}}$, closed under $\lt\alpha$-sequences, for which there is an $M$-ultrafilter. [bibcite key=HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals] Thus, we actually only need a single $\theta=2^{\kappa^+}$! So instead of $H_{\kappa^+}$ as in the definition of super Ramsey cardinals, the natural stopping point is $H_{2^{\kappa^+}}$. With the new characterization, we can also show that a strongly Ramsey cardinal is a limit of $\alpha$-Ramsey cardinals for every $\alpha&lt;\kappa$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
So now we have in order of increasing strength: weakly Ramsey, $\omega$-Ramsey, $\alpha$-iterable for $2\leq\alpha\leq\omega_1$, Ramsey, $\alpha$-Ramsey for $\omega_1\leq\alpha&lt;\kappa$, strongly Ramsey, super Ramsey, $\kappa$-Ramsey, measurable.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why the restriction $\gamma&gt;\omega$? I showed that an $\omega$-Ramsey cardinal is a limit of cardinals with the $\omega$-filter property (see [bibcite key=HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals] for proof). The problem arises because even if the judge wins the game $G^\theta_\omega(\kappa)$, the ultrapower of $M_\omega$ by $F_\omega$ need not be well-founded. The same problem arises for any singular cardinal of cofinality $\omega$. The solution seems to be to consider a stronger version of the game for cardinals $\alpha$ of cofinality $\omega$, where it is required that the final filter $F_\alpha$ produces a well-founded ultrapower. Let's call this game $wfG^\theta_\alpha(\kappa)$. The well-founded games don't seem to behave as nicely as $G^\theta_\alpha(\kappa)$. For instance, it is not known whether having a winning strategy for a single $\theta$ is equivalent to having a winning strategy for all $\theta$. I conjecture that it is not the case. Still with the well-founded games, the arguments now generalize to show that $\kappa$ is $\omega$-Ramsey if and only if $\kappa$ has the well-founded $\omega$-filter property for every $\theta$.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Finally, what about $\alpha$-Ramsey cardinals for singular $\alpha$? Well, since a weak $\kappa$-model $M$ that is closed under $\lt\alpha$-sequences for a singular $\alpha$ is also closed under $\lt\alpha^+$-sequences, $\alpha$-Ramsey for a singular $\alpha$ implies $\alpha^+$-Ramsey. So instead Holy and Schlicht defined that $\kappa$ is $\alpha$-Ramsey for a singular $\alpha$ if $\kappa$ has the well-founded $\alpha$-filter property (the well-founded part is only needed for $\alpha$ of cofinality $\omega$) &lt;a href=&quot;#HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;. Now we have the $\alpha$-Ramsey hierarchy for all cardinals $\alpha\leq\kappa$. Holy and Schlicht showed that this is a strict hierarchy of large cardinal notions: if $\kappa$ is $\alpha$-Ramsey and $\beta&lt;\alpha$, then $V_\kappa$ is a model of proper class many $\beta$-Ramsey cardinals, and moreover if $\beta$ is regular, then $\kappa$ is indeed a limit of $\beta$-Ramsey cardinals &lt;a href=&quot;#HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;References&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;bibliography&quot;&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;HolySchlicht:HierarchyRamseyLikeCardinals&quot;&gt;P. Holy and P. Schlicht, “A hierarchy of Ramsey-like cardinals.” &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span id=&quot;gitman:ramsey&quot;&gt;V. Gitman, “Ramsey-like cardinals,” &lt;i&gt;The Journal of Symbolic Logic&lt;/i&gt;, vol. 76, no. 2, pp. 519–540, 2011. Available at: http://dx.doi.org/10.2178/jsl/1305810762&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">This is a talk at the CUNY Set Theory Seminar, October 20, 2017.</summary></entry></feed>